<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> Welcome to CosmicVarta.</title>
    <description> Platform for promoting Indian astronomy research to the public.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 14:52:27 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 14:52:27 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Exploring the topology of hydrogen distribution in the early universe</title>
        <description>&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We study how galaxies and other sources in the early universe change the neutral universe or InterGalactic Medium (IGM) into the ionized one. We compare different kinds of source models and how they ionize the neutral universe which mainly consists of neutral hydrogen. We trace the largest ionized region formed by these sources by using a statistic known as the Largest Cluster Statistics (LCS). We found that LCS of different source models evolve differently and hence show different natures of ionizing photons or sources. We also investigate the geometry and topology of these ionized regions and how they are different for each model.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The universe on a very large scale seems like a web which we astronomers refer to as the cosmic web. Entities like galaxies and clusters of galaxies are trapped within this giant web (see figure 1). The unknown but the most abundant matter, dark matter, plays a governing role in shaping these giants by capitalizing the full potential of the most dominant force on a cosmic scale, gravitational force. We put our efforts to understand the formation and evolution of the universe including these giants by looking at the driving physics behind these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
 Figure 1: Image of the cosmic web. Figure shows the dark matter distribution (taken from the Millennium simulation). Here, every bright point represents a galaxy cluster. Image Credit: V.Springel, Max-Planck-Institut für Astrophysics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The universe has undergone a significant transition on a regular basis since its birth. Figure 2 shows the evolution of our universe from the Big Bang on the left hand side to the current local universe which we see today  on the right hand side of the plot. One of the major recent and remarkable phase transitions is the Epoch of Reionization (EoR), when the neutral Intergalactic Medium (IGM), mainly composed of neutral hydrogen, gets transformed into an ionized one. The galaxies residing within the dark matter halos (host of galaxies) act as one of the primary sources responsible for the reionization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Pictorial representation of the evolution of our Universe according to the standard cosmological model. Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://astrobites.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;astrobites&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to understand this era, we use several techniques and approaches to recreate the environment. We use analytic models (refer to  &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1209.2215&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;  Wyithe and Loeb 2012&lt;/a&gt;), semi-analytic models (refer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1512.00562&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;  Mutch et al 2016&lt;/a&gt;), semi-numerical models (refer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stv2812&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;  Majumdar et al. 2016&lt;/a&gt; ), etc., to understand the EoR and to comply with what we observe from large surveys conducted using advanced telescopes that are increasingly more sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is evident that different sources during EoR emit different kinds of ionizing photons, and hence, ionize the IGM in a different way. In our analysis, we investigate this era by focusing on the properties of some of these possible sources which can ionize the IGM. We consider six reionization source models based on the semi-numerical method originally proposed in &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stv2812&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;  Majumdar et al. 2016&lt;/a&gt;. These source models differ from each other in two main aspects: a) how the number of ionizing photons emitted by the sources are related to their host halo mass i.e. Nphotons ∝ (Mhalo)n and b) how the rest frame energy of the ionizing photons is distributed. The different source models considered in our work are mentioned in the table below. The Uniform Ionizing Background (UIB) dominated source model emits hard X-ray photons having large mean free path and hence creates a uniform ionizing background. The Soft X-Ray (SXR) dominated source model emits soft X-ray photons having limited mean free path. Source models like Fiducial (assumes 100% contribution of UV rays coming out from the galaxies residing inside the dark-matter halos) and Power Law (PL) (n=3) differ from each other in terms of the number of ionizing photons they emit following the relation shown in point (a) above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Reionization models&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Ultraviolet photons (UV)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Uniform Ionizing Background (UIB)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Soft X-Ray photons (SXR)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Power Law (PL), (n)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Fiducial&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;100 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Clumping&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;100 % and Non Uniform Recombination&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;UIB Dominated&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;80%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;SXR Dominated&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;80%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;UV + SXR + UIB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;50%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;PL (n=3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reionization scenario like clumping model shows an extreme reionization case considering the clumpiness of the density field and emits ultraviolet (UV) photons. On the other hand, UV + SXR + UIB source model shows a combined contribution of UV photons, hard X-ray photons and soft X-ray photons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We investigate how the ionized regions formed by these sources evolve with redshift and what geometrical or topological information we can grab from their evolution by looking at their shape and size. One can use Minkowski functionals (a set of four functionals which gives information about the geometrical and topological distribution of matter in the universe) (for example,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/sty714&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bag et al. 2018&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/9312028&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mecke et al. 1994&lt;/a&gt;) to define the morphology of an object. In our work, we specifically use this to define the shape and size of our object (ionized region in our case). We use an algorithm called SURFGEN2 which identifies ionized regions from the density field and informs about their shape and size in the form of three Shapefinders (namely, thickness, breadth and length).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at these ionized regions, with time, different reionization source models forming these ionized regions grow in size as well as in numbers, which then start to overlap. At some point in time, they coalesce together and form a single large connected ionized region as one can notice from the middle and right panels in the figure 3. This transition phase is known as the percolation transition (one can look at the articles &lt;a href=&quot;https://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/pdf/1993ApJ...413...48K&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Klypin and Shandarin 1993&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/pdf/1996ApJ...465....2Y&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Capp Yess and Shandarin 1996&lt;/a&gt;).  In our analysis, out of many ionized regions, we primarily focus on the largest ionized region and its evolution around the percolation. We use the Largest Cluster Statistics (LCS) which is defined as the ratio of the volume of the largest ionized region to that volume of all ionized regions in a simulation volume to trace the largest ionized region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;

LCS = Volume of Largest Ionized Region / Volume of all ionized region 

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before percolation we have a very small largest ionized region but as we reach percolation and after percolation, the ionized region increases drastically, and at the end of reionization, almost the entire simulation box is filled with the largest ionized region as evident from the figure 3 as we go from left to right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Figure shows the transition of the largest ionized region from smaller size before percolation to the size of the entire simulation box after percolation. Middle panel shows the onset of percolation. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the reionization progresses, the neutral hydrogen present in the IGM ionizes and eventually the entire IGM converts into an ionized one at the end of the reionization. The neutral fraction (x&lt;sub&gt;HI&lt;/sub&gt;) informs about the amount of neutral hydrogen present in a volume with respect to the entire hydrogen species including both neutral and ionized one at any time. In our analysis, we use this quantity to see the evolution of LCS and shapefinders which we discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;evolution-of-largest-cluster-statistics&quot;&gt;Evolution of Largest Cluster Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest ionized region evolves differently for different reionization source models. The point of percolation is also different for different models. The inside-out scenarios where the reionization starts from the denser part of the IGM and then proceeds to the less dense part, the percolation occurs at much higher neutral fraction as compared to its counterpart, the outside-in scenario, where reionization starts from less dense regions and then the high-dense region is covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 4 shows the variation of Largest Cluster Statistics (LCS) with the neutral fraction and Filling Factor (FF) for different reionization models. Here, Filling Factor is defined as the ratio of volume of all ionized regions to volume of our simulation box. One can notice from the left panel that the largest ionized region or LCS before percolation (shown by vertical lines) is significantly small for all reionization models but at the onset of percolation and after percolation, an abrupt increment in LCS can be observed. This result is quite obvious because as the reionization progresses, different ionized regions grow and interconnect with each other and hence form a single interconnected ionized region which is true for all reionization models as one can notice from the figure. Hence, before percolation, when we have a very small largest ionized region, it is indistinguishable from other ionized regions but as we reach percolation, they interconnect and become quite distinguishable. It depicts how the neutral IGM slowly transformed into an ionized one when the ionized bubbles got enough time to develop. However, percolation for different models occurs at different neutral fractions. The inside-out reionization models percolate at higher neutral fraction (shown by solid lines) whereas the outside-in reionization models percolate at lower neutral fraction. At the end of reionization, we can observe a single large ionized region occupying the entire simulation volume as is evident from the right panel of figure 4, where LCS is close to unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: The percolation transition has been compared for all six reionization models in terms of LCS. The left panel shows the LCS as a function of neutral fraction (x&lt;sub&gt;HI&lt;/sub&gt;) whereas the right panel illustrates how LCS evolves with FF for the different reionization scenarios. In both panels, the vertical lines represent the percolation transitions in the reionization models with corresponding colors. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, we can say that following the LCS along with the percolation, we can distinguish between the two broad categories of reionization models i.e, inside-out and outside-in reionization models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shape-of-largest-ionized-region&quot;&gt;Shape of Largest Ionized Region&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ionized bubbles formed by different sources, in principle, can be of complicated shape or geometry as they grow. For ease of understanding, one can use a simple geometrical or topological approach for the same. The Shapefinder technique uses Minkowski functionals to unveil the shape and size of the ionized region. The four Minkowski functions for a closed 2-D surface are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volume enclosed, V:&lt;/strong&gt; Informs about the enclosed volume within the surface of an object or ionized region.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surface area, S:&lt;/strong&gt;  Informs about the surface area of the object.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrated Mean Curvature (C):&lt;/strong&gt; Informs about the concavity or convexity of the surface or in other words principal curvature (or radius of curvature) of the surface.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaussian Mean Curvature (Euler Characteristics):&lt;/strong&gt; Informs about the topological properties of an object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shapefinders are expressed as the ratio of these Minkowski functionals to assess the shape of an object. In 3-D, the three shapefinders are :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thickness: T&lt;/strong&gt;  = 3V/S&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breadth: B&lt;/strong&gt; = S/C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Length: L&lt;/strong&gt; = C/4π&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These three are the good measures of the extension of an object in 3-dimension. We can further use these shapefinders to determine the morphology of an object by means of these two dimensionless quantities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planarity: P&lt;/strong&gt; = (B-T) / (B+T)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filamentarity: F&lt;/strong&gt; = (L-B) / (L+B)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We employ these aforementioned techniques to see how the geometry or topology of the largest ionized region evolves with the redshift. An ionized region can be expressed in terms of its length, breadth and thickness, which are the three Shapefinders mentioned earlier. We show the variation of cross-section and length with the neutral fraction in figure 5. We can observe that the cross-section of the largest ionized region for all reionization scenarios in the left panel remains almost constant with the variation in neutral fraction. Whereas, in the right panel, its length increases several orders of magnitude as the reionization progresses. Hence, one can robustly confirm the fact that as the reionization progresses, the topology of the largest ionized region becomes filamentary, as one can notice in figure 6 where the filamentarity (shown by thick line curves) has a larger value than the planarity (thin line curves) for all reionization scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 5: This figure illustrates the evolution of the shape of the largest ionized region (LIR) for the five reionization scenarios (excluding the clumping model since this is the only scenario where extreme reionization is considered and hence it’s shapefinders behave differently) near the respective percolation transitions. The left and right panels show the variation of cross-section (estimated by T x B) and the length (L) of the LIR on the y-axis against the neutral fractions on the x-axis. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image6.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 6: Planarity and filamentarity of the largest ionized region in different models have been compared near the respective percolation transitions. The solid and dashed curves represent the reionization models following inside-out and outside-in reionizations respectively. The thick line curves (solid and dashed) represent the filamentarity and thin line curves represent the planarity of the largest ionized region in different models.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also observe that as the reionization progresses, the largest ionized regions in all the scenarios become more multi-connected as their genus (in simple words, for any surface, it represents the number of holes present in the surface and hence informs about the multi-connected regions) increases. Thus, from our findings, we can conclude that at the later stage of reionization, we observe multi-connected filamentary structures for all reionization models. We found that the reionization model, like the clumping model, which follows extreme reionization, can be distinguished or separated quite easily by the Shapefinder technique. We crudely estimate the uncertainties by dividing each original simulation volume into eight smaller sub-volumes followed by estimating the variance of various quantities from these sub-volumes. Our research group at IIT Indore is currently working on noise which we get from the observations and the impact of primary beams on LCS analysis of the 21-cm signal considering the upcoming low-frequency Square Kilometer Array (SKA1-low) observations using a realistic simulations for such observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We consider the evolution of the largest ionized region by using a statistic called LCS in order to distinguish between the different reionization models.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We found that LCS for all reionization models before percolation is quite small and hence indistinguishable, but it increases abruptly at the onset of percolation. However, different reionization models percolate at different neutral fractions. Hence, following the evolution of LCS along with the percolation can help to distinguish between different models, and especially the inside-out or out-side- in models.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also find that the cross-section of the largest ionized region in all the scenarios (except for the clumping model) remains stable at the percolation transition when the largest ionized region abruptly grows, mostly in terms of its third Shapefinder – ‘length.’ The genus of the largest ionized region also increases as reionization progresses. Hence, multi-connected filamentary structure is observed at a later stage of EoR.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1088/1475-7516/2022/11/027&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Distinguishing reionization models using the largest cluster statistics of the 21-cm maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Aadarsh Pathak&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Satadru Bag, Saswata Dasgupta, Suman Majumdar, Rajesh Mondal, Prakash Sarkar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Department of Astronomy, Astrophysics &amp;amp; Space Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Indore, Indore, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh</guid>
        
        <category>Cosmology</category>
        
        <category>Epoch of Reionization</category>
        
        <category>Largest Cluster Statistics</category>
        
        <category>Percolation</category>
        
        
        <category>Cosmology and Nongalactic Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Astrophysical autopsy of a cosmic demise</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As the saying goes, “न कंचित् शाश्वतम्” (lit. Nothing is permanent), and hence the nature of this universe. The ever-evolving twinkles in the starry night are also non-discriminate towards this concept. If a star is born, it ought to die. Supernovae  are cosmic fireworks that do not require any occasion (e.g., New Year or winning a football world cup!) to explode. This explosion is the terminal stage of stellar evolution. Therefore, we can say that supernova is the death of a star that sends a siren to the universe in the form of gravitational waves to radio emissions (one of the best candidates for multi-messenger astronomy).  We study one such demise in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: OpenAI’s DALL.E 2 rendering of a core-collapse supernova [Generated by author]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supernovae (SNe) have fascinated humankind since time immemorial with recorded events millennia ago. Many essential elements that are part of us also resulted from such explosions. It is imperative to understand these events in detail and try to ascertain their origins. SNe can be broadly classified as Type I and Type II on the basis of the absence and presence of hydrogen features in their spectra, which is unrelated to their explosion mechanisms (thermonuclear SN and Fe core-collapse SN). Apart from their use as independent distance indicators (Type Ia, Type II-P), they are part of various multi/interdisciplinary studies, viz. galactic chemical evolution, origins of various heavier elements, etc. The key question in supernova studies is ascertaining the progenitor, for which, at times, archival images are available through &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.stsci.edu/missions-and-data/hst&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hubble Space Telescope&lt;/a&gt;, but this is quite rare. There are other analytical solutions based on simplified physics related to the explosion and derived relations to estimate the explosion energy, pre-SN mass, ejecta mass, initial mass of progenitor star that exploded as SN, etc. crudely. But a more sophisticated way is to generate synthetic time evolution of flux ( light curves), and velocity evolution of ejecta, then try to match them with observations. Currently, 3D modeling is challenging and resource-hungry, and we rely on 1D hydrodynamical modeling using tools viz. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.mesastar.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Modules for Experiments in Stellar Astrophysics (MESA)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ascl.net/1108.013&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stella&lt;/a&gt;, and other open-source frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such explosion, SN 2020jfo, happened in the galaxy M61 [Figure 2], a stellar graveyard that has also hosted 8 SNe in the past century. In contrast, our Galaxy is due for even one for centuries! We carried out the observations extensively in the optical regime from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/?q=telescope_iao&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Himalayan Chandra Telescope&lt;/a&gt; situated at the Indian Astronomical Observatory, Hanle, UT of Ladakh. More than 25 epochs of multi-band photometry and spectroscopy covered the evolution of SN 2020jfo for about a year [Figure 3]. The observations were supplemented with data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/facilities/astronomical-telescopes/360cm-telescope&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Devasthal Optical Telescope&lt;/a&gt;, Nainital (Uttarakhand), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ztf.caltech.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Zwicky Transient Facility (ZTF)&lt;/a&gt; survey, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://swift.gsfc.nasa.gov/about_swift/uvot_desc.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Swift/UVOT&lt;/a&gt; data. SN 2020jfo, although a Type II-P (plateau) SN, did not fit in the classical definition of a plateau which is a constant luminosity phase in light curve evolution and typically lasts for about a hundred days. A deviation from the plateau was seen after 65 days putting it under one of the rare short plateau Type II SN. The SN explosion synthesizes many radioactive elements, primarily Nickel-56, that solely power its light curve in the late phase, estimated to be 0.033(6) solar mass. As the SN ejecta expands with time, we see the constituent inner layers of the progenitor as evident in spectral time evolution [Figure 3].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   Figure 2: The location of SN 2020jfo in the host galaxy M61 is shown. Orange boxes marked are the available SDSS spectra for the host. [Credits: &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac610b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Teja et al. 2022&lt;/a&gt;] 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plethora of information about ejecta, elements, and the ejecta velocity evolution could be obtained using spectra. Overall evolution is typical of Type II spectra, but we find ionized helium and rare stable nickel. Having these peculiarities, it warranted detailed studies and modeling to look for the origins of this supernova. With all the observational evidence, viz. compact progenitor, presence of stable nickel produced during stellar nucleosynthesis, and strength of nebular oxygen lines pointed towards a small mass progenitor, the present theoretical and modeling works hinted otherwise. Hence to ascertain this progenitor scenario, we employed hydrodynamical modeling of this event from the inception of the star to its death. Eventually, it defied the situation presented in some models regarding the high mass progenitors. It resulted from a lower-mass red supergiant star (RSG) going SN. Still, the mass loss mechanism with which the star lost its significant hydrogen layer is uncertain (the weighing is more towards the presence of a binary counterpart). We present the alternative scenario to the current understanding of short plateau supernova origins. We also obtained the non-detection in the radio light curve. Some of the key results obtained are as follows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh/image3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  Figure 3: Panchromatic photometric (above) and optical spectroscopic (below) observations spanning about a year for SN 2020jfo are shown here. [Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac610b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Teja et al. 2022&lt;/a&gt;] 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh/image5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  Figure 4: Model light curves obtained using the MESA+STELLA framework for various evolved progenitors are plotted along with the pseudo-bolometric light curve for SN 2020jfo. The figure in the inset shows the requirement to include CSM interaction to fit the observed light curve. [Adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac610b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Teja et al. 2022&lt;/a&gt;] 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SN 2020jfo peaked in the Bessell’s V photometric filter at an absolute magnitude of -17.4(4) mag; for comparison, the Sun has an absolute magnitude of +4.83 in the same filter, implying SN to be millions of times brighter than the Sun. From 1D hydrodynamical modeling, we found that the most plausible progenitor is an RSG with an initial mass about 12 times the mass of the Sun, a radius about 600 times the Sun’s radius, and a final pre-SN mass &amp;lt;6 solar mass. Using the nebular-phase (post plateau decline phase, which is majorly powered by radioactive nickel decay chain) spectrum, we estimated a progenitor of mass ∼12 solar mass in corroboration with modeled mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We concluded that It evolved in a relatively high-metallicity environment and shredded a significant amount of mass during its evolution. The presence of ionized Helium line, HV Hα feature, higher luminosity in contrast to slower velocity evolution, and the steeper decline in luminosity indicated the presence of circumstellar (CSM), which was corroborated in models [Figure 4]. A fraction of the solar mass of CSM spread across 40 AU was deduced for SN 2020jfo’s progenitor, possibly resulting from a high mass loss a few years before the collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of various night sky surveys, viz. ZTF , &lt;a href=&quot;https://atlas.fallingstar.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ATLAS (Asteroid Terrestrial-impact Last Alert System)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://asas-sn.osu.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ASAS-SN (All Sky Automated Survey for SuperNovae)&lt;/a&gt;, and upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lsst.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LSST (Legacy Survey of Space and Time)&lt;/a&gt;, there is a great boom in discovering the exotic transients, which challenge our understanding of these events. It is necessary to study these in detail using observations and modeling and, if possible, weed out any cases which are not deemed worthy as indicators of distance. With the growing sample of these events, it is possible there could be more classes to these SN than the given one, and hence these kinds of studies provide the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac610b/meta&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SN 2020jfo: A Short-plateau Type II Supernova from a Low-mass Progenitor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Rishabh Singh Teja&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Avinash Singh, D. K. Sahu, G. C. Anupama, Brajesh Kumar, and Nayana A. J.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru, 560034; India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh</guid>
        
        <category>Transients</category>
        
        <category>Supernova</category>
        
        <category>Observations</category>
        
        <category>Hydrodynamic Modelling</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Accounting for the presence of dust in galaxies</title>
        <description>&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dust is as ubiquitous in galaxies as are stars, gases and dark matter. Although dust forms less than 1% of the mass of the interstellar medium, its importance can be gauged from the fact that dust reprocesses more than half of a galaxy’s stellar emissions. It absorbs the stellar light emissions (at UV and optical wavelengths) and re-emits in the infrared range of the spectrum. For example, our Milky Way would have been doubly bright in the optical if no dust was present in its interstellar medium. This effect of dust gets best encapsulated by the dust attenuation curve of the galaxy, which gives the optical depth of the galaxy as a function of wavelength. Analyzing data for thousands (~17000) of local galaxies (z&amp;lt;0.3), we find that the dust attenuation properties of a galaxy are dependent on its structure, i.e., its internal distribution of stars and dust.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;less-formal-description&quot;&gt;Less Formal Description&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Accounting for the presence of dust in galaxies&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this work, we have found that the behavior or the effect of dust present inside a galaxybis according to its distribution with respect to various stellar populations. We will try to explain the context and the significance of this finding in this article. We would like to begin by reminding you that dust is as crucial a component of a galaxy and as omnipresent as stars, gas, and dark matter. Dust is mainly composed of carbon and silicates, where the size of a typical dust grain ranges from 0.01 to 1 micron. For comparison, this is about 2 orders of magnitude smaller than the dust we see on our furniture. The importance of dust can very well be gauged from the fact that it reprocesses more than half of the galaxy’s total stellar light. Stars, as we know, emit mainly from UV to near-IR. These photons interact with the dust particles, get scattered and absorbed, and dust then re-emits the light in the middle and far-IR region of the spectrum. For example, our Milky Way would have been doubly bright in the optical if dust was not present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/dust_in_galaxies_sonali/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: Due to the increased presence of birth clouds and the denser interstellar medium in spiral galaxies, both UV and optical stellar emissions encounter dust on a similar level. Thus, the slope of the attenuation curve is not steep in the UV-optical range for spiral galaxies. In contrast, in the case of elliptical galaxies, only UV emission from newly formed stars encounters dust from the circumambient birth cloud. Optical stellar emissions escape due to a decreased presence of birth clouds and the less dense interstellar medium. Thus, the slope of the attenuation curve is steep in the UV-optical range for elliptical galaxies.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that even though the dust has such a splendid effect on a galaxy’s stellar light, it constitutes a minuscule fraction of the galaxy’s total mass. Baryonic mass (i.e., non-dark matter mass)  is nearly 1/6th of the galaxy’s total mass. Of this baryonic mass, 1/6th is in the interstellar medium. And of the total mass in the interstellar medium, 99% is gas, and 1% is dust. There are various mechanisms through which dust is understood to get formed, transformed, and destroyed inside a galaxy. It is mainly expected to form during the asymptotic giant branch (AGB) phase of the stars. Recent evidence also suggests that it could have formed around supernovae. But the mystery is how dust would have survived the shockwave associated with supernovae. It has also been proposed that dust might get formed around supermassive black holes. It gets destroyed either through UV rays and also gets consumed in the formation of new stars being part of the giant molecular clouds. It plays a critical role in the cooling and coagulation of such clouds. What this conveys is that the cycle of dust is intricately linked with both the star formation history as well as the future star formation rate of a galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus accounting for the effect of dust is a primary requirement for any reasonable estimation of a galaxy’s stellar mass and star formation rate. This effect of dust is accounted for through the dust attenuation curve of a galaxy. It gives the attenuation or optical depth of a galaxy as a function of wavelength. It describes how a galaxy’s light is affected by dust at each wavelength. So a general attenuation curve peaks at far UV and becomes negligible by the time it reaches IR. These curves are used as an input in the computation of a galaxy’s stellar parameters. Their accurate knowledge is crucial for simulations, modeling, and data analysis, basically at all places where the aim is to understand the formation and evolution of galaxies. If we do not know the attenuation curve accurately, there’s no way we can distinguish between a young dusty galaxy and an old non-dusty one. In tracing the evolution of galaxies, one of the most intriguing things is that the star formation rate density of galaxies has fallen by a factor of 5 to 10 since redshift 2. This could have been both due to the decrease in star formation efficiency as well the decrease in gaseous material inside galaxies. To solve this puzzle, accurate attenuation curves have to be known for the observed galaxies over the entire redshift range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a lot of progress in the estimation of these curves. Improving over the comparison methods, model methods have been successful in deriving these curves individually for each galaxy. Here the basic idea is to obtain the best match spectrum or Spectral Energy Distribution (SED) for a galaxy out of 100 thousand SEDs created with a whole range of model parameters. A major advancement has occurred with the availability of mid and especially far-IR measurements. Thanks to that, total IR luminosity works as a constraint on the dust emission and allows the attenuation parameters to be fitted freely. This has led to more detailed attenuation parameters and, thus, more accurate stellar parameters. The observations in the far-IR for a large number of galaxies have mainly happened over the last decade with space-based telescopes, especially Herschel. This information will allow you to appreciate the sample that we have chosen for our study. Stripe 82 is a 220-square-degree patch in the Northern Hemisphere of the sky. It has been the focus of many deep multi-wavelength photometric and spectroscopic surveys. Thanks to that, it has the range of most accurate dust attenuation and structural and stellar parameters computed through various dedicated efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we have done is that we have used all this information to probe the dependence of the shape of the dust attenuation curve on all other galaxy properties. This kind of observational undertaking is possible now with the availability of all the defining galaxy parameters for a large sample of local galaxies. Deciphering the dependence of dust on other galaxy properties is fundamental in our pursuit of understanding the processes that have governed the growth of galaxies. There is growing evidence that galaxies with different morphology types have witnessed characteristically different evolutionary paths. For example, ellipticals are understood to form during major mergers, and discs might have formed later through accretion, minor mergers, and secular evolution. If we are able to quantify the difference in their dust content and attenuation properties, we can obtain more insight into the dominant physical processes. So we have a sample of nearly 17000 local galaxies, covering the entire mass range. We divide these galaxies based on their dominant structural component, that is, if majorly the galaxy has a spheroid or elliptical-like structure or if it’s mainly a disc-like structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This classification is achieved with the application of multiple stringent criteria that include the placement of galaxies on the projection of the fundamental plane and the value of their global Sersic index. The sersic index defines the shape of a galaxy’s light profile. Galaxies with dominant spheroid components will follow the tight fundamental plane relation observed for local ellipticals, while those with dominant disc components will be outliers to such a relation. Galaxies that didn’t comply with the stringent multiple criteria were kept separately so as not to contaminate the two classifications. We found that the normalized slope of the attenuation curve is markedly different for the two structural types. The curve is twice as shallow for discs as it is for spheroids (see Figure 2). However, for the whole group of a given structural type, the slope values are constrained within a narrow range. Thus the shape of the dust attenuation curve is dependent on the dominant mode of stellar mass distribution inside a galaxy. Similar to structure, the curve is nearly twice as shallow for star-forming galaxies as for passive galaxies. We divide the galaxies into star-forming and passive based on their placement on the main sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/dust_in_galaxies_sonali/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 2. The fractional distribution of various structural types of galaxies, i.e., spheroid-dominated (red), disc-dominated (blue), and the rest (green), is shown with respect to the normalized slope of their dust attenuation curves in UV (R FUV ). Discs exhibit shallower slopes than spheroids emphasizing the role of structure in determining dust properties.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dependence of the attenuation curve on star formation rate could be driven by the structure because discs are star-forming and spheroids are passive. But also, star-forming galaxies will have more dust clouds in addition to the diffuse interstellar medium. Either way, this adds to the evidence that the distribution of stars and dust inside a galaxy determines the curve properties. Another interesting thing to note is that the amount of dust is irrelevant to the shape. That’s why we see no correlation between the normalized shape and the total mass of the galaxy or the inclination of its disc component. Although more mass and higher inclination will result in the stellar light encountering more dust before reaching the observer, it doesn’t affect the shape of the curve. So, rather than the amount of dust encountered by the stellar light, it is the placement of the dust vis-a-vis the stars that determine the attenuation properties. Thus, all evidence suggests that it is the distribution of dust vis-a-vis various stellar populations that determines its behavior, i.e., star-dust geometry is the main determinant of the dust attenuation properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;more-formal-description&quot;&gt;More Formal Description&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Star-dust geometry: main determinant of dust attenuation in galaxies&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dust is as crucial a component of a galaxy and as omnipresent as stars, gas, and dark matter. Its importance can be gauged from the fact that it reprocesses more than half of the galaxy’s stellar light. The dust properties (mainly its amount and constituents) inside a galaxy depend on the star formation history of that galaxy. In addition to that, the dust properties of a galaxy are a critical determinant of its future star formation activity. Unraveling the connection between the properties of dust and its host galaxy is, therefore, a powerful diagnostic for the processes involved in its evolution (Dunne et al. 2011; Santini et al. 2014).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The properties of dust inside a galaxy are deduced by analyzing its effect on the galaxy’s stellar emission over the spectrum (Calzetti 1997; Draine 2003). This effect of dust is accounted for through the dust attenuation curve of a galaxy. The dust attenuation curve gives the optical depth of a galaxy over the spectrum, i.e., it describes how a galaxy’s light is affected by dust at each wavelength. So a general attenuation curve peaks at far UV and becomes negligible by the time it reaches IR. Constant efforts are made to compute attenuation curves for galaxies in a robust manner as it is a prerequisite for estimating galaxies’ stellar mass and star formation rate (Walcher et al. 2011; Conroy 2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The method that has lately gained traction for providing the most reliable attenuation curves for galaxies individually is the ‘model method’. This involves the creation of a library of dust-free spectrums or Spectral Energy Distributions (SEDs) spanning a large range of star formation histories and metallicities through the usage of stellar population synthesis models. The dust-free SEDs are then attenuated and compared with observed SEDs to obtain estimates of galaxy parameters and dust content. Recently, Salim et al. (2018) implemented the ‘energy balanced SED fitting’ technique on a quarter million local galaxies with far-UV to far-IR observations resulting in a detailed set of dust attenuation parameters for galaxies individually, covering the whole mass and stellar activity range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Stripe 82 - a 270 square degrees area in the sky - spectra as well as deep images are available for tens of thousands of local galaxies (Dawson et al. 2013; Annis et al. 2014). Utilizing that, Bottrell et al. (2019) have computed a detailed set of structural parameters (like size, ellipticity, bulge-to-total ratio, etc.) for all galaxies (∼17000) in this area in optical wavebands. Thus, detailed structural, stellar, and attenuation curve defining parameters - understood to be the most accurate to date - are available for all (∼17000) galaxies in the Stripe 82 region. In our work, we employ this data to perform a detailed investigation of the processes and properties responsible for the observed variation in dust attenuation parameters of galaxies covering the entire mass and stellar activity range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We probed the cause of variation in the dust attenuation curves of galaxies by studying the trend of the normalized attenuation slope in the ultraviolet with the structure, star formation activity, total stellar mass, inclination, and optical depth of galaxies. The main findings are discussed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The attenuation curve for spheroid-dominated galaxies is twice as steep as that for disc-dominated ones. Both structural types occupy non-overlapping ranges of the attenuation slope value (10-20% overlap). Thus, stellar mass distribution within the galaxy is one of the main determinants of its dust attenuation behavior. More importantly, within a structural group, i.e., that of discs, slope values are constrained to a narrow range, emphasizing the primacy of structure in determining dust properties.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The steepness of the attenuation curve for spheroids is driven by minimal attenuation in the optical bands compared to that in the ultraviolet. Thus, only newly formed stars get attenuated in the case of spheroids. In contrast, the shallowness of the curve in the case of discs is driven by near-uniform attenuation in UV and optical bands. Thus, all stars face attenuation in the case of discs, both due to a more dominant presence of ‘birth clouds’ and a denser interstellar medium (Charlot &amp;amp; Fall, 2000).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The trends observed in the case of the structure are reflected in the case of star formation activity as well. The slope for passive galaxies is twice as steep as that for star-forming ones. This is expected because most (&amp;gt;85-90%) discs are star-forming, and spheroids are passive. Since star-forming galaxies are more gas-rich, clumpier and have a larger presence of birth clouds compared to passive galaxies, it provides further evidence that the distribution of stellar mass and dust inside a galaxy is the main cause of variation in attenuation curves (Inoue 2005).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; All our findings add up to the argument that if the extinction curve is assumed to be universal, the distribution of stars and dust, i.e., star-dust geometry, is the primal determinant of the attenuation properties of a galaxy. Recently, under similar assumptions, Narayanan et al. (2018) have shown through simulations that star-dust geometry drives the variation in attenuation curves. Our results confirm that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dunne L. et al., 2011, MNRAS , 417, 1510&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Santini P. et al., 2014, A&amp;amp;A , 562, A30&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Calzetti D., 1997, AJ , 113, 162&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Draine B. T., 2003, ApJ , 598, 1017&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Walcher J., Gro v es B., Budav ári T., Dale D., 2011, Ap&amp;amp;SS , 331, 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conroy C., 2013, ARA&amp;amp;A , 51, 393&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salim S., Boquien M., Lee J. C., 2018, ApJ , 859, 11&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dawson K. S. et al., 2013, AJ , 145, 10&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Annis J. et al., 2014, ApJ , 794, 120&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bottrell C., Simard L., Mendel J. T., Ellison S. L., 2019, MNRAS , 486, 390&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Charlot S., Fall S. M., 2000, ApJ , 539, 718&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inoue A. K., 2005, MNRAS , 359, 171&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Narayanan D., Conroy C., Dav é R., Johnson B. D., Popping G., 2018, ApJ, 869, 70&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.513L..63S/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Star-dust geometry main determinant of dust attenuation in galaxies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Sonali Sachdeva&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Biman B. Nath&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Raman Research Institute(RRI), Bengaluru, 560080; India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/dust_in_galaxies_sonali</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/dust_in_galaxies_sonali</guid>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Spreading the joy of science - The science outreach activities during the Young Astronomer’s Meeting, 2022</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A summary of science outreach performed during the Young Astronomer’s Meeting, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human mind is always curious and questioning. It has a very compulsive behavior of asking “why,” “how,” and sometimes “what if?”. As Farhan Akhtar sings in the movie Rock On!! (2008), &lt;em&gt;“Why is the sky blue, why is the water wet, and why is the Earth round? Socha hai? Ye tumne kya kabhi?”&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &lt;em&gt;“Have you ever thought of this?”&lt;/em&gt;. Curiosity is one of the most fundamental qualities of humans and is unbridled in children. Children ask questions that are sometimes startlingly profound - “Why is the North of a magnet attracted to the South?”. Such questions are crucial to understanding the world around us and the very nature of our existence!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science is generally approached in schools as a collection of facts about the world, with a smattering of numerical problems. However, this is hardly the case. Science is a method or a prescription for understanding the world. Typically, we perceive (see or hear or taste, for example) the world and are driven by an innate curiosity as to how the world functions. To answer this curiosity, we come up with reasons – some may be correct, but others may be utterly wrong. How do we decide this? Through the scientific method! Each reason may give rise to multiple testable results, which we then compare against the things we see or infer. We keep updating our different “reasons” if they fail and try to come up with a general picture of the world. If any person tests out these different “reasons,” they should also come up with the same answer – and then we would know if our understanding of the world is correct!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Young Astronomers Meet (YAM) is a meeting of &lt;strong&gt;only research scholars&lt;/strong&gt; in astronomy and astrophysics in India. This meeting is of the scholars, for the scholars, and by the scholars. After a “coronal hiatus,” the meeting was held this year at the Aryabhatta Research Institute of observational sciencES (ARIES) in Nainital between 9th-13th November. As research scholars aiming to be professional scientists in the future, we ought to share our understanding, enthusiasm, and excitement about the scientific analysis of the world with everyone. With this in mind, the YAM committee organized a series of outreach activities aimed mainly at school children. The unbridled enthusiasm and curiosity of school children are an excellent motivator for the research scholars who were on the other side just a decade ago. The outreach activities were initiated by Dr. Virendra Yadav of ARIES/ASI-POEC and brought into shape by Mr. Atharva Pathak of Pune Knowledge Cluster, who was earlier with the IUCAA Science Popularization team. Along with the two experts were the YAM chair Vivek Jha, YAM coordinator Dimple, and YAM SOC member/ CosmicVarta editorial team member Vishal&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, who edited and finalized the outreach program. This complete team had almost more than 15 research scholars who volunteered from purchasing materials to conducting outreach!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-initial-outreach-session&quot;&gt;The initial outreach session&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, the schools had requested outreach sessions for a specific range of classes. For example, students between classes 6th to 8th formed one batch, and those from 9th to 12th included another. On the first day of YAM, we were yet to receive a full confirmation from various schools which had been approached. One school – Dikshant International, Haldwani – had confirmed the outreach session for both batches on the 10th of November, 2022. So on the 9th, Atharva, Virendra, Dimple, Vivek, and I sat down with the set of experiments and demonstrations of IUCAA Scip-pop brought by Atharva. Every region, every school, and every batch is unique. Hence, we selected an initial set of demonstrations suitable for the two batches of students. The initial preparation was extremely important – the demonstrations had traveled all the way from Pune to Nainital and had to be in perfect condition to work. Thus, we narrowed down a couple of demonstrations and presentations to be showcased to the students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team on the first day was led by both Atharva and Virendra. It consisted of Sreetama Das Choudhury and Samik Mitra from IIT Guwahati, Priyesh Tripathi from ARIES, Ajay Kumar from NCRA, Pune, and myself. The outreach started with the senior batch students, to whom Virendra introduced astronomy and ARIES. This was followed by a set of demonstrations led by Atharva and the volunteers, involving participation from the crowd as “student volunteers.” A part of the team then led these students for sunspot observations through the 5” Cassegrain telescope. The junior batch students were presented with most of the demonstrations – however, this crowd was more challenging to control, with the time running short. Thus, while the volunteers conducted the demonstrations, each step and reasoning was interactively performed, with the students sometimes shouting an answer in unison! Finally, these students were shown sunspots through the telescope, and the sessions concluded with an informal interaction with the outreach team and teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/outreach_activities_yam_vishal/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Outreach sessions at Dikshant International. Top: The research scholar volunteers with the school students. Bottom: A talk by Dr. Virendra Yadav is underway.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learning-from-feedback&quot;&gt;Learning from feedback&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sessions at Dikshant International were a big hit and taught us many things. First, the younger students were typically chaotic and easily fascinated by science experiments – especially those making a lot of noise or being disruptive. These kids were not very interested in any presentation unless it was highly captivating. Second, the older students showed a greater inclination toward the presentations. Furthermore, the presentations were effective if they were relevant to the experiment being performed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had confirmed attendance at four schools the next day (11th November). Since the demos were limited in number, we had to select demos that may be showcased at these different schools and make multiple copies of each demo for each school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking all this data, we formulated a plan of action. The subsequent sessions would have the sunspot observation as the epicenter, and from thereon, we would diversify to different topics. Each session would first start with sunspot observations, giving an observational treat. Next, we would have a presentation on sunspots with lots of visuals. Then, we change tracks to the experiments: (i). Demonstration of magnetic levitation – an extension of the magnetic nature of sunspots, (ii). Mixing of different colours of light, and the meaning of “electromagnetic spectrum” (iii). The demonstration of transverse and longitudinal waves and energy transfer using a slinky-like construction (iv). The dependence of pitch of the sound on the length of the air/water column, using two demonstrations, (v). Concave and convex mirror and lens demonstration, and (vi). The application of an astrolabe to find the coordinates of objects in the sky. The session would then end with slides on ARIES and YAM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With our demos confirmed, we needed to replicate them. Volunteers from ARIES stepped up to perform the purchase. The demonstrations are constructed with simple, day-to-day objects: colored papers, pencils, plastic straws, sponges, and protractors, for example!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/outreach_activities_yam_vishal/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Session planning, demonstration construction, and presentation curation by the YAM attendees. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since there were four schools with four volunteers per team, we needed around 16 volunteers for our team. The YAM attendees enthusiastically turned up to volunteer for the outreach and were split into different teams. Each team had a lead and a set of volunteers trained and readied for the outreach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;large-scale-outreach-session&quot;&gt;Large-scale outreach session&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two large cars containing two teams each left ARIES early in the morning after breakfast on the 11th. The schools gave timings for conducting the sessions, so we had to ensure there was correct coordination, for we only had two telescopes for four schools. The outreach plan was to go to the first school, perform sunspot observations, and let the second team take the telescope to the next school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four schools that had requested outreach were Shemford, Sacred Heart, Aurum Global, and Aryaman Vikram Birla Institute of Learning. Atharva, Virendra, Gourav, and I led the teams at different schools. In Atharva’s team were Eshita Banerjee (IUCAA) and Kiran Wani (ARIES), while in Virendra’s team were Sayak Dutta, Suraj Dhiwar (IUCAA), and Vikas Rawat (ARIES). Gourav Banerjee of CHRIST (Deemed to be University), Bangalore led Anju Panthi (BITS Pilani), Mizna Ashraf (IISER Tirupati), and Arpit Kumar Shrivastav (ARIES), while I led Pranshu Kumar, Bhavya Ailawadhi and Prajjwal Rawat from ARIES.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/outreach_activities_yam_vishal/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Outreach at Aryaman school, with the sunspot observations (top) and demonstrations (bottom). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/outreach_activities_yam_vishal/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Outreach session and demonstrations at Aurum school 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/outreach_activities_yam_vishal/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Outreach session and demonstrations at Sacred heart school 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/outreach_activities_yam_vishal/image6.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Outreach session and demonstrations at Shemford school  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outreach events went almost perfectly according to our plans. Since each team had a leader with prior experience performing science outreach, the teams adapted to the student’s responses. We aimed not just to showcase experiments but to inculcate excitement and develop an innate curiosity about the world. Thus, depending on which demos were well received, the teams tinkered with the order and the set of demos to be presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The junior batch students were extremely chaotic. Navigating the chaotic energy is a major task in itself, but in general, all the volunteers were amazed by the observation skills and thought processes of these kids. The students were attentive to what we spoke about and asked some questions which, at a scientific level, were quite profound! Also, we noticed that the little things we do significantly impact kids with confidence issues. A little encouragement to such kids to come onto the stage and perform the demos has quite an impact on these kids. In fact, some of these kids stayed much later to chat with us and thanked us for giving them an opportunity on stage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 12th of November, a final outreach session was planned for senior batch students at Longview Public school with the same demos. This school was not in the plains of Haldwani but rather in the mountains of Nainital. This session was undertaken by Virendra, Kiran, and Pranshu and joined by Srashti Goyal of ICTS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/outreach_activities_yam_vishal/image7.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Outreach session and demonstrations at Longview school 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;wrapping-up-and-next-steps&quot;&gt;Wrapping up and next steps&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The science demos we created for individual schools were given away to these schools to let the teachers perform such demonstrations. In most schools, the teachers showed as much enthusiasm as the students while the demos were underway. This is critically important in inculcating love, excitement for the scientific process, and a general curiosity about the world. Dr. Virendra Yadav, the co-chair of the Outreach team of the Astronomical Society of India, presented a summary report to ASI on the conducted outreach sessions. The team of volunteers hopes that the YAM outreach becomes a standard template of outreach to be followed as a part of any conference/meeting occurring within India; looking forward to increased participation and sharing our scientific enthusiasm!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yeah me - Nice to meet you :P &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/outreach_activities_yam_vishal</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/outreach_activities_yam_vishal</guid>
        
        <category>scicomm</category>
        
        <category>outreach</category>
        
        <category>conference</category>
        
        
        <category>Science Outreach</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Astronomers find cold atomic gas playing peek-a-boo around a powerful quasar</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The interaction of radio jets with gas associated with the host galaxy could play an important role in determining their morphology.  Such interactions may be more prevalent at high redshifts, when these powerful AGN are still the assembly sites of giant galaxies.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/cold_atomic_gas_powerful_quasar_neeraj/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 1 The canonical model of AGN (&lt;a href=&quot;https://imagine.gsfc.nasa.gov/science/objects/active_galaxies1.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Credit: Aurore Simonnet, Sonoma State University&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The active galactic nuclei (AGN) are among the most luminous sources in the Universe. Their energy output is fuelled by the supply of gas to the central engine, i.e., a supermassive black hole (SMBH) through an accretion disk (see Fig. 1).  The detection of Lyman-alpha emission from neutral hydrogen (HI) has established that the powerful AGN at high redshift are embedded in huge (10 - 100 kpc) gaseous halos of diffuse atomic gas.  The observations of absorption lines detected in the spectra of AGN can provide crucial insights into the processes through which gas at large scales can be transported to the circumnuclear disk to fuel the central engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/link_gateway/2022ApJ...927L..24G/doi:10.3847/2041-8213/ac589f&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gupta et al.(2022, ApJL, 927, L24)&lt;/a&gt; recently used the Robert Stobie Spectrograph (RSS) on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.salt.ac.za/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the Southern African Large Telescope (SALT)&lt;/a&gt; in South Africa and &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.nrao.edu/facilities/vlba/introduction-to-vlba&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the Very Long Baseline Array (VLBA)&lt;/a&gt;  in the USA to discover a curious case of high HI column density absorber that exhibits strong HI 21-cm absorption at radio wavelengths but is absent at optical wavelength! SALT is the largest single optical telescope in the southern hemisphere whereas VLBA is a radio interferometer  consisting of 10 identical antennas, separated by distances from 200 km to transcontinental 8600 km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/cold_atomic_gas_powerful_quasar_neeraj/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 2 HI 21-cm absorption line associated with the powerful AGN M1540-1453.  Note that the HI 21-cm line (rest frequency of 1420.405752 MHz) is redshifted to ~456.2 MHz.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The large reservoir of cold HI gas associated with the quasar M1540-1453 at the redshift of z = 2.104 was discovered using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gmrt.ncra.tifr.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the upgraded Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope (uGMRT)&lt;/a&gt;  in India.  The corresponding HI 21-cm absorption profile is shown in Fig. 2.  It doesn’t exhibit any unusual features except that such absorbers have been difficult to find at high redshifts and only four are known at z &amp;gt; 2.  To understand the origin of detected cold gas, Gupta et al. observed M1540-1453 with SALT to detect the strong Lyman-alpha (Lyα) absorption corresponding to the gas detected with uGMRT.  But to their surprise, no such absorption was detected in the optical spectrum (see Fig. 3).   Also, in comparison to typical quasars, the Lyα emission line associated with the AGN is much narrower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/cold_atomic_gas_powerful_quasar_neeraj/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 3 SALT spectrum of M1540-1453.  Note the absence of strong HI Lyman alpha absorption.  The blue curve represents the absorption profile expected on the basis of absorption detected in the uGMRT spectrum at radio wavelengths.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/cold_atomic_gas_powerful_quasar_neeraj/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 4 VLBA image revealing the diffuse radio morphology of M1540-1453.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparison to optical, in general the radio emission associated with AGN is much more spatially extended. This difference can be used to explain such ambiguities in the radio and optical spectra. To dissect this further and understand the &lt;em&gt;ghostly&lt;/em&gt; nature of this HI absorber, Gupta et al. observed M1540-1453 with VLBA.  Usually, one expects radio emission associated with such powerful AGN to exhibit well collimated radio jets and lobes (see Fig. 1). However, the milliarcsecond-scale resolution observation of M1540-1453 shows a diffuse morphology (Fig. 4), which implies that the gas in front of it, which is producing absorption, is also not a few localized gas clumps, but rather forms a clumpy shell or halo which could be as large as 10 kpc (see Fig. 5). It is conjectured that this HI shell represents infalling gas clouds that may have been blown by the interaction between radio jets and the host galaxy medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/cold_atomic_gas_powerful_quasar_neeraj/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 5: Cartoon depicting a quadrant of M1540–1453 embedded in a clumpy ISM. The quasar’s optical sight line (dashed line) may not intercept infalling HI clouds. In comparison, extended radio emission (&amp;gt; 425 pc) from the lobes will be intercepted by several such clouds, producing the broad redshifted HI 21 cm absorption line. The extent of the HI halo and radio emission could be as large as 10 kpc.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quasar M1540-1453 was discovered through an ambitious spectroscopic survey using SALT (180 hrs) and the Nordic Optical Telescopes (6 nights) to build a purely infrared-selected sample of radio-loud quasars (RLQs) at z &amp;gt; 1.5 and define the footprint of &lt;a href=&quot;https://mals.iucaa.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the MeerKAT Absorption Line Survey&lt;/a&gt;  (MALS; PI: N. Gupta).  MALS is one of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ska.ac.za/science-engineering/meerkat/observers/observing-programme/large-survey-projects/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the ten large surveys&lt;/a&gt; being carried out with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ska.ac.za/science-engineering/meerkat/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; the MeerKAT radio telescope&lt;/a&gt; in South Africa. In the coming years, MALS is expected to detect several such absorbers that may have escaped detection at other wavelengths, and address various fundamental issues related to AGN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.3847/2041-8213/ac589f&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; H I Gas Playing Hide-and-seek around a Powerful FRI-type Quasar at z ∼ 2.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Neeraj Gupta&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; R. Srianand, E. Momjian, G. Shukla, F. Combes, J.-K. Krogager, P. Noterdaeme, and P. Petitjean&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Inter-University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics (IUCAA), Pune, India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/cold_atomic_gas_powerful_quasar_neeraj</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/cold_atomic_gas_powerful_quasar_neeraj</guid>
        
        <category>Active galactic nuclei; Radio loud quasars; Radio jets; Quasar absorption line spectroscopy</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A comparison of the properties of Narrow Line and the Broad Line Seyfert galaxies</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;AGNs are very luminous objects at the centre of active galaxies. The inner regions of these galaxies can not be resolved directly, yet the understanding of these regions can be achieved by employing indirect methods. In this study, we employed a statistical approach to understand a very peculiar class of AGN with respect to the general AGN population- the Narrow Line Seyfert galaxies, and have found out that emission line region outflows exist in the innermost regions of these AGN which adds another peculiarity to their behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent discoveries have pointed out that a supermassive black hole (SMBH) exists in the centre of the galaxies, with mass ranging from a million to a billion solar masses. This central black hole accretes matter at a very high rate. In turn, an accretion disk is formed and it radiates a luminosity ranging from a billion to a trillion times the luminosity of the Sun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FPF1X13wbDI&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
This animation is an artistic impression of the inner regions of an active galaxy. The animation starts with the optical image of 3C273, a very well-known quasar, and zooms in up to the sub-parsec scale, where the clumps of gas known as the Broad Line Region (BLR) clouds exist embedded beneath a torus of dust. (Video Courtesy: ESO YouTube channel)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These kinds of galaxies are called active galaxies, or more popularly these objects are called Quasars. Quasars were discovered to be very luminous extragalactic objects only in 1963, through the work of Martin Schmidt. In research, various names: Active galactic Nuclei (AGN), Quasars, Blazar, Seyferts, etc. are known (see this for detailed information about the Quasars). Commonly, people use AGN as a generic term, while Quasar is used for AGNs having higher luminosities (&amp;gt; 1e44 ergs/sec). Seyferts are the AGN that are a little less luminous than Quasars. Type-1 AGN are the ones where the observer is able to view the innermost regions comprising the accretion disk and the BLR without any obscuration, while in the Type-2 AGN, the dusty torus obscures the innermost regions. 
Among the type 1 Seyferts, a peculiar class of galaxies known as the Narrow line Seyfert 1 galaxies is known to exist. These are young AGN, with very high accretion rates. The study of these objects provides clues to the understanding of the formation and growth of AGNs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/narrow_broad_seyfert_galaxies_vivek/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
The Unified Model for AGN accounts for various properties observed in AGN. This simple model differentiates between the various classes based on the orientation with respect to the observer. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://fermi.gsfc.nasa.gov/science/eteu/agn/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image courtesy&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this work, we have studied the properties of these NLSy1 galaxies as compared to the general type-1 AGN which we term Broad-line Seyfert galaxies (BLSy1) galaxies. We achieved this by collecting optical spectra for a sample of about 260 galaxies. We searched for the spectra in the publicly available SDSS database. SDSS provides information for hundreds and thousands of such objects on their server. We assembled a set of 144 NLSy1 and 117 BLSy1 galaxies which are in a similar luminosity and redshift range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/narrow_broad_seyfert_galaxies_vivek/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
The multiple-component spectral decomposition was applied to fit one of the sources in this study.(&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.09150&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image courtesy&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After fitting the spectra by employing a multi-component spectral decomposition technique, we studied a set of 11 physical parameters to compare these two populations. It is very important to know that the exact relation of the NLSy1 galaxies with the BLSy1 galaxies remains unknown for the general AGN population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We characterized the population of these galaxies based on the asymmetry observed in a very prominent emission line: the H-beta emission line. In our sample, we found out the NLSy1 galaxies are 3 times more likely to show emission line asymmetries as compared to the BLSy1 galaxies population. This result is very important in our understanding of the difference between these two populations. Note that the emission lines are generated in the Broad-line Region (BLR) of these AGNs, and this region cannot be resolved by any observation technique at present. Thus, we are reliant on indirect tools to infer the dynamics of matter in these regions. In this regard, emission line asymmetries encode information about the dynamics of matter at the location from where they are emitted and thus it becomes necessary to characterize. The outflows may also be due to the winds arising from the accretion disk in these AGNs, which influences our understanding and further modelling of the AGN accretion disks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/narrow_broad_seyfert_galaxies_vivek/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
A cluster map showing the correlations between 11 parameters.  (&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.09150&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image courtesy&lt;/a&gt;) 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We calculated the Spearman rank correlation coefficients among the parameters. We found that the accretion rate characterized by the Eddington Ratio is anti-correlated with the FWHM of the H-beta emission line which means the AGNs which are accreting at a faster rate, will have narrower emission profiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, we ran a Principal component analysis (PCA) on the data to understand the parameters deriving the correlations and anti-correlations. Basically, PCA reduces the dimensions of the dataset in the sense that what we were able to derive based on 11 physical parameters, we could do with fewer principal components. This helps us understand the underlying correlations among the fewer parameters. Based on the results from the PCA, we find out that the Eigenvectors 1 and 2 of the PCA are a bit different for both populations. What can be the possible reason behind this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/narrow_broad_seyfert_galaxies_vivek/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
The main sequence of quasars obtained from the recent studies. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fspas.2018.00006/full&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image courtesy&lt;/a&gt;) 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, based on an ensemble study of around 500,000 AGN, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature13712&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Shen et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt;  reported the same Eigenvector correlation as has been observed in this study. This is significant because it points out that AGN located in different redshifts and luminosity bins show similar properties which can be arranged to form a sort of main sequence. The main sequence is a very neat way to arrange the population of stars based on the luminosities and their age. A similar main sequence for the AGN has been proposed based on this correlation.
Are the Eigenvectors telling a different story? We don’t know yet. However, we can safely say that the NLSy1 galaxies form the extreme end of the AGN population with very high accretion rates and low SMBH masses. The discovery of significant emission line asymmetries in the NLSy1 galaxies means that outflowing gas is indeed present in the line emitting regions. Similar studies covering a larger population will be very helpful in our understanding of the peculiarity of these AGNs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.510.4379J/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A comparative study of the physical properties for a representative sample of Narrow and Broad-line Seyfert galaxies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Vivek Kumar Jha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hum Chand, Vineet Ojha, Amitesh Omar, Shantanu Rastogi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Aryabhatta Research Institute of observational sciencES (ARIES), Nainital, 263002; India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/narrow_broad_seyfert_galaxies_vivek</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/narrow_broad_seyfert_galaxies_vivek</guid>
        
        <category>AGNs</category>
        
        <category>Blackhole</category>
        
        <category>Galaxies</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>3.6m DOT discovered unexpected kilonova emission from a long-duration gamma-ray burst</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) are flashes of high-energy radiation arising from energetic cosmic explosions. Bursts of long (greater than two seconds) duration are produced by the core-collapse of massive stars, and those of short (less than two seconds) duration by the merger of compact objects, such as two neutron stars. A third class of events with hybrid high-energy properties was identified, but never conclusively linked to a stellar progenitor. The lack of bright supernovae rules out typical core-collapse explosions, but their distance scales prevent sensitive searches for direct signatures of a progenitor system. Only tentative evidence for a kilonova has been presented. Here we report observations of the exceptionally bright GRB 211211A, which classify it as a hybrid event and constrain its distance scale to only 346 megaparsecs. Our measurements indicate that its lower-energy (from ultraviolet to near-infrared) counterpart is powered by a luminous kilonova possibly formed in the ejecta of a compact object merger. To study the aftermath of this long GRB, we used several telescopes in space and on Earth, in which the 3.6 m Devasthal Optical Telescope of the Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES) played a significant role.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some massive stars die as the brightest and most explosive astrophysical sources in the universe, known as gamma-ray bursts (GRBs). GRBs are powerful astronomical bursts of high-energy gamma-ray radiation and are one of the most interesting and scientifically fulfilling phenomena studied in modern astronomy. GRB events have two distinct emission phases: one is the short-lived prompt emission (the initial burst phase, that emits gamma-rays), followed by a long-lived multiwavelength afterglow phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past few decades, based on the observed time scale of prompt emission, astronomers have generally divided GRBs into two categories: long and short-duration GRBs, respectively. Long GRBs typically emit gamma rays for two seconds or more. They are associated with the death of very massive stars and are sometimes associated with supernovae. On the other hand, Short GRBs emit gamma rays for short periods of less than two seconds. This class of GRBs is formed when pairs of very dense celestial bodies (compact) - such as neutron stars or black holes - merge with each other, rotating in a spiral form over a period of billions of years. They also generate gravitational waves. In recent years, scientists have discovered a special phenomenon called a kilonova of visible and infrared light with short-period GRBs. According to a possible scientific hypothesis, the heat produced by the radioactive decay of heavier elements may emit kilonova. This process, known in physics as the r and s process, also produces heavier elements such as gold and platinum. However, observing kilonovas at near-infrared wavelengths is technically challenging, and only a few telescopes on Earth have been useful. The 3.6-meter Devasthal Optical Telescope (see Figure 1) of the Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), is one such telescope that is  sensitive enough to detect kilonova and optical/near-IR counterparts of gravitational wave objects at these wavelengths up to faint limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On December 11, 2021, NASA’s Neil Gehrels Swift Observatory and the Fermi Gamma-ray Space Telescope detected a burst of high-energy light (GRB 211211A) from the outskirts of the Milky Way located approximately 1 billion light-years away. To study the aftermath of this long GRB, astronomers used several telescopes in space and on Earth, in which the 3.6 m Devasthal Optical Telescope of the Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES) played a very important role (see Figure 2). The spectral energy distribution of GRB afterglow is usually explained in terms of non-thermal emission (due to synchrotron radiation). However, in this event, both thermal and non-thermal emissions are included in the spectral energy distribution of the afterglow, modeled using the magnificent and dim observations of the 3.6 m Devasthal Optical Telescope. After subtracting the afterglow contribution from the collected data taken using the 3.6 m telescope and 4Kx4K CCD IMAGER, the scientists found that the multiwavelength data could be well explained by additional thermal spectra and that this thermal emission could be explained in terms of kilonova emission. &lt;strong&gt;This is the first astronomical event in which a long GRB has been accompanied by the unexpected discovery of a kilonova emission&lt;/strong&gt;, and  has shaken the understanding of scientists. In this event, the high-energy outburst lasted about a minute, and follow-up observations taken from the 3.6-meter Devasthal Optical Telescope identified a kilonova. Observations by the 3.6 m Devasthal Optical Telescope have provided information on the earliest phase of a kilonova ever detected. In addition to the first data taken by the 3.6-meter telescope, this scientific discovery, published in the journal &lt;strong&gt;Nature&lt;/strong&gt;, also used Hubble Space Telescope, Multicolor Imaging Telescopes for Survey and Monstrous Explosions, Calar Alto Observatory, Devasthal Fast Optical Telescope, and many other space and ground-based telescopes. This discovery will help in understanding the process of the formation of heavy elements in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/dot_kilonova_emission_grb_rahul/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: 3.6m Devasthal Optical Telescope installed at Devasthal Observatory of  Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Nainital. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Several years ago, Neil Gehrels, an astrophysicist, and namesake of Swift suggested that some long-duration GRBs may be produced by merging neutron stars,” said Eleonora Troja, an astrophysicist at the University of Rome who led the team on the study. By GRB standards, this event was relatively nearby, allowing space and ground-based telescopes to capture the dim light of the kilonova. Kilonovae may also arise from more distant long GRBs, but we have not yet been able to see them through observations. PI of the 4Kx4K CCD IMAGER mounted on ARIES’ 3.6-meter telescope, senior Scientist Dr. Shashi Bhushan Pandey, along with research students Rahul Gupta, Amar Aryan, Amit Kumar, and Senior Scientist Kuntal Mishra, contributed significantly to the discovery of this milestone event published in the journal Nature on 07-12-2022 at 16:00 (London time). Dr. Shashi Bhushan Pandey and the team of Indian scientists involved in this work said that this discovery challenges our current understanding of the origin of GRBs and gives rise to new possibilities in this thrust area of research. Professor Dipankar Banerjee, director of ARIES, pointed out that future time-domain astronomy has a unique potential to make a lot of such discoveries using the 3.6m Devasthal optical telescope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/dot_kilonova_emission_grb_rahul/image2.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: The temporal evolution of optical emission (in R band) from GRB 211211A based on DOT data. The scientists from the ARIES, an autonomous institute of DST, used data from 3.6m DOT, in studying the aftermath of the long GRB (GRB 211211A), detected by NASA&apos;s Neil Gehrels Swift Observatory and the Fermi Gamma-ray Space Telescope on December 11, 2021. The high-energy outburst lasted about a minute, and follow-up observations taken from the 3.6-meter Devasthal Optical Telescope identified a kilonova. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discovery opens new questions regarding the origin and classification of GRBs. These sources’ unique gravitational wave signatures could be the key to unraveling the mystery. The gravitational wave detectors such as LIGO, Virgo, and KAGRA did not detect GRB 211211A, as these detectors were offline for advancements. Suppose  gravitational wave detectors can see a long-duration GRB after they begin operating again in 2023. In that case, the combination of gravitational wave and electromagnetic data may solve the mystery of this newly discovered event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-05327-3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A nearby long gamma-ray burst from a merger of compact objects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; E. Troja&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; C. L. Fryer, B. O’Connor, G. Ryan, S. Dichiara, A. Kumar, N. Ito, R. Gupta, R. Wollaeger, J. P. Norris, N. Kawai, N. Butler, A. Aryan, K. Misra, R. Hosokawa, K. L. Murata, M. Niwano, S. B. Pandey, A. Kutyrev, H. J. van Eerten, E. A. Chase, Y.-D. Hu, M. D. Caballero-Garcia, A. J. Castro-Tirado&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Department of Physics, University of Rome “Tor Vergata”, Rome, Italy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;School of Earth and Space Exploration, Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ, USA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/dot_kilonova_emission_grb_rahul</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/dot_kilonova_emission_grb_rahul</guid>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fantastic beasts and where to find them: the elusive nature of X-ray quiet black holes</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;With the gravitational wave observations capturing the coalescence of compact objects, hunting for black holes has taken quite a front-row seat in astronomical observations. Here, we discuss two such detection of black holes in orbit with a main sequence companion, and why it is very difficult to find them in the forest of massive stars.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massive stars are objects that are more massive than eight times the mass of our Sun (M⊙). They play an essential role in the evolution of our Universe. They enrich the void between stars with matter via strong winds and provide mechanical feedback. However, many aspects of massive star evolution are still unconstrained, such as their wind mass-loss rates, the mixing efficiency inside their surface, and their death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massive stars that are heavier than ~20 M⊙ are thought to collapse directly to form black holes. Expectantly, there are many uncertainties such as the mass range for black hole formation, the natal kick imparted during the black hole formation due to asymmetric collapse,
and the spin of the resultant black hole. The gravitational wave detectors have already observed ~90 compact object merger events involving black holes and neutron stars. However, more than a million black holes are predicted to be present in our Galaxy itself, waiting to be discovered. So, observationally detecting a large sample of black holes can shed necessary light on their formation properties and their subsequent evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empirically, massive stars have been observed to exist in binaries and higher order multiples, with about three out of every 100 massive star binary above 10M⊙ expected to harbour a black hole as its companion. However, a large fraction of these binaries that will eventually form double compact object binaries will not merge within the current age of our Universe. Hence, they will remain unobservable in the current gravitational wave surveys. Nevertheless, progress can be made to discover these black holes while they are in orbit with a massive star companion, where they are detectable via alternative methods. This is possible, for example, by measuring the X-ray emission from the accretion disk of the black hole, the radial velocity variations in the spectral lines&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of the massive main sequence companion, and through periodic astrometric variations&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or photometric variability&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of the massive star companion induced by the black hole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black holes in binaries are thought to form from the collapse of massive Wolf-Rayet stars, which are very hot and bright stars that show emission lines in their spectrum. Now, there are many observed Wolf-Rayet+O star binaries in our Galaxy (~80) compared to observed black hole+O star binaries (only one, Cyg X-1). To resolve this disparity, it was recently suggested that black holes receive a significant natal kick when the Wolf-Rayet stars collapse to form a black hole, disrupting the binary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since black holes do not emit any light of their own, we need to rely on the indirect ways discussed above to observe a black hole. The most common method has been to detect X-rays from the accretion disk around the black hole in a binary with the O star companion. Some of the wind matter from the companion gets attracted by the gravity of the black hole, and if that matter falling into it has enough angular momentum, it can form a disk before being engulfed by the black hole. The matter then swirls around the black hole multiple times, gets heated up to millions of degrees, and gets hot enough to emit X-rays. Bondi, Hoyle and Lyttleton did pioneering work in this field in the 1940s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we find that such wind accretion in our black hole+O star binary models is not expected to lead to observable X-ray emission. Only in exceptionally favourable cases, such as high angular momentum accretion efficiency and low wind velocities, can an accretion disk form, leading to observable X-ray emission. Moreover, the formation of an accretion disk is also biased towards binaries containing rapidly spinning black holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first-born black hole in a massive binary is expected to be slowly spinning due to efficient angular momentum transport inside a star. The wind velocity of O stars is very high (~2000 km/s), empirically verified through observations. Detailed hydrodynamic calculations predict only one-third of the angular momentum available is accreted by the black hole. Hence, most black holes in orbit with an O star are not expected to form an accretion disk and remain unobservant via X-ray telescopes. So, the discrepancy in the number of observed Wolf-Rayet+O star binaries in comparison to black hole+O star binaries may be due to the lack of observability of the black hole binaries in X-rays. We conclude that high black hole natal kicks are not necessary to explain the scarcity of observed high-mass X-ray binaries. Instead, searching for black holes via alternative methods may be more fruitful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One alternative would be to search for black holes in our Milky Way via astrometric variations in visible stars - that is, variations in the precise measurements of the position of stars in the sky. This method has been shown to be very promising as our Milky Way is expected to harbour millions of black holes in orbit with main sequence companions whose astrometry can be carried out in principle by the GAIA telescope. Unfortunately, the GAIA Data Release 3 did not have the relevant data for stars massive enough to host black holes, and hence this method could not be pursued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus in this work, we look at radial velocity variations of observed massive stars. We have a nearly complete census of the massive star content in the Tarantula nebula of Large Magellanic Cloud, which enables us to also carry out precise number statistics for the massive stars in this region. In fact, it is the most active star-forming region known in the Local Group of galaxies containing very massive stars with a metallicity resembling the peak of star formation in our Universe. The radial velocity of stars is measured by observing the Doppler shift in a prominent spectral line of the star. As the star moves around in one full orbit, the spectral lines are blue-shifted for half of the orbit and red-shifted for the remaining orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we see a Doppler shift in a spectral line of a stellar object both towards the bluer and redder wavelengths simultaneously, we identify the object as a double-lined spectroscopic binary. This is because both the components of the binary are responsible for creating the Doppler shifts in opposite directions, one moving towards us in orbit and the other away from us. When we see a Doppler shift in only one direction, we identify the object as a single-lined spectroscopic binary. This is because the companion star is usually too faint for its spectral line to be detected. Or, in the most interesting case, the companion is a compact object which does not emit any light of its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identify the single-lined spectroscopic binaries in the sample of massive stars observed in the Tarantula region. The VLT Flames Tarantula Survey observed approximately 800 massive stars, out of which 300 were O-type stars. From these, around 100 targets that showed radial velocity variations were followed up in the Tarantula Massive Binary Monitoring Survey. Of these, 51 of them were categorised as single-lined spectroscopic binaries. Through follow-up spectral disentangling, we retrieved hidden spectra in 43 of these targets. For the remaining targets where we were not able to find a non-degenerate companion, three of them had an estimated minimum mass of the unseen companion above 4M⊙.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/xray_quiet_blackholes_koushik/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 1 : Visualisation of the BH+O star binary VFTS 243, a 10.4 d-period binary with a (near-)circular orbit situated in the Tarantula nebula in the Large Magellanic Cloud (credit: Isca Mayo / Sara Pinilla). The sizes of the star, black hole, and orbits are not to scale.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the above, we were able to find unambiguous evidence for the presence of a 9.1M⊙ object in the system named VFTS 243. The orbital period of this system is 10.4  days and the orbit is also circular. Through follow-up rigorous analysis, we arrive at the conclusion that the object is a black hole, the first one detected in the Large Magellanic Cloud. The system is also X-ray quiet, in agreement with our earlier study on the X-ray emission from black hole + main sequence systems. The above number statistics show how big an observing program needs to be undertaken to unambiguously find black holes via radial velocity monitoring of observed massive stars. In the Milky Way, we have found another system, HD 130298, that could be another candidate to host a stellar-mass black hole. Our journey towards identifying a population of X-ray quiet black holes has only started, and we aim to slowly but surely hunt them down, through future observational surveys, one black hole at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;i.e. the spectral lines oscillate about the mean wavelength due to doppler effect. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;i.e. change in absolute position on the sky. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;change in luminosity or flux. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/xray_quiet_blackholes_koushik</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/xray_quiet_blackholes_koushik</guid>
        
        <category>stars</category>
        
        <category>massive black holes</category>
        
        <category>binaries</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Precise Measurement of Flux Density of Radio Emissions from the Sun using Day-time Celestial Radio Sources</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;During astronomical observation, astronomers measure the amount of energy emitted by astronomical objects. This energy is generally measured in terms of the flux density of the source. At radio frequencies, these measurements are calibrated using calibrator sources, which have known constant flux densities. Since the Sun is about 1000 times brighter at radio frequencies than the calibrator sources, estimating the flux density of the solar radio emission is challenging. With the new generation radio telescope, the Murchison Widefield Array, it is now possible to observe the faint background radio sources simultaneously with the Sun. This is the first such an observation has been made, which seems like “observing stars in the day”. Using these background radio sources it is now possible to estimate the flux density of the solar radio emission with much better accuracy, which is important to understand the emission mechanisms of solar radio emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most physics experiments, researchers measure various quantities in different units, like the mass of a body measured in grams, the length of an object measured in centimeters, and so on. Similarly, Astronomers also measure different quantities during astronomy observations, which can be used to understand the physical properties of that astronomical object. In astronomy, measurements are done in some well-defined units, like any other area of physics. One such important quantity in astronomy is the &lt;em&gt;flux density&lt;/em&gt;, which defines the amount of energy received per unit of time from astronomical sources if collected over a unit area and unit solid angle for a monochromatic emission. At radio wavelengths, the unit of this flux density is &lt;em&gt;Jansky (Jy)&lt;/em&gt;, named after the pioneer of radio
astronomy, Karl. J. Jansky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an astronomer observes the radio emission from a celestial object using a radio telescope, the tiny amount of incident radio emission is converted into electronic voltages by the very sensitive electronic instruments of the radio telescope. The corresponding power generated by these very tiny voltages is recorded in some arbitrary units. But, to understand the physical processes happening on that celestial object, astronomers need to convert this measured power into the units of &lt;em&gt;Jy&lt;/em&gt;. The process to convert this is known as flux density calibration. Precise measurement of the flux density in units of &lt;em&gt;Jy&lt;/em&gt; is essential to properly measure other physical properties, like distance, size, temperature, and so on, of that astronomical source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process is routinely done using a bright radio source with a well-pre-defined flux density. These are called calibrator sources. While observing the Sun at radio wavelengths, this standard approach does not work. The flux density of the Sun is about 1000 times more than the brightest celestial radio source in the sky. Like at the optical wavelengths, it is tough to observe the background sources in the sky at radio wavelengths when the Sun is in the sky. Hence, to obtain the flux density of the Sun at radio wavelengths, solar physicists have used different laboratory measurements of the properties of the instrument to estimate the flux density of solar radio emission. But those estimations had comparatively large errors in the flux density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;observing-stars-in-the-day&quot;&gt;Observing Stars in the Day&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/flux_density_radio_emission_devojyoti/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 1 : An image of the daytime sky at radio frequency (80 MHz). The image is made from the observations taken with the instrument called the Murchison Widefield Array, which can observe a large, about 2500 square degrees of the sky at a time. The red circle in the image marks the Sun. All small white dots in the image are background sources
emitting radio frequencies, including stars, galaxies, quasars, pulsars, and others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For precise flux density calibration of solar observation, several background radio sources with well-known flux densities must be observed during the daytime. This is extremely challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite great challenges, a team of solar physicists from NCRA, led by Devojyoti Kansabanik, have successfully observed more than 80 background radio sources with the Sun in the field of view (FOV) of the telescope using images having a dynamic range of 1000. The dynamic range is the ratio between the brightest and faintest emission detected in the image. They used one of the most advanced telescopes in the world, the Murchison Widefield Array (MWA), situated in the western Australian desert, to make this high dynamic range image. This image is shown in Figure 1. A red circle marks the Sun, and all other small white dots are the radio emissions from background stars, galaxies, and other celestial bodies. They detected more than 80 sources with the Sun in the sky. This is the first time such an image of a daytime sky is made, which seems like &lt;em&gt;observing stars in the day&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;precise-measurement-of-flux-density-of-the-radio-sun&quot;&gt;Precise Measurement of Flux Density of the Radio Sun&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kansabanik et al. use these background radio sources to estimate the flux density of the radio Sun. The known flux density of these sources is obtained from the GLEAM survey and determines a scalar number for each source to match their flux density obtained from the image with the previously known values. They have found that these scalar numbers are constant for the full image. Hence, the same scalar number can be used to obtain the true flux density of the Sun in units of &lt;em&gt;Jy&lt;/em&gt;. This method allows them to measure solar flux density with a precision of 10 %, which is about 3 to 6 times more precise than the previous method developed by Oberoi et al. 2017. They also found that the 10% error is mostly coming from the error on the known flux densities from GLEAM of these radio sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kansabanik et al. also devise a method exploiting the extreme stability of the MWA. They demonstrated that a very precise solar flux density could be obtained only using an analytical function of frequency without using any dedicated observation of flux density calibrator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;importance-for-future-observations-of-the-sun-and-heliosphere&quot;&gt;Importance for Future Observations of the Sun and Heliosphere&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As said earlier, astronomers use precise flux density measurements to estimate several physical parameters of the celestial source. The radio emission from quiet solar corona or coronal mass ejections can be used to measure those media’s temperature, magnetic field, and electron properties. The estimated values of these plasma parameters strongly depend on the precision of the flux density measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides achieving precise flux density measurement, the first-ever successful detection of a large number of faint background radio sources makes it possible to observe the heliosphere close to the Sun using a wide FOV instrument, which is otherwise impossible. These sources and their polarized emission can be used in the future to measure the magnetic field in interplanetary space. When a large amount of plasma is erupted from theSun in the form of a CME and crosses the background sources, its polarization properties get changed by the magnetic field of the CME plasma. A similar phenomenon can be observed when magnetized solar wind passes through the line of sight of these background sources. The changes in polarization properties of them can be an efficient method to measure the magnetic field in the heliosphere over a larger region, which is rather challenging and only limited to some vantage point measurements directly from a handful of spacecraft. Work is currently underway to use the polarization properties of these sources to achieve this objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oberoi, D., Sharma, R. &amp;amp; Rogers, A.E.E. Estimating Solar Flux Density at Low Radio Frequencies Using a Sky Brightness Model. Sol Phys 292, 75 (2017). https://doi.org/10.1007/s11207-017-1096-1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac4bba&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robust Absolute Solar Flux Density Calibration for the Murchison Widefield Array&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Devojyoti Kansabanik&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Surajit Mondal, Divya Oberoi, Shilpi Bhunia, Ayan Biswas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; National Centre for Radio Astrophysics, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Pune,
India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/flux_density_radio_emission_devojyoti</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/flux_density_radio_emission_devojyoti</guid>
        
        <category>Solar Physics</category>
        
        <category>Solar Radio Physics</category>
        
        <category>MWA</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vainu Bappu Observatory: the telescope town of India</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A popular article describing the history and contributions of the Vainu Bappu Observatory: the telescope town of India.&lt;br /&gt;
My affair with the observatory is also highlighted in brief.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Development of astronomy in ancient civilizations like during the times of Babylonians, Greeks, Egyptians, etc. took place due to some fundamental needs. Some of these needs were predicting seasons precisely which helped the ancient people in agriculture, using the night sky for proper navigation while travelling in uncharted areas without having any compass or clock, fixing the time for religious rites, etc. The earliest recorded astronomical observations date back to around 1600 BCE by Babylonians, much before the beginning of the Christian era. As time progressed, advancement in astronomy took place gradually. And in parallel to this, an overall progress in science and technology also occurred. History shows that studying astronomy has generated fundamental knowledge which has benefited every human being through ages. For example, the discovery of gravitation by Newton led to the understanding of planetary motion, which further laid the foundation of space technology – a boon of science which has benefited almost every human being. STD phone, mobile, internet, etc. are some of the results of the development of space technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, invention of telescope and then studying the sky with bigger and better telescopes stationed in different astronomical observatories has greatly helped in this progress of astronomy since the past few hundred years. Encyclopedia Britannica defines an ‘astronomical observatory’ as “any structure containing telescopes and auxiliary instruments with which to observe celestial objects”. Like different other countries, India also possesses a long tradition of astronomy since ancient times [1].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standing in the present day twenty-first century, India possesses several world-class research institutes and observatories carrying high-class researches in astronomy. One such important astronomical observatory situated in Indian soil is the Vainu Bappu Observatory, a place which one can truly be considered as the ‘Telescope City of India’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;vainu-bappu-observatory-vbo-telescope-city-of-india&quot;&gt;Vainu Bappu Observatory (VBO): Telescope city of India&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 200 km south-west of Chennai and 175 km south-east of Bangalore, in the Tirupathur district of the Indian state of Tamil Nadu lies the picturesque Javadi hills. Amidst this forested vegetation, near the neighborhoods of the village known as Kavalur and at an altitude of around 750 m (longitude 78° 49.6’ E; latitude 12° 34.6’ N) is located the Vainu Bappu Observatory (VBO) – one of the most important and active astronomical observatories in India and also in Asia. Situated away from light pollution and hustles-bustles of any big city, VBO is operated by the Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA), Bangalore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spread over an area of 40-hectare, this place attracts astronomers and researchers from across the country who are involved in studying celestial objects like stars, exoplanets, galaxies, etc. and also engineers, operators and other staff members who look after the proper functioning of the observatory. Apart from these busy and always cheerful people, VBO is filled with a variety of greenery of tropical region besides a number of medicinal plants. This is because the area is inside a protected forest. Monkeys are regular visitors among animals. And occasionally, appearance of some wildlife like deer, snakes and scorpions also greet the people working inside the campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: Arial view of the Vainu Bappu Observatory located at Kavalur, Tamil Nadu (credit: P. Deshmukh, IIA, Bangalore)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the location of VBO provides advantages for night sky observation for astronomers. Apart from being reasonably away from city lights and industrial areas, this particular location was chosen in order to be closer to the Earth’s equator. Thus, coverage of both northern and southern hemispheres with equal ease becomes possible. Moreover, the longitudinal position of VBO is such that it is the only major astronomical facility between Australia and South Africa for observing the southern celestial objects [2].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;establishment-of-vbo&quot;&gt;Establishment of VBO&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VBO traces its root far back in history. I shall discuss here in brief about how it was established. The first astronomical observatory in India was established at Madras (now Chennai) in 1786 by the East India Company “for promoting the knowledge of astronomy, geography and navigation in India.” It became the premier institute in India for works on the fundamental positions of stars during the 19th century.  A catalogue of 11, 015 southern hemisphere stars was produced by the Madras observatory in 1843 under the guidance of T.G. Taylor, the then Director of the observatory. This is the famous Madras Catalogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research in planetary science and stellar astronomy at the Madras Observatory reached its peak during the latter half of the 19th century, under the leadership of Norman Pogson, the Director of the observatory during 1861-1891. With his Indian assistants Pogson measured accurately the positions of around 50, 000 stars, discovered six variable stars and six asteroids during this period. In 1867, an Indian astronomer, Chintamani Ragoonathacharry (1838-1932), an assistant of Pogon, discovered a variable star– R Reticuli. This is probably the first recorded astronomical discovery by an Indian in the era of telescopes.  Then, during the Total Solar Eclipse on August 18, 1868, the first spectroscopes were used to observe an eclipse event. So this eclipse became an important landmark which signaled the birth of solar physics in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Pogson’s death (June 23, 1891), initiatives were taken to establish a separate solar physics observatory. Following the decision, Kodaikanal Solar Observatory was established at Kodaikanal, Tamilnadu within few years. It started working officially on April 1, 1899. However, due to the climate it was understood that Kodaikanal can provide very few nights available for observation. In 1945, the Government of India appointed a committee, chaired by the eminent physicist Meghnad Saha which started planning the post-war development of astronomy in India. Manali Kallat Vainu Bappu, a great visionary who took over as the director of the Kodaikanal Observatory in 1960 knew that Kodaikanal is not a suitable place for stellar research. However, establishing an observatory for stellar studies and optical astronomy was the dream of M.K. Vainu Bappu. So he led a search since 1962 for finding a suitable site in southern India for establishing an optical observatory. He succeeded in finding a sleepy little hamlet i.e. Kavalur in the Javadi Hills as a suitable site for establishing optical telescopes for observing celestial objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observations began in 1968 with a 38 cm telescope made in the backyard of the Kodaikanal Observatory [3]. Then in 1971, a fully autonomous research institute was formed under complete funding from the Government of India, which came to be known as the Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA) [4]. Located in Bangalore, IIA took over the VBO facility henceforth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;facilities-at-vbo-2-5-6&quot;&gt;Facilities at VBO &lt;i&gt;&lt;sub&gt;[2, 5, 6]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presently, VBO boosts of a number of sophisticated telescopes and asoociated instruments for looking at the heavens. The historical 1-m Carl Zeiss reflecting telescope, the 2.34-m Vainu Bappu Telescope, the recently installed 1.3-m J.C. Bhattacharya Telescope forms the major facilities. The first telescope was of 38 cm (15-inch) aperture, with which astronomical observations were started in 1968 at VBO. Later, a 75 cm (30-inch) telescope was completely designed and fabricated at the workshops of the IIA. It is still used for observations at VBO. Another 45-cm aperture joined the arsenal within few years. In recent years, one more telescope, known as the ‘DIMM Telescope’ also stands tall in the campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: The DIMM Telescope at the VBO site (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vainu_Bappu_Observatory#/media/File:15-inch_telescope_seen_from_the_40-inch_telescope_at_Vainu_Bappu_Observatory.JPG&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;credit&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in 1972, a 1.02-m (primary mirror diameter) class reflecting telescope made by Carl Zeiss Jena was installed at VBO. Having the Ritchey-Chretien F/13 optical configuration, this remained as one of the primary facility for observing celestial objects for over a decade. It is working fully till now and is attached with two instruments for observations, a stellar optical polarimeter and the Universal Astronomical Grating Spectrograph (UAGS). Anyone of them can be used at a time attaching with the telescope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav/image3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: The historic 1-m (40-inch) telescope at VBO (credit: author)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on January 6, 1986, another 2.34-m (93 inch) diameter reflecting telescope was inaugurated in the observatory. Completely designed and built in India, this telescope project was started by Vainu Bappu. However, he passed away in 1982 and could not see the successful installation and working of this dream telescope. On January 6, 1986, the observatory was renamed as the Vainu Bappu Observatory and the 2.3-m telescope as ‘Vainu Bappu Telescope’ (VBT) [6]. It remained as the largest telescope in Asia until a 3.6-meter telescope was set up at Devasthal, near Nainital, by ARIES. It is majorly used for deep sky observations including stars and galaxies currently using two instruments at prime focus. It is operated as a national facility and attracts proposals from all over the country and occasionally from abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on January 6, 1986, another 2.34-m (93 inch) diameter reflecting telescope was inaugurated in the observatory. Completely designed and built in India, this telescope project was started by Vainu Bappu. However, he passed away in 1982 and could not see the successful installation and working of this dream telescope. On January 6, 1986, the observatory was renamed as the Vainu Bappu Observatory and the 2.3-m telescope as ‘Vainu Bappu Telescope’ (VBT) [6]. It remained as the largest telescope in Asia until a 3.6-meter telescope was set up at Devasthal, near Nainital, by ARIES. It is majorly used for deep sky observations including stars and galaxies currently using two instruments at prime focus. It is operated as a national facility and attracts proposals from all over the country and occasionally from abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: The 2.34-m Vainu Bappu Telescope (VBT) at VBO (credit: author)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recent addition to these existing facilities is the 1.3-m aperture J.C. Bhattacharya Telescope, popularly known as the JCBT. It was installed in April 2014 and was named after the ex-Director of VBO, Dr. Jagadish Chandra Bhattacharya. Possessing a Ritchey-Chretien F/8 optical configuration, JCBT has three instrument ports. The main port consists a 2k x 4k CCD system for direct imaging purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav/image5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 5: The 1.3-m JCBT at the VBO campus (credit: https://www.iiap.res.in/vbo.htm)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;major-discoveries-and-research-highlights&quot;&gt;Major discoveries and research highlights&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contributions of VBO in astronomy are immense. This included some major discoveries which are discussed below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 1-m telescope started producing fruitful results just within few months after it began operation in January, 1972. In June, 1972, it discovered the presence of a thin atmosphere around Ganymede, the largest satellite of Jupiter [7].&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In March, 1977, rings of Uranus were discovered by J. C. Bhattacharya (Director of VBO after M. K. Vainu Bappu) and his colleagues while observing through the same telescope [8].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav/image6.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 6: News on confirmation of the rings of Uranus published in Deccan Herald newspaper on April 28, 1981 (credit:http://prints.iiap.res.in/bitstream/handle/2248/1059/E7.2.pdf;jsessionid=F7FDBA92400FD589617ED58C49E0ED30?sequence=1)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then in 1984, the discovery of a thin outer ring around Saturn was reported by VBO using the same telescope [9].&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another important discovery was made using the 45 cm Schmidt telescope. On February 17, 1988, a new minor planet was discovered by a team of six astronomers led by R. Rajamohan [10]. It was a part of a special search program for asteroids called ‘Project Kalki’. Later, this asteroid was named ‘4130 Ramanujan’ after the legendary Indian mathematician Srinivasa Ramanujan. This became the first discovery of an asteroid from the Indian soil in the 20th century.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav/image7.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 7: Discovery of the asteroid Ramanujan published in Current Science journal in 1989 
(credit:http://prints.iiap.res.in/bitstream/handle/2248/3975/Discovery%20of%20asteroid%20number%204130?sequence=3&amp;amp;isAllowed=y)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another notable work performed from VBO was to survey the stars of the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC) galaxy using ultraflow dispersion spectroscopy. Moreover, astronomers of IIA started observing the famous supernova of 1987, i.e. SN1987A in LMC within 48 hours of the discovery. Observing this supernova in details using both 1-m and the 75 cm telescopes, despite its low elevation in the southern sky, proved the importance of the geographic location of Kavalur. Apart from these major achievements, front-line research is carried out at VBO in present days also, using different focal plane instrument facilities. Research at VBO focuses in observing and studying most of the areas of optical astronomy viz. solar system objects, stars, star clusters, galaxies, stellar explosions, blazars, optical imaging of gamma-ray burst fields, etc. Communication facilities via the VSAT satellite connection are available for every user for the telescopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;vbo-and-me-a-personal-account&quot;&gt;VBO and me: a personal account&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large number of Indian observational astronomers owe a lot to VBO. Many of the major projects leading to PhD by observational Indian astronomers have been carried out using data obtained from the VBT, or at least any one telescope facility from VBO. I am also one among those numerous researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My official tie-up with VBO started since October, 2017. Being an MPhil scholar of astrophysics at the CHRIST (Deemed to be University), I started observing a carefully selected sample of classical Be (Be hereafter) stars using the historical 1-m telescope at VBO. It was a study where I, my supervisor and co-supervisor collaborated with IIA. Continuous monitoring of these stars was necessary for few years to study the disc formation and dissipation timescales in Be stars. I fell in love with the serene beauty, wonderful co-operative staff members of the campus from the very first days. And then started a never forgettable journey of my life. The same project became a part of my PhD thesis which I led as the Principal Investigator since February 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2017, we received over 150 nights of observation to obtain the spectra for our selected stars. A total of 61 nights I myself have stayed at VBO doing the observations, which would have definitely increased if COVID19 did not hit the world. I can truly say that these 61 nights of my life were among the best ones I have experienced. It was during my stay at Kavalur I was able to work for over 12 hours a day, in a calm and quiet place without any man-made disturbances. This was the place where I was able to complete a major portion of my analysis works related to MPhil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav/image8.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 8: The 1-m telescope visible from the balcony of VBT at Kavalur observatory (credit: author)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole night of observations was a routine schedule when the only sound was originated from the chirpings of monkeys, and the murmurs of insects mixed with an un-describable drizzling sound of leaves of trees due to mild breeze. Morning arrived with excellent views of sunrise and amazing roars of innumerable birds. The days passed by mostly sleeping and taking care of my belongings from the anytime invaders – the monkeys. Occasional appearance of scorpions and snakes was also not something unusual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav/image9.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 9: Morning arrives after a night’s observations using the 1-m telescope. The moon is still visible in the sky
(credit: author)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most beautiful periods of spending at VBO, I presume, is during the summers, especially April. Apart from clear skies, almost the entire campus becomes colorful with the arrival of flowers in the treetops. For me, working in such an environment was like a childhood dream come true, a dream which turned to love and then into passion ultimately setting my aim – to become an observational astronomer studying the stars. I do cherish these wonderful days spent in the midst of telescopes, jungles, warm people and serene nature while working for my MPhil and then PhD. As an astronomer in near future, I would definitely love to maintain my attachment with VBO, forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav/image10.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 10: A colorful view of the VBO campus during summer time. VBT is  visible from the balcony of the 1-m telescope (credit: author)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rapid development of technology, presently we are actually standing in a golden era of astronomy. Apart from the VBO, India currently possesses several world-class research institutes and observatories carrying high-classresearches in astronomy. One such observatory is the Indian astronomical Observatory (IAO) located in the remote village of Hanle, Ladakh in the Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir district. Situated at a height of 4, 517 meters from the sea level, this place was found to be a world-class astronomical site for establishing a large optical telescope. IAO was started in 2001 and contains the 2-m (200-cm) aperture Himalayan Chandra Telescope (HCT), which was dedicated to the nation in August 2001. Like the VBO, IAO is also operated by IIA, Bangalore. The HCT facility can be operated from a remote control centre at Hoskote, around 35 km from Bangalore, making it one of the most powerful remote controlled telescope facility of the world. The HCT is being used to study several types of celestial objects and phenomenon including stellar spectroscopy, galactic and extra-galactic star forming regions, young stellar objects, star clusters, supernova, gamma-ray bursts, etc. During the past decade, different other facilities such as the 0.7-m wide field robotic telescope (under the GROWTH project), Himalayan Gamma Ray Array (HAGAR), imaging Cherenkov telescope (MACE) have come up due to the infrastructure developed by IIA at the IAO site. The site is also being characterized for another 10-m class telescope which is a future project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participation in international projects was also envisaged in the Astronomy and Astrophysics “Decadal Vision Document 2004” sponsored by the Indian Academy of Sciences and the Astronomical Society of India. Development and successful operation of ASTROSAT - India’s first astronomy satellite was a major achievement in the past decade. Moreover, India is now playing an active role in participating in different future world class megaprojects related to astronomy. India-TMT, LIGO-India, SKA (Square Kilometer Array) are some such highly ambitious projects, whereas Aditya L1, NLST, INSIST, Gaganyaan are some of the future space missions to study various objects and phenomenon of the universe. Plans to send future missions to the Moon and Mars are also under consideration. Hence, one can understand that India’s future in astronomy seems truly promising. Now, it is up to the intellect of motivated young Indians whether we will be able to exploit these facilities fully and hence, will be able to carry forward the astronomy tradition of India or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Becoming an Astronomer; Gourav Banerjee; Palmview Publishing; 2018&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Telescopes in India; Mohan Sundara Rajan; National Book Trust; 2009&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.iiap.res.in/?q=history.htm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Kavalur comes of age”; The Times of India; January 20, 1986; Retrieved August 28, 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.iiap.res.in/vbo.htm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Vainu Bappu Observatory”; Vellore District Website; Vellore District Administration; Government of Tamil Nadu; Archived from the original on February 22, 2015; Retrieved August 28, 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Carlson, R. W. et al., 1973; Science; 182: 53&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bhattacharyya, J. C., Kuppuswamy, K., 1977, Nature, 267, 331&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vasundhara, R. et al., “Possible Detection of a Ring System in Saturn’s Magnetosphere”. Nature; 1984; 312; 5995; pp. 621–623&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rajamohan, R. et al.; “Discovery of asteroid number 4130”; Current Science; 1989; 58; 18; pg. 998&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; CHRIST (Deemed to be University), Bangalore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/vainu_bappu_telescope_town_gourav</guid>
        
        
        <category>General articles (in any of the above categories)</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
