<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> Welcome to CosmicVarta.</title>
    <description> Platform for promoting Indian astronomy research to the public.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 00:45:43 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 00:45:43 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aditya-L1: India&apos;s Array of Instruments on a Journey Closer to the Sun, Continuing a Legacy of Space Excellence</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Sun has fascinated mankind since the dawn of civilization. From famines to fertile farms, every aspect of life on Earth was defined by it. Unaware of the true nature of the Sun, humans have worshipped this mighty celestial being for thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was not until 400 years ago, when Galileo first looked at the Sun through his telescope, that humans realized the Sun is very dynamic and has its style of fluctuations. This triggered the genesis of observing the Sun by the ‘scientific method’. Over this time, we have realized that the Sun has several layers in its atmosphere and that they look very different when observed at different wavelengths. This led us to the pursuit of understanding the sun’s activity in its various layers, from the photosphere to the outer atmosphere and further out in space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable these studies, several organizations all over the globe have established telescopes on the ground and in space. India has been a part of this huge network of observatories, with contributions from telescopes like MAST at Udaipur Solar Observatory, radio observations with the Ooty Radio Telescope and Gauribandur Radio Observatory, and the rich historical data of the Sun from the Kodaikanal Observatory, spanning over three solar cycles. India is next venturing into space to observe the Sun with its first dedicated space-based solar observatory, Aditya-L1. It will be traveling to the Sun-Earth Lagrange 1 point, making the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO) the third space agency to send a spacecraft to L1, after NASA, ESA, and the Chinese CNSA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spacecraft will be placed in a halo orbit around L1, located 1.5 million km from the Earth towards the Sun. One might wonder why there’s a need to observe the Sun from space when it’s feasible to do so from the Earth. While ground-based observations rely on the prevailing atmospheric conditions at the observation site, they are also limited in continuous monitoring. The Earth’s atmosphere scatters the incoming sunlight, causing the day sky to be bright and blue, making the million times fainter corona of the Sun invisible from the Earth’s surface. The corona is made visible by a total solar eclipse, however, restricting the duration of observation to a couple of minutes. Moreover, the atmosphere cuts a significant portion of UV light and charged particles from the Sun, necessary to support life on the surface of the Earth. Therefore, uninterrupted observation of the solar corona and UV radiance and detection of the charged particle flux from the Sun justify the need for a space-based vantage point at L1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/aditya_l1/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: A schematic diagram of Aditya-L1 Payloads (credits: ISRO)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aditya-l1-payloads&quot;&gt;Aditya-L1 Payloads&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aditya-L1 has a collection of 7 instruments to study various aspects of the Sun. ASPEX, PAPA and MAG are in-situ in nature, which detects multiple conditions happening locally at the L1 vantage point. In contrast, VELC, SUIT, SoLEXS and HEL1OS detect the real-time activity on the Sun, making them ex-situ in nature. The significance and functionality of the various payloads are discussed in detail in the coming sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;visible-emission-line-coronagraph-velc&quot;&gt;Visible Emission Line Coronagraph (VELC)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visible Emission Line Coronagraph (VELC) is a payload on Aditya-L1 with simultaneous imaging and spectroscopic diagnostics capability. VELC contains a multi-slit spectrograph that will perform spectral observation in three visible emission lines, 5303 Å, 7892 Å, and 10747 Å, which are emitted at very high temperatures when iron loses many of its electrons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/aditya_l1/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 2: The imaging (3 Rⵙ) and spectroscopic (1.5 Rⵙ) field of view of VELC along with the slits. (Credits: IIA)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field of view of VELC starts from 1.05 Rⵙ (1.05 Solar Radius), close to the solar limb, and it can perform spectroscopic measurement in corona up to 1.5 Rⵙ. Furthermore, VELC can diagnose temperature at slit positions, using intensity ratio of spectral lines and magnetic field using spectropolarimetry observations. These unique capabilities of VELC will help us to understand the initiation mechanism of Coronal Mass Ejections (CMEs) and the forces responsible for their evolution in the corona, which still needs to be fully understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solar-ultraviolet-imaging-telescope-suit&quot;&gt;Solar Ultraviolet Imaging Telescope (SUIT)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Solar Ultraviolet Imaging Telescope (SUIT) is an off-axis Ritchey-Chretien type telescope built to observe the sun in eight narrow and three broad bandpasses within the 200-400 nm wavelength spectrum. The specific scientific targets of these filters are tabulated below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table style=&quot;width:100%; border-collapse: collapse;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;th style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Spectral Channel (nm)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Solar Feature&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Bandpass (nm)&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB1- 214&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Photosphere&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;11.55&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB2- 276.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Wing of MgII K line&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;~0.4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB3- 279.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Mg II k line&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;~0.4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB4- 280.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Mg II h line&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;~0.4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB5- 283.2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Wing of Mg II h line&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;~0.4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB6- 300&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Sunspots&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB7- 388&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Lower Photosphere&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB8- 396.85&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Ca II line&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;0.1&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;BB1- 200-242&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Continuum&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;BB2- 242-300&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;O3v Hartley Band&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;BB3- 320-360&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;O3 Hartley-Huggins Band&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SUIT is designed to continuously take images of the sun in all of its 11 scientific bandpasses every two hours. Additionally, SUIT has the capability for 2x2 on-chip binning and shall take binned full disk images in the Mg-II h band every minute for a more dynamic view. It also enables user-defined region of interest (RoI) selection, enabling the possibility for a faster cadence while observing a small area of the Sun. SUIT has a pixel resolution of 0.7”/pixel, comparable to that of SDO/AIA (0.6”/pixel) and SDO/HMI (0.5”/pixel), making it easy to co-align them without much rescaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SUIT electronics offer high flexibility and come packed with a “Flare mode” dedicated to observing the emergence of a solar flare in NUV. So, it has the means to detect a solar flare in its early stages and image them as they develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aditya-solar-wind-particle-experiment-aspex&quot;&gt;Aditya Solar Wind Particle EXperiment (ASPEX)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ASPEX is an in-situ payload with multi-directional data acquisition capabilities. Within ASPEX, there are two distinct subsystems: SWIS (Solar Wind Ion Spectrometer) and STEPS (SupraThermal and energetic Particle Spectrometer), comprising two and six units, respectively. The principal research aim of SWIS is to analyze solar wind plasma particles, while STEPS focuses on examining suprathermal and solar energetic particles (Goyal et al. 2018). Multiple units of these spectrometers are strategically mounted across the spacecraft to enable simultaneous measurements from various directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novelty of ASPEX lies in its multi-directional, high-cadence, and proton-alpha differentiated measurements. SWIS will continually monitor low-energy (100 eV - 20 keV) proton and alpha particles individually in radial and azimuthal directions and integrated flux in the meridional direction. It possesses an extensive field of view (FOV) of 360 degrees in and across the ecliptic plane, along with a modest latitudinal coverage of 6 degrees. Conversely, STEPS will measure higher-energy (20 keV/n - 5 MeV/n) ion flux from six directions: Sun-radial, Intermediate, Parker Spiral, North Pointing, South Pointing, and Earth Pointing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This unique payload, developed by the Physical Research Laboratory (PRL), Ahmedabad, will contribute to our understanding of solar wind ion variations and aid in identifying their source mechanisms. It will be especially valuable in studying the variation in ion abundance ratios during transient events like CME, CIR, and interplanetary shocks. Additionally, it will effectively examine the variations and disparities in the thermal anisotropy of protons and alpha particles. Moreover, it will be crucial to explore the origins of suprathermal particles in the solar wind and their association with SEPs. Its specialized design will also allow for the assessment of the role of Earth’s bow shock in generating suprathermal particles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plasma-analyser-package-for-aditya-l1-papa&quot;&gt;Plasma Analyser Package for Aditya L1 (PAPA)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PAPA is another in-situ payload on the spacecraft and is engineered by the Space Physics Laboratory (SPL) at VSSC, Thiruvananthapuram. This payload consists of two subsystems: the Solar Wind Electron Energy Probe (SWEEP) and the Solar Wind Ion Composition Analyser (SWICAR). Both sensors are mounted perpendicularly to each other and share a unified processing unit within the same chassis. PAPA will be instrumental in studying the composition and energy distribution of solar wind particles. The payload is specifically designed to investigate the velocity distribution and temperature anisotropy of solar wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;magnetometer-mag&quot;&gt;Magnetometer (MAG)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fluxgate Magnetometer (MAG) is one of three in-situ payloads on the Aditya L1 spacecraft, alongside ASPEX and PAPA. This triaxial magnetic sensor is mounted on a 6-meter, 5-segment deployable boom and is situated on the Sun-facing deck of the spacecraft. One set of MAG sensors is located at the tip of the boom, while a second set is positioned midway along the boom, 3 meters from both the tip and the spacecraft. This payload was developed by the Laboratory of Electro-Optics Systems (LEOS) in Bangalore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This apparatus renders the Aditya L1 spacecraft a comprehensive observational platform. It enhances the data collected by other in-situ payloads on board, providing measurements of both the magnitude and direction of the interplanetary magnetic field. The primary aim of MAG is to investigate the magnetic characteristics of the surrounding solar wind as well as transient phenomena like Corotating Interaction Regions (CIR) and Coronal Mass Ejections (CME) at the Sun-Earth L1 point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solexs&quot;&gt;SoLEXS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoLEXS is a soft X-ray spectrometer built to detect an energy range of 1 keV to 22 keV at a resolution of 250 eV (at 6 keV and &amp;lt; 0 deg C). This signifies that spectral features separated by 250 eV can be distinctly detected. Two apertures of 10 mm^2 and 0.1 mm^2 provide a field of view of 1.8 sq deg and 1.3 sq deg, respectively, with two separate silicon drift detectors to cover from A class to X class flares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hel1os&quot;&gt;HEL1OS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEL1OS, on the other hand, operates in the 10-150 keV range, with a significant spectral overlap with SoLEXS. Aimed at detecting hard X-rays, it offers a spectral resolution of 1 keV at 13.81 keV through its CdTe detector and ~7 keV at 59.5 keV through its CZT detector. The X-rays are collimated by a stainless steel collimator, giving the payload a field of view of 6 x 6 degrees. It is the only payload mounted inside the panels of the satellite, increasing the criticality severalfold. It was necessary to first mount HEL1OS and close the satellite body. Other payloads and equipment could be mounted on the panels. Thus, any modifications in the HEL1OS would require removing all the payloads and sensitive equipment on the satellite and opening the satellite body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoLEXS and HEL1OS shall operate both as independent payloads, and their functionality shall be augmented with SUIT for early detection of solar flares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If seen in a broader sense, all the payloads on board Aditya-L1 shall simultaneously observe the Sun and make in-situ and ex-situ measurements. The data from SUIT can be combined with VELC to get a broad view of the Sun, from the photosphere to the corona. Additionally, augmentation of SoLEXS and HEL1OS triggers with SUIT electronics can help detect flares at an early stage for faster imaging and flare emergence (Sarkar et al., Poster, ASI 2022). This nature of several instruments augmenting the functionality of several others gives us the ability to generate scientifically exclusive data, keeping the true spirit of an observatory class mission alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/aditya_l1/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 3: Field of view of VELC and SUIT. Correlation of NUV solar photosphere and chromosphere with solar corona (Credits: Sreejith P., SUIT Team/ MCNS.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/strong&gt; The article has been jointly authored by Arpit Kumar Shrivastav of ARIES, Nainital, Janmejoy Sarkar of IUCAA, Pune and Tezpur University, along with Prateek Mayank of IIT Indore. Arpit primarily works on the observations of magnetohydrodynamic waves in the solar corona. Janmejoy is a research fellow and was responsible for the optical alignment, mechanical integration, calibration and complete optical testing of the SUIT payload onboard Aditya-L1. Prateek, a Prime Minister’s Research Fellow working on the MHD simulation of solar wind and CME, extends his gratitude for the invaluable support received from Dr. Dibyendu Chakrabarty of PRL, Ahmedabad, the Principal Investigator of ASPEX. We are also thankful to Abhilash Sarwade of the Space Astronomy Group, URSC, ISRO, one of the prime members of the SoLEXS team, for helping us with critical information about SoLEXS and HEL1OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/aditya_l1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/aditya_l1</guid>
        
        <category>International</category>
        
        <category>India</category>
        
        <category>ISRO</category>
        
        <category>Aditya-L1</category>
        
        <category>Sun</category>
        
        <category>Solar exploration</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Origin of ultra-bright blazar emissions: An astronomer’s glimpse into cosmic volcanoes</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Blazars are a rare class of active galactic nuclei (AGN), in which the jets are pointed directly toward our line of sight, making them one of the brightest yet extremely compact sources. Relativistic effects such as beaming makes the jet emission the dominant component. Blazars exhibit multiwavelength variability across several timescales (varying from hours to years). However, the location of the emission region with respect to the central engine is an open question. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.515.1655B/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barat et. al (2022)&lt;/a&gt; try to address this question by combining information from multiwavelength variability of a sample of 11 blazars. Comparing the energy of the detected flares in multiple wavelength bands to state-of-the-art numerical models we put constraints on the location of the emission region.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-blazars&quot;&gt;What are blazars?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blazars are the most luminous non-transient objects known in the universe; they often emit across all electromagnetic bands from radio all the way to gamma-rays, which is unlike any other astrophysical source studied till date. Blazars also exhibit multiwavelength variability over timescales of a few hours to months and years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every galaxy is known to host a super massive black hole (SMBH, weighing a million to billion times more than our Sun) at its center. Sometimes, these giant monsters can feed off gas in the interstellar medium by forming large accretion disks. These accretion disks convert the gravitational potential energy of the infalling material to electromagnetic radiation, making them extremely bright, outshining the entire galaxy consisting of billions of stars. The inner compact region of a galaxy hosting a supermassive black hole is only a few astronomical units (AU) in size (roughly the scale of the solar system), which is negligible compared to the rest of the galaxy, which can be tens of thousands of light years across (1 ly = 63421 AU). Thus, a compact yet extremely luminous inner region of a galaxy, powered by the accretion of the SMBH at its heart is called an Active Galactic Nucleus (AGN). It has been observed that in roughly 10% of the cases, these AGNs are accompanied by large scale jets or outflows, orthogonal to the accretion disk which can extend as far out as thousands of light years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Artists’ impression of accretion black hole. &lt;em&gt;Credits: European Space Agency (ESA)&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the unification model proposed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1995PASP..107..803U/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Urry and Padovani (1995)&lt;/a&gt;, blazars are a sub-class of AGNs, where the jets are pointed towards our line of sight (see Figure 1). The jets are composed of ultra-relativistic plasma powered by the accretion energy and are launched very close to the SMBH. The situation is comparable to staring down the vent of an active volcano; because of relativistic effects, the radiation from the jet is beamed towards us making it extremely bright and outshining the contribution from any other region of the SMBH. Infact, most of the extragalactic high energy (gamma-ray) radiation we detect can be attributed to blazars. Till date, we have detected over 2000 blazars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: A schematic diagram showing the AGN unification model &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1995PASP..107..803U/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Urry and Padovani (1995)&lt;/a&gt;. The central Super Massive Black Hole (SMBH) is powered by the infalling material through the accretion disk. The AGN is also accompanied by fast and slow moving gas clouds in its vicinity (Broad-Line and Narrow-Line regions respectively) and a relativistic plasma jet launched close to the SMBH. The existence of a distant gas-dust envelope, called the torus is also known for such objects. Depending on the orientation of the SMBH with respect to our line of sight, we perceive it as a different object. In blazars, the jet is oriented along our line of sight, the entire emission is dominated by the beamed radiation from the jet, making them the brightest non-transient objects in the universe. &lt;em&gt;Image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1412.1177&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Reynolds et. al (2014)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;characterizing-a-blazar&quot;&gt;Characterizing a blazar&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two generic characteristics of blazar emissions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blazars are known to be highly variable sources, exhibiting variability across all wavelengths and a wide array of timescales starting from hours to months and years. A typical time-series of blazars (see Figure 2) shows `flares’ or sporadic outbursts of varying amplitudes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blazars have a characteristic double-peaked spectral energy distribution (SED), with a lower energy peak around optical-UV frequencies and a higher energy peak around X-rays and gamma rays (see Figure 3).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variability seen in blazar light curves is explained by the rapid energization of the underlying plasma. The reason for such rapid acceleration is an active area of research. However, the rapid acceleration and subsequent cooling of the plasma can explain the ‘outbursts’ we observe in the blazar lightcurves. The shape of the SED points towards non-thermal modes of emission (i.e., not like a blackbody spectrum which results from a thermalized object like a star).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lower energy peak in the SED can be explained by synchrotron emission by the relativistic plasma particles (electrons, positrons or possibly even protons).  In the presence of a magnetic field, charged particles are known to ‘gyrate’ due to Lorentz force, and as a result emit electromagnetic radiation (Maxwell’s laws predict that charged particles produce electromagnetic radiation). In the relativistic limit, this radiation due to charged particles is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.exul.ru/education/1/Note3f.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;synchrotron emission&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The higher energy peak is produced due to inverse-Compton scattering of low energy photons by the same ultra-relativistic particles in the plasma which produce the synchrotron emission. As photons interact with charged particles, there is an exchange of energy and momentum between them. In the low energy regime, the photon imparts energy to the charged particle (Compton scattering), however if the charged particle is ultra-relativistic, it can upscatter the low energy photon to very high energies &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.exul.ru/education/1/Note3f.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Inverse Compton scattering)&lt;/a&gt;. In this process, low energy optical photons can be energized to X-rays/gamma-rays producing the second peak in blazar SEDs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 2: Gamma-ray time-series observations of well known blazars 3C-279 (upper panel), PKS-1510-089 (middle panel) and PKS 2155-304 (bottom panel) taken using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fermi.gsfc.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fermi telescope&lt;/a&gt;. The red circles represent the observed flux. The time series is characterized by multiple sporadic outbursts or flares of varying sizes and durations. The entire lightcurve can be decomposed into a cumulative effect of a number of such flares (green spikes) and each flaring activity could be connected to an energy injection event within the jet. Blazars exhibit such variability across a wide range of electromagnetic frequencies (radio, IR, optical and X-rays) and often such multiwavelength variability is found to be correlated. &lt;em&gt;Image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/482/1/743/5126366&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Roy et. al (2019)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 3: The observed spectral energy distribution (SED) of the blazar Mrk 421 &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2011ApJ...736..131A/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Abdo et. al 2011)&lt;/a&gt;. The lower energy peak around the optical-UV wavelengths is attributed to synchrotron emission and the higher energy peak (X-ray/𝝲-ray) can be explained using the inverse-Compton mechanism (See text for detailed explanation).  This double humped SED is a universal characteristic of all blazars. &lt;em&gt;Image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.08401&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tavecchio 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;where-does-the-blazar-emission-originate&quot;&gt;Where does the blazar emission originate?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The location of the emission site within a blazar jet is an open question; several astronomers have suggested that the emission region is located near the Broad Line Region (BLR) within ~1 parsec (3.26 lightyears) of the central SMBH. However, there is also strong evidence suggesting that the emission site could be located further downstream (1-10 parsec), for e.g., the detection of extremely high energy gamma-rays from these sources which would have been absorbed within the BLR and never made it to our telescopes. Therefore, a constraint on the location of the emission zone within a jet would be extremely important for refining our theoretical understanding of blazars and their emission mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.515.1655B/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barat et. al (2022)&lt;/a&gt; proposed a new and complimentary prescription to constrain the location of the emission region within the blazar’s jet. The same population of ultra-relativistic particles is responsible for both the synchrotron (low energy) and inverse-Compton (high energy) emission. Therefore, any outburst in high energy gamma-rays can be accompanied by a similar outburst in lower energies such as optical and such events can be considered to have originated at the same location. Such simulatemous outburst events are termed ‘flare pairs’ (see Figure 4). In this paper, we analyzed simultaneous gamma-ray light curves from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fermi.gsfc.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fermi space telescope&lt;/a&gt; and optical light curves from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.astro.yale.edu/smarts/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yale-SMARTS program&lt;/a&gt; for 11 blazars and identified 25 flare pairs. We found that the ratio of the energy dissipated in the optical to gamma-ray flares roughly varies between 1-10% (Figure 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high energy emission, coming from Inverse Compton scattering, requires a supply of low energy photons. This seed photon field could either be provided by the synchrotron photons produced within the jet itself, or could be externally supplied from the Broad-Line Region (BLR) and/or the molecular torus (See Figure 1). For lower energy blazars, up-scattering of the external seed field dominates the gamma-ray emission. The density and energy of the seed photon field is strongly distance dependent, therefore the location of the emission region with respect to the BLR and molecular torus determines the total energy output in the gamma-rays compared to optical frequencies.  We developed detailed numerical models to simulate blazar outbursts from optical to gamma-ray energies. The ratio of the optical to gamma-ray flare energies were estimated from the simulated light curves for a range of distances from near the BLR up to 10 parsecs (Figure 5). From this, we were able to conclude that for most of the flare pairs identified, the emission region was likely to be located farther away compared to the BLR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constraining the emission site of blazars has important implications for the underlying physics of these extreme objects. In this paper, we develop an idea to constrain the location of emission by comparing the energy dissipated in gamma-rays and optical frequencies for outburst events where we have simultaneous optical and gamma-ray flare detections. Our numerical models suggest that most of the events we detected are likely to have originated beyond the BLR region, close to the molecular torus. This approach is a novel and complementary approach to determine the emission location and application to a broader sample of blazar flare pairs is necessary to validate this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image6.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 4: Top: Simultaneous gamma-ray (upper panel) and optical (lower panel) light curves of the blazar PKS 2326-502 observed using the Fermi space telescope and in the Yale-SMARTS program, respectively (orange points). The decomposed flares in both the light curves are shown with red lines and the identified flare pairs are numbered. Bottom: Raxtio of observed energy ratio of optical and gamma-ray flares identified as ‘flare pairs’ for the sample of 11 blazars analyzed in this study. The ratio varies between 1-10% approximately. &lt;em&gt;Image:&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.515.1655B/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Barat et. al (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image7.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 5:  Dependence of optical to gamma-ray outburst energy ratio for ‘flare pairs’ simulated for the blazar PKS 2326-502. The position of the BLR and the molecular torus have been shown with blue dashed lines. The green dotted line shows the median value of the energy ratio observed for this blazar (Figure 4, right panel). The simulated light curves were generated using detailed numerical models of dominant emission mechanisms like synchrotron and inverse-Compton scattering. The simulations show that the observed energy ratio of the flare pairs is more consistent with an emission region located farther downstream of the jet from the BLR. &lt;em&gt;Image:&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.515.1655B/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Barat et. al (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Further resources&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fspas.2017.00006/full&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fspas.2017.00006/full&lt;/a&gt;
, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1986rpa..book.....R/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rybycki Lightman (1986)&lt;/a&gt;
, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2020mbhe.confE..35C/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Costamate 2020&lt;/a&gt;
, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4434/10/1/35&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Prandini 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.515.1655B/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Locating the GeV emission region in the jets of blazars from months time-scale multiwavelength outbursts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Saugata Barat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ritaban Chatterjee, Kaustav Mitra&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; 
Anton Pannekoek Institute for Astronomy, University of Amsterdam, Netherlands
Presidency University, Kolkata, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata</guid>
        
        <category>Active galactic nuclei</category>
        
        <category>jets</category>
        
        <category>blazars</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Ghost of a Star Screams 6 Days After Its Death</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dying heavy stars forms black holes and sometimes emit jets, producing very narrow-angle flashes of gamma rays known as Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs). This article summarises the findings from the follow-up of such a GRB 210204A. The GRB showed typical afterglow decaying behaviour while seen in optical bands for up to a week. However, about a week later, we detected some unusual brightening in the emission from this GRB. We investigate possible causes for this flaring and conclude that the most likely cause is a refreshed shock in the jet. The high energy properties suggest that GRB 210204A might not have any special properties that caused late-time flaring. Our analysis of the GRB 210204A shows that the late time bump in the light curve is likely due to the late time flaring activity. The flare of GRB 210204A is the latest flare detected to date.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A certain class of massive stars end their life in a violent explosion. As these massive stars end their life, they sometimes launch powerful jets during this process (~1.3 out of every 100) as if they are screaming as they take their last breath. These jets are very narrow-angle flashes of gamma rays known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma-ray_burstGamma-Ray&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs)&lt;/a&gt;. GRBs were discovered accidentally in 1967 while Vela satellites were looking for traces of nuclear tests on Earth and rather detected a very short duration burst (~10 sec) of gamma rays coming from space. Within a few years, astronomers were able to conclude that these events do not belong to our neighbourhood, nor to our solar system, nor to our Galaxy. GRBs are extragalactic and are detected from all directions in the universe. These jets are extremely powerful and emit as much energy as the Sun would emit in its entire lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last 20 years, various gamma-ray satellites have baeen launched to study these events. To date, we have detected over five thousand GRB events. The study of the full sample suggests that there exist two types of these GRBs: 1) Short Gamma-ray Bursts and 2) Long Gamma-ray bursts. 
As the name suggests, Short GRBs are very short in duration  (less than 2 seconds). Compact object merger events are mainly responsible for the majority of these bursts. These are mainly found in the outskirts of elliptical galaxies, where there is a high population of compact binary objects. On the other hand, Long Gamma-ray bursts originate from the death of massive stars. Arms of spiral galaxies where new stars are formed are the common sites of Long GRBs. In such regions, new stars are born and die (usually as a supernova) very quickly and thus have higher chances of being a promising site of Long GRBs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 4th Feb 2021, one such event, ‘GRB 210204A’, was detected by various gamma-ray satellites, including the first Indian multi-wavelength astronomy satellite ‘AstroSat’. A team of Indian astronomers studied this unusual event to explain its behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ghost_of_a_star_harsh/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: An artistic impression of Gamma-ray burst. &lt;em&gt;Credits: Anna Serena Esposito&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GRBs are among the brightest electromagnetic events in the Universe since the Big Bang. These bursts are highly energetic flashes of gamma rays and radiate ~10&lt;sup&gt;51-53&lt;/sup&gt; erg of energy within a few seconds. Interaction of these jets with the nearby interstellar medium (ISM) creates an afterglow that shines in all electromagnetic bands. As an analogy, you can think of the main GRB jet as burning coal with flames and the remaining embers as the afterglow, which shines for a longer time. The afterglow usually becomes fainter with time as the central engine stops. However, in some cases, a re-brightening in the afterglow is seen due to chaotic central engines. Such events are typically seen between seconds to hours after the main burst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GRB 210204A started looking like an ordinary GRB - steadily fading for a few days. But, after ~7 days, it showed rebrightening by a magnitude, not once but twice. This is very unusual for GRBs as there is no way a central engine could be active at this time. It is like a Diwali firecracker that goes boom and shows flashes again after an hour when no one is expecting it to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ghost_of_a_star_harsh/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 2 shows the luminosity decline (light curve) of GRB 210204A based on data from various Indian facilities. The re-brightening at ~12 days after the event is clear in the inset image when it deviates significantly from the expected power-law behaviour (red-dashed line).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team of astronomers from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iitb.ac.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IITB)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Astrophysics Bengaluru (IIA)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/aries-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES)&lt;/a&gt; and National Centre for Radio Astrophysics (NCRA), led by Harsh Kumar, PhD student at the Department of Physics of IITB, came together, with other international collaborators, to study GRB 210204A. They used various Indian facilities like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/growthindia/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GROWTH-India Telescope (GIT)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/?q=telescope_iao&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Himalayan Chandra Telescope (HCT)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/facilities/astronomical-telescopes/360cm-telescope/telescope&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Devasthal Optical Telescope (DOT)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/facilities/astronomical-telescopes/130cm-telescope&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Devasthal Fast Optical Telescope (DFOT)&lt;/a&gt; for optical data, AstroSat for gamma-ray data and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gmrt.ncra.tifr.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope (GMRT)&lt;/a&gt; for radio data to find plausible reasons behind the re-brightening of the afterglow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ghost_of_a_star_harsh/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 3 shows a comparison of the re-brightening time (along the y-axis) and relative flux of re-brightening in GRB 210204A, marked in red, with previously known GRB re-brightening events. It clearly indicates that GRB 210204A is the most delayed flaring detected so far.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors detected the most delayed flaring ever from a GRB event, explained as being caused by “Refreshed Shock”, where two shells with different speeds that were emitted almost simultaneously collided at later times. The findings are highly significant as they highlight complex behaviour in GRB events. This research, published in the Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society (MNRAS) journal, emphasised late-time monitoring and the need for multi-wavelength data to understand the nature of these events in further detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.07587&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The long-active afterglow of GRB 210204A: Detection of the most delayed flares in a Gamma-Ray Burst&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt;  Harsh Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt;  Rahul Gupta, Divita Saraogi, Tomás Ahumada, Igor Andreoni, G.C. Anupama, Amar Aryan, Sudhanshu Barway, Varun Bhalerao, Poonam Chandra, Michael W. Coughlin, Dimple, Anirban Dutta, Ankur Ghosh, Anna Y. Q. Ho, E. C. Kool, Amit Kumar, Michael S. Medford, Kuntal Misra, Shashi B. Pandey, Daniel A. Perley, Reed Riddle, Amit Kumar Ror, Jason M. Setiadi &amp;amp; Yuhan Yao&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IITB);  Main Gate Rd, IIT Area, Powai, Mumbai, Maharashtra 400076&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/ghost_of_a_star_harsh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/ghost_of_a_star_harsh</guid>
        
        <category>GRBs</category>
        
        <category>Optical</category>
        
        <category>Black Hole</category>
        
        <category>Compact Objects</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Looking at five radio-quiet AGN through the polarization lens</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This article discusses the results from our combined radio polarization and emission line study of five type-2 radio-quiet quasars. We investigate the origin of radio emission in these sources and understand what impact the local gaseous environments have on the nature of radio outflows in them. Our work further sheds light on the potential of using radio polarization as an efficient tool to look for signatures of AGN feedback in the relatively understudied class of radio-quiet AGN.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AGN are amongst the most energetic and extraordinarily radiant phenomena in the Universe. They are powered by supermassive black holes (SMBHs; with masses ranging between 106 − 1010 solar masses (M⊙)) that are actively accreting matter through an accretion disk and releasing tremendous amounts of energy in the form of radiation and outflows. While AGN exhibits a variety of classes, such as quasars, Seyfert galaxies, radio galaxies, blazars, etc., they all share some fundamental constituents, which include (see Figure 1): a SMBH at the center, an accretion disk, an X-ray emitting corona presumably located above the accretion disk, fast moving, dense gas clouds giving rise to the broad optical emission lines (broad line region or BLR), slow moving, relatively less dense gas clouds giving rise to the narrow optical emission lines, (narrow line region or NLR) and a doughnut-shaped torus of gas and dust (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781139170901&quot;&gt;Peterson, 1997&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1086/133630&quot;&gt;Urry &amp;amp; Padovani, 1995&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/five_agn_polarization_silpa/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: The standard model of AGN by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1086/133630&quot;&gt;Urry &amp;amp; Padovani, 1995&lt;/a&gt;. Figure taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1010.6281&quot;&gt;Khassen (2010)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AGN are classified as type-1 and -2 based on their optical spectra: type-1 AGN exhibit both broad and narrow emission lines while type-2 AGN exhibit only narrow emission lines. These differences have been suggested to arise as a result of the different viewing angles of the central engine (see Figure 1). The torus is believed to surround the central engine and obscure the BLR clouds from certain lines of sight (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.aa.31.090193.002353&quot;&gt;Antonucci, 1993&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1086/133630&quot;&gt;Urry &amp;amp; Padovani, 1995&lt;/a&gt;). The sources viewed edge-on (i.e, when the observer’s line of sight intersects the torus) are recognized as type-2 AGN while the sources viewed face-on are recognized as type-1 AGN. Quasars, which are known to be an extremely luminous and highly accreting class of AGN, have been traditionally associated with type-1 class. However, recent studies have identified a few type-2 quasars as well based on their optical spectra (for e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1086/133630&quot;&gt;Reyes et al., 2008&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1086/133630&quot;&gt;Mullaney et al., 2013&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, powerful and collimated structures of relativistic plasma, known as jets, are launched perpendicular to the black hole-accretion disk interface. In 10-20% of the AGN population, these jets extend over scales ranging from a few hundred kiloparsecs (kpc) to several megaparsecs (Mpc); this class is called radio-loud (RL) AGN. On the other hand, a vast majority of the AGN population (80−90%) launch weak and small-scale radio jets of typically less than 10 kpc in extent. They may, alternatively, host poorly collimated wind-like or bubble-like, diffuse radio outflows. These constitute the radio-quiet (RQ) class of AGN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/five_agn_polarization_silpa/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2. Diagram of synchrotron emission (https://emmaalexander.github.io/resources.html) by Emma Alexander/ CC BY 4.0 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AGN jets emit synchrotron radiation at radio frequencies. Synchrotron radiation is produced by relativistic charged particles spiraling around magnetic field lines, and is concentrated within a narrow cone pointing in the direction of the particle motion (see Figure 2). Synchrotron radiation is intrinsically linearly polarized in the plane perpendicular to the magnetic fields. Radio polarization observations can, therefore, provide information about the orderliness and orientation of the magnetic fields giving rise to the synchrotron emission. According to the synchrotron theory, the magnetic fields are inferred to be parallel to the electric polarization vectors for optically thick regions like the core, and perpendicular for optically thin regions like jets, lobes and hotspots. For ordered magnetic fields and optically thin regions, the maximum theoretical fractional polarization of synchrotron emission is expected to be 75%. However, in reality, since the magnetic fields also consist of a random component, the fractional polarization is observed to be typically lower than this intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, as the electromagnetic radiation passes through the region between the source and the observer, it interacts with the intervening magneto-ionic medium that consists of free charges and magnetic fields, resulting in the rotation of the plane of polarization of the electromagnetic wave. This effect is known as Faraday rotation (see Figure 3), which when coupled with other factors such as observing bandwidth and telescope beam could cause a further drop in the fractional polarization. The mechanisms causing depolarization (i.e., drop in the fractional polarization) of the radio emission can be broadly categorized as external and internal. The former (latter) refers to the case where the Faraday rotating medium is extrinsic (intrinsic) to the synchrotron emitting plasma (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/133.1.67&quot;&gt;Burn 1966&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-8711.1998.01782.x&quot;&gt;Sokoloff et al. 1998&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/five_agn_polarization_silpa/image3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Faraday rotation of a polarized electromagnetic wave as it propagates through the magneto-ionic medium. Figure taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stab1641&quot;&gt;Ferri`ere et al. (2021)&lt;/a&gt;.			 				 		
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘AGN feedback’ is a process by which AGN impact and regulate the growth and evolution of their host galaxies (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-astro-081811-125521&quot;&gt;Fabian, 2012&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-astro-082214-122316&quot;&gt;King &amp;amp; Pounds, 2015&lt;/a&gt; for details). AGN feedback is believed to shape the black hole-bulge mass relation, which is the correlation between the black hole mass and the luminosity (and mass) of the bulge component of the host galaxies. AGN feedback can have both positive and negative impacts on galaxy evolution. AGN feedback could either suppress star formation and thereby prevent inordinate growth of massive galaxies (called ‘negative feedback’) or could enhance star formation locally (called ‘positive feedback’). Traditionally, AGN feedback is known to come in two modes: (i) quasar-mode, which is typically associated with quasars that drive high-velocity winds capable of removing the star-forming fuel from host galaxies, and ultimately resulting in the shut-down of star-formation, and (ii) jet-mode, which is associated with low accretion rate AGN that launch large-scale jets capable of transferring the power mechanically and regulating star-formation. In order to develop a comprehensive picture of galaxy formation and evolution in the Universe, an in-depth understanding of AGN feedback is indispensable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AGN feedback has become an important constituent in the cosmological simulations of galaxy formation and evolution. However, finding observational signatures of this phenomenon is a challenging task and an active area of ongoing research. One way AGN can influence the gas in the host galaxies is through galactic-scale outflows that can transport matter and energy from the central engine to the host environments. It is widely believed that these outflows are driven by large-scale, powerful jets in RL AGN. However, whether these outflows are prevalent in RQ AGN, and if so, what drives them is still an unsettled question. Over these years, a lot of progress has been made in understanding how AGN feedback operates in RL AGN, but not so much in case of RQ AGN, with only a handful of them having been looked at so far. Yet, what is exciting even from these minimal studies is that despite lacking large-scale, powerful radio outflows, RQ AGN could be efficient agents of AGN feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limited AGN feedback studies in RQ AGN is a major setback in our attempts towards understanding how the Universe is working, since the majority of the AGN in the Universe are RQ. Probing AGN feedback in RQ AGN has been difficult because the radio emission in these sources can arise from a wide range of mechanisms like star formation, low-powered small-scaled jets, AGN/starburst winds, coronal emission, or even a combination of them with each of them being able to impact the interstellar medium (ISM) differently (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1038/s41550-019-0765-4&quot;&gt;Panessa et al. 2019&lt;/a&gt;, for details). Therefore, AGN feedback in RQ AGN becomes a two-fold problem: first probing the relative radio contributions from different emitters, and then determining their relative roles in driving galaxy-wide outflows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we have presented results from our 5 GHz B-array (resolution∼1 arcsec) Karl Jansky Very large Array (VLA) polarimetric observations in conjunction with the archival [O iii] images from the Hubble Space Telescope (HST) of five type-2 RQ quasars selected from the Quasar Feedback Survey sample (QFeedS; find out more about this survey at  &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.ncl.ac.uk/quasarfeedbacksurvey/&quot;&gt;the project website&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stab549&quot;&gt;Jarvis et al. 2021&lt;/a&gt;). This paper aims to establish the origin of radio emission (jet or wind) in these sources and the impact of the local gaseous environments on the nature of the radio outflows in them. This paper also explores the potential of using radio polarization as a tool to look for signatures of AGN feedback in these sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 5 sources that constitute our sample are: J0945+1737, J1000+1242, J1010+1413, J1356+1026, J1430+1339. These sources, from their previous studies of spatially resolved radio and [O iii] observations, are known to exhibit powerful and galactic-scale [O iii] outflows, prominent kpc-scale radio structures that are likely to be dominated by jet emission and a close association between radio emission and [O iii] emission. These sources, therefore, can serve as potential candidates to study the interplay of jets, winds and emission-line gas in the poorly studied class of RQ AGN. We used the Astronomical Image Processing System (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-astro-081811-125521&quot;&gt;AIPS&lt;/a&gt; ) and Common Astronomy Software Applications (&lt;a href=&quot;https://casaguides.nrao.edu/index.php/VLA_Continuum_Tutorial_3C391-CASA4.6&quot;&gt;CASA&lt;/a&gt; ) software to reduce and analyze the VLA data of our sources (see for details of the analysis &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stac1044&quot;&gt;Silpa et al. 2022 &lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results-and-discussion&quot;&gt;Results and Discussion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We detect polarization in 4 sources, viz. J0945+1737, J1000+1242, J1356+1026 and J1430+1339. This is a good detection fraction given that the sample is RQ. J1010+1413 is the only unpolarized source in our sample. The lack of polarization in this source could either be due to limited sensitivity of our observations or due to strong depolarization effects. In Figures 4 and 5, we present the VLA images of J0945+1737 and J1430+1339 (popularly known as “Teacup” quasar) respectively, at 5 GHz in the B-array configuration. The black contours represent VLA 5 GHz B-array total intensity image (with ~1 arcsec resolution), the red ticks represent the  polarization electric vectors (whose lengths are proportional to the linear polarized intensity), the gray-scale background represents HST [O iii] image and the cyan contours represent higher resolution (~0.25 arcsec) VLA 6 GHz A-array total intensity image (taken from &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stz556&quot;&gt;Jarvis et al. 2019 &lt;/a&gt;). Please refer to the original paper (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stac1044&quot;&gt;Silpa et al. 2022 &lt;/a&gt;) for similar images of other sources. Polarization is detected as discrete knots in these sources. The polarization vectors have the same orientation within each knot while they are different between the knots (see Figures 4 and 5). The polarized emission seems to be arising from compact regions with ordered B-fields. The radio cores exhibit about 0.5 − 1% fractional polarization, which is also typically expected for RL AGN, while the lobes reveal higher fractional polarization (10 − 30%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The higher resolution (i.e., ~0.25 arcsec) images of J0945+1737, J1000+1242, J1010+1413 and J1430+1339 show radio structures that resemble jets and hotspots. However, in the case of J1356+1026, the higher resolution imaging has only revealed a radio core. In addition, all 5 sources possess radio cores and lobes with steep to ultra-steep radio spectrum. The 4 sources that show polarization display complexities in their polarization structures as well as in the orientation of their inferred magnetic fields. Based on these results, we can deduce that the radio emission in J0945+1737, J1000+1242, J1010+1413 and J1430+1339 is likely to be originating from low power jets. These jets possess kinetic powers in the range of 10&lt;sup&gt;43&lt;/sup&gt; − 10&lt;sup&gt;44&lt;/sup&gt;  erg s&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; . However, we cannot fully discern the origin of radio emission (among jet or wind) in J1356+1026 with the current data. Please see Table 1 where we summarize the results for our individual sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Source name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Possible origin of radio emission&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Polarization detected?&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;J0945+1737&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Jet&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;J1000+1242&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Jet&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;J1010+1413&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Jet&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;J1356+1026&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Uncertain&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;J1430+1339&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Jet&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
Table 1: Summary of the results for individual sources.			 				 		
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/five_agn_polarization_silpa/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: VLA 5 GHz B-array (resolution∼ 1 arcsec) total intensity contours in black for J0945+1737 superimposed with polarization electric vectors (whose lengths are proportional to linear polarized intensity) in red, HST [O iii] image in gray-scale and VLA 6 GHz A-array (resolution∼ 0.25 arcsec) total intensity contours in cyan. 			 				 		
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/five_agn_polarization_silpa/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 5: Same as Figure 4, but for J1430+1339. 			 				 		
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous studies of these sources have shown that the radio emission spatially overlaps with [O iii] emission in them (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stz556&quot;&gt;Jarvis et al. 2019 &lt;/a&gt;). Our study suggests that the polarized knots more often do not spatially overlap with the [O iii] emission. Polarization is predominantly seen in regions of jets and lobes that have a dearth of [O iii] emission while it is mostly absent in regions dominated by [O iii] emission. Such a spatial anti-correlation between polarized radio emission and [O iii] emission has been observed in some of the RL AGN in the literature, and is often explained as a result of the depolarization of radio emission by the emission line gas. As already mentioned in the Introduction, this can happen in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(i) external depolarization, where the radio lobes of the source are surrounded by emission line gas clumps/clouds, with the typical sizes of these clumps being smaller than the telescope beam, (ii) internal depolarization, where the emission line gas entrained inside the radio lobes mixes with the synchrotron lobe plasma and depolarizes the lobe emission. In order to study the depolarization effects in greater detail, we modeled different depolarization mechanisms acting in the lobe of one of the sources: J0945+1737. This was done by fitting the sub-band polarization data for this source with the equations given in &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/133.1.67&quot;&gt;Burn 1966&lt;/a&gt; (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stac1044&quot;&gt;Silpa et al. 2022 &lt;/a&gt;, for details on fitting and analysis). This source was chosen since it was the only one (out of 4) that showed significant polarization in individual sub-band images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By modeling external depolarization of the lobe emission in J0945+1737, we obtained the size of the emission line gas clumps/clouds to be of the order of 10&lt;sup&gt;-5&lt;/sup&gt; pc. Interestingly, we also found that the range of the cloud sizes obtained for RQ AGN from our work (10&lt;sup&gt;-5&lt;/sup&gt; pc - 1300 pc) broadly spans the range derived for the lobes of the radio galaxies (which are RL AGN) in the literature (10&lt;sup&gt;-5&lt;/sup&gt; pc - 300 pc). By modeling internal depolarization of the lobe emission in J0945+1737, we estimated the amount of the thermal gas mixed with the synchrotron plasma in its lobe to be of the order of 106 M⊙. Similar studies have not been extensively carried out for RQ AGN in general, and this sample, in particular. However, our result agrees with the estimates of the ionized gas masses (∼ 10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; − 10&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt; M⊙) obtained for some of the Seyfert galaxies (which are RQ AGN) in the literature from optical spectroscopic and imaging studies. For comparison, in the lobes of the radio galaxies, much higher estimates of the mixed thermal gas masses (∼ 10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;− 10&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; M⊙) have been derived using X-ray and CO observations as well as radio polarization studies. We note that although there may be other reasons contributing to the spatial anti-correlation observed between the polarized radio emission and [O iii] emission, such as lack of telescope sensitivity and beam depolarization effects, the broad consistency found between the values derived from our work and the values reported in the literature gives us confidence in our argument regarding the role of the emission line gas in depolarizing the lobe emission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One caveat in this study is that while we find a clear spatial anti-correlation between polarized radio emission and [O iii] emission in most regions, we also find regions showing a correlation between them. Nevertheless, the number of polarized knots that spatially anti-correlate with [O iii] emission (8/12) is more than the number of knots that correlate (4/12). In Figures 4 and 5, we have only annotated the polarized knots that show an anti-correlation (i.e., J1 and J2 in J0945+1737 and J3, CJ1 and CJ2 in J1430+1339). The correlation could be explained as a result of the clump sizes of the depolarizing media being larger than the telescope beam or there not being enough mixing between the emission line gas and the synchrotron lobe plasma. It is also important to note that deeper multi-frequency and multi-resolution observations are needed to distinguish between internal and external depolarization effects more rigorously. Therefore, the current work using ∼ 2 GHz bandwidth data has limited implications. Yet, this study is promising in that it provides a first-order treatment of the depolarization mechanisms at play in the poorly studied class of RQ AGN and provides lower limits on the derived parameters, such as the cloud sizes and the mixed gas masses. We emphasize that the system is much more complex than the models used here, and more rigorous methods must be used instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this work, we have presented the results from our joint radio polarization and emission line study of 5 type-2 radio-quiet quasars. We find that the radio emission in J0945+1737, J1000+1242, J1010+1413 and J1430+1339 is likely to be jet-based depending on their morphological, spectral and polarization properties. However, the origin of radio emission (among jet or wind) in J1356+1026 cannot be ascertained with the current data. Polarization is detected in 4 out of 5 sources (J1010+1413 is unpolarized) as discrete knots with ordered magnetic fields. From previous studies, our sources are known to show a spatial coincidence between radio emission and [O iii] emission. Our study suggests that the polarized knots more often do not spatially coincide with [O iii] emission, similar to that seen in some of the radio-loud AGN in the literature. This suggests that the radio emission is likely to be depolarized by the emission line gas clouds surrounding the radio lobes, or by the emission line gas that has entrained inside the radio lobes and mixed with the synchrotron lobe plasma. For the case of J0945+1737, the size of the emission line gas clouds is found to be of the order of 10−5 pc, and the amount of the mixed thermal gas in its lobe is found to be of the order of 106 M⊙. An important insight from this study is the signature of the jet/wind-gas interaction, suggested by the spatial anti-correlation observed between the polarized radio emission and the emission line gas. This in turn could be interpreted as tentative evidence for AGN feedback. Our work also demonstrates that the interplay of jets, winds and emission line gas might have a significant impact on the nature of the radio outflows in radio-quiet AGN. In addition, all sources in our sample show evidence for ongoing galactic mergers, such as the presence of double optical nuclei, or morphological distortions in the host galaxy. We, therefore, note that the merger scenario may also influence the overall interpretation of AGN feedback in these sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stac1044&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Quasar Feedback Survey: revealing the interplay of jets, winds, and emission-line gas in type 2 quasars with radio polarization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Silpa Sasikumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt;   P Kharb, C M Harrison, A Girdhar, D Mukherjee, V Mainieri, M E Jarvis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; National Centre for Radio Astrophysics (NCRA) - Tata Institute of Fundamental Research (TIFR), Pune, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/five_agn_polarization_silpa</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/five_agn_polarization_silpa</guid>
        
        <category>AGNs</category>
        
        <category>Blackhole</category>
        
        <category>Galaxies</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chandrayaan-3 : A 14 day lunar cruise</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;India’s ambitious space program reaches new heights as Chandrayaan-3, the eagerly anticipated lunar exploration mission, prepares for launch. Get ready to witness history in the making as India embarks again on an extraordinary journey towards the Moon, marking a remarkable milestone for the nation and igniting a wave of excitement across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Chandrayaan-3&lt;/b&gt; is the planned 3rd lunar exploration mission by the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO), with the aim of demonstrating the end-to-end capability in safe landing and roving on the lunar surface along with the development and demonstration of new technologies intended towards inter-planetary missions. The developed system for the mission consists of an indigenous Lander module (Vikram), a Rover (Pragyan) and a Propulsion module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/chandrayaan_3_cysil/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: A schematic illustration of the Integrated Module. &lt;em&gt;Credits:&lt;/em&gt; ISRO
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launcher identified for Chandrayaan-3 is LVM3-M4 (Launch Mark 3 - Mission 4), which will place the integrated module in an Elliptic Parking Orbit (EPO). The pri- mary function of the Propulsion module is to transport the Lander from the launch vehicle injection till its entry into the lunar polar orbit at an altitude of 100 kms from the lunar surface, after which the Lander separates from the Propulsion module and begins its descent. The Lander is equipped with the capability to perform a soft land at a specified lunar site (69.367621 S, 32.348126 E) and deploy the Rover which will then carry out in-situ chemical analysis of the lunar surface during the course of its planned lifetime of 14 Earth days (1 Lunar Day). The Propulsion Module also has one scientific payload as a secondary function which will be operated post separation of Lander module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/chandrayaan_3_cysil/image2a.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/chandrayaan_3_cysil/image2b.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: A schematic illustration of the Chandrayaan-3 Lander (Top) and Rover (Bottom). &lt;em&gt;Credits:&lt;/em&gt; ISRO
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mission objectives of Chandrayaan-3 are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To demonstrate Safe and Soft Landing on Lunar Surface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To demonstrate Rover roving on the moon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To conduct in-situ scientific experiments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Propulsion module, the Lander and the Rover hosts a total of 7 scientific payloads
in order to carry out experiments on the lunar surface and atmosphere. They are listed
below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Radio Anatomy of Moon Bound Hypersensitive ionosphere and Atmosphere
(RAMBHA)&lt;/b&gt; - [Lander] - This experiment makes use of a Langmuir Probe in order to measure the near surface plasma density and its changes with time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Chandra’s Surface Thermo physical Experiment (ChaSTE)&lt;/b&gt; - [Lander] - To measure the thermal conductivity and temperature of the lunar surface.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instrument for Lunar Seismic Activity (ILSA)&lt;/b&gt; - [Lander] - An experiment to measure the seismicity of the lunar surface and delineating the structure of the lunar crust and mantle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Laser Retroreflector Array (LRA)&lt;/b&gt; - [Lander] - A passive experiment to understand the dynamics of Moon system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Alpha Particle X-Ray Spectrometer (APXS)&lt;/b&gt; - [Rover] - To determine the elemental composition of the surface in the immediate vicinity of the landing site.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Laser Induced Breakdown Spectroscope (LIBS)&lt;/b&gt; - [Rover] - To infer the mineralogical composition of the lunar surface through elemental analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Spectro-polarimetry of HAbitable Planet Earth (SHAPE)&lt;/b&gt; - [Propulsion module] - To observe the Earth in reflected light in an attempt to decipher future discoveries of Exo-planets which would qualify for habitability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the predecessors to the Chandrayaan-3, Chandrayaan-2 boasted a ‘significant technological leap’ compared to the Chandrayaan-1. The Vikram Lander onboard the Chandrayaan-2 accomplished its intended descent trajectory, smoothly transitioning from an orbit of 35 km to a position slightly below 2 km above the lunar surface. During this phase, all systems and sensors of the Lander operated flawlessly, demonstrating the successful utilization of groundbreaking technologies, such as the innovative variable thrust propulsion system. Unfortunately, communication with the Lander was lost during the final descent phase. Subsequent investigations confirmed that the lander experienced a hard landing on the lunar surface, resulting in the loss of the lander itself. Chandrayaan-3 aims to address the challenges of its predecessors and enhance the current understanding of the Moon. On successful landing at the specified site, India will immortalise herself as the fourth country to land its spacecraft on the surface of the Moon and the first country to land near the South Pole of the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch of Chandrayaan-3 has been scheduled for &lt;b&gt;July 14, 2023, at 2:35 pm IST&lt;/b&gt; from the &lt;b&gt;Satish Dhawan Space Centre, Sriharikota&lt;/b&gt;. The spacecraft is expected to reach the moon by the 23rd − 24th August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live telecast of the launch can be viewed on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/live/q2ueCg9bvvQ?feature=share&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; official ISRO YouTube channel.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/chandrayaan_3_cysil</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/chandrayaan_3_cysil</guid>
        
        <category>International</category>
        
        <category>India</category>
        
        <category>ISRO</category>
        
        <category>Chandrayaan</category>
        
        <category>moon</category>
        
        <category>lunar exploration</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Investigating the massive plasma blobs from the Sun using an ‘in-situ’ eye</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This article is about investigating the characteristics of Interplanetary Coronal Mass Ejections using in-situ observation. ICMEs are well-known to expand as they propagate through the heliosphere. Despite this, their cross-sections are usually modeled as static plasma columns within the magnetohydrodynamics (MHD) framework. We test the validity of this approach using in-situ plasma data from 151 magnetic clouds (MCs) observed by the WIND spacecraft and 45 observed by the Helios spacecraft. We find that the most probable cross-section expansion speeds for the WIND events are only ≈ 0.06 times the Alfvén speed inside the MCs, while the most probable cross-section expansion speeds for the Helios events is ≈ 0.03. MC cross-sections can thus be considered to be nearly static over an Alfvén crossing timescale. Using estimates of electrical conductivity arising from Coulomb collisions, we find that the Lundquist number inside MCs is high (≈ 10&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt; to 10&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt;), suggesting that the MHD description is well justified. The Joule heating rates using our conductivity estimates are several orders of magnitude lower than the requirement for plasma heating inside MCs near the Earth. While the (low) heating rates we compute are consistent with the MHD description, the discrepancy with the heating requirement points to possible departures from MHD and the need for a better understanding of plasma heating in MCs.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might wonder what is &lt;em&gt;in-situ&lt;/em&gt; and what are &lt;em&gt;ICMEs&lt;/em&gt;. Don’t worry, I am here to guide you
through this article. ‘CMEs’ or Coronal Mass Ejections are massive blobs of plasma along with
strong magnetic fields that erupt from the solar corona. Corona is the Latin word for ‘crown’ and
it is the outermost layer of our Sun. It has nothing to do with the awful COVID pandemic. Due to
the presence of the bright photosphere (the bright yellow disk we see during daytime), we cannot
see the corona with our naked eyes. However, during a total solar eclipse, we can have a glimpse
of it. Remember that beautiful aura encircled the sun during a total solar eclipse? Yes, that is
solar corona (see Figure 1). It is extremely hot (temperature around a few million Kelvin (K)),
much hotter than the photosphere (temperature ~ 6000 K). Why the corona is so hot, remains a
mystery to the solar astrophysicists. Throughout this article, you will encounter the word,
‘plasma’. A plasma is a medium filled with charged particles and due to its higher conductivity,
the charged particles often gyrate closely to the magnetic field lines present in that medium.
Hence, the charged particles can follow the motion of the magnetic field. Although made of
charged particles, the plasma can be overall neutral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/massive_plasma_blob_sun_debesh/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
(&lt;em&gt;Figure 1: Total solar eclipse during April 1999. Picture courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://lucnix.be/&quot;&gt;Luc Viatour &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most spectacular events that come out from this ever-changing dancing dynamics of corona is the CME. CMEs are the largest-scale eruptive phenomena in the solar system. The huge lump of plasma of mass 10&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt;-10&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt; kg, accompanied with strong magnetic fields, is hauled up out of the corona all the way into the interplanetary space with a typical velocity ranging from several hundred to more than 1000 km per second. Due to their high velocities, CMEs are often accompanied by shocks in front of them. A typical CME has a kinetic energy of around 10&lt;sup&gt;22&lt;/sup&gt;-10&lt;sup&gt;25&lt;/sup&gt; Joules. Broadly, CME observation methods can be divided into two categories: 1) remote observations and 2) in-situ observations. The first kind, as the name suggests, observes the CMEs from far away, usually when they come out of the Sun. We need to rely on the CME images as none of the spacecraft can go that much close to the Sun. This is because, as of now, we do not have the technology which can survive the extreme environment (the million K coronal temperature, the strong electromagnetic fields, the bombardment of highly accelerated charged particles, strong radiation hazards, etc.) in the proximity of the Sun. One of the key techniques used in this method is the use of ‘coronagraphs’. A coronagraph acts like an artificial total solar eclipse by blocking the bright solar disk so that we can observe the dynamics of the CME while it is getting ejected out into the interplanetary space. Figure 2 shows two coronagraph images of a CME on February 27, 2000, observed by the Large Angle and Spectrometric COronagraph (LASCO) instrument on board the SOlar and Heliospheric Observatory  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/soho/index.html&quot;&gt;(SOHO) &lt;/a&gt;, a joint mission by NASA and ESA. The left panel is an image from the C2 coronagraph with a field of view (FOV) of 2.2 - 6.0 R&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt; (R&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt; is the radius of the Sun) and the right panel is from the C3 coronagraph with FOV from 3.7 to 30 R&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt;. In both images, the inner circle represents the Sun while the outer circle signifies the occulter of the coronagraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/massive_plasma_blob_sun_debesh/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: The coronagraph image of a CME eruption. Image courtesy: LASCO instrument
aboard SOHO
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the CME travels through the interplanetary space, it expands and interacts with the solar wind. In the propagation phase, CMEs are often called ‘Interplanetary CMEs’ or ICMEs. Due to its humongous size and low plasma density during this phase, it becomes almost impossible to capture the entire ICME using any imaging technique. Here the second method, the in-situ observation, becomes useful. In this method, the spacecraft passes through the ICME cross-section and directly measures the important parameters of a propagating ICME. During its propagation, the plasma entangled with the smooth and twisted magnetic field lines (which resemble the telephone cord) forms a huge cloud-like structure known as the Magnetic Cloud or MC. Figure 3 shows a cartoon describing an MC associated with an ICME as it travels through interplanetary space. An example of the in-situ data measured close to 1 astronomical unit (The distance between the Sun and the Earth is called 1 astronomical unit or AU. It is approximately 15 crore km) by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wind.nasa.gov/&quot;&gt;WIND &lt;/a&gt; spacecraft as shown in Figure 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/massive_plasma_blob_sun_debesh/image3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: A cartoon diagram of a magnetic cloud associated with an ICME.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article aims at understanding the ICME expansion and heating (using in-situ observation) during their propagation through the interplanetary space by asking three questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Good Is the Static Assumption for ICMEs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Good is the Ideal MHD Assumption for ICMEs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can Joule Heating Meet the Heating Budget of ICME plasma?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three questions are addressed in detail in their respective paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/massive_plasma_blob_sun_debesh/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: An example of the in-situ data from the WIND spacecraft. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spacecraft measures the parameters (total magnetic field (B), magnetic field components (B&lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;,B&lt;sub&gt;y&lt;/sub&gt;,B&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;/sub&gt;), proton number density (N&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt;), plasma beta (β), etc.). The plasma beta is the ratio between gas pressure (P&lt;sub&gt;gas&lt;/sub&gt;,) and magnetic pressure (P&lt;sub&gt;mag&lt;/sub&gt;,). The vertical lines depict the width of the MC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it is evident from the observations that ICMEs do expand (i.e., their cross-sections
increase with time) as they propagate through the heliosphere, a lot of studies (Lundquist(1951),
Burlaga (1988), Möstl et al., 2009; Isavnin, Kilpua, and Koskinen, 2011) assumed the ICME
cross-sections to be ‘&lt;strong&gt;static plasma columns&lt;/strong&gt;’! (In simpler words, it means the plasma inside the
ICMEs are at rest.) This is because this assumption leads to the magnetohydrostatic (it is similar
to hydrostatic equilibrium which is a certain type of equilibrium used for fluids when they are at
rest, the only difference is, it is used for a plasma, not for a regular fluid) equilibrium. We know
that physicists love equilibrium as it makes mathematical computations a lot easier. So, though
we all know that the ICME cross-sectional expansion speed is never strictly zero, it is assumed to
be zero (the scientists assumed that the expansion speed is very small) and hence we get the
equilibrium. But no one to date has ever investigated the validity of this approximation. And so,
in the first part of this study, we are aiming at the question: &lt;em&gt;How Good Is the Static Assumption for ICMEs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that, we compare the cross-sectional expansion speed (v&lt;sub&gt;exp&lt;/sub&gt;) of MCs with the Alfven speed (v&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt;)
inside them. Alfven speed is the measure of the propagation of the magnetic perturbations
perpendicular to the magnetic field. We know that the sound speed of a medium is the
characteristic speed of that particular medium. Similarly, is one of the characteristic speeds of
the plasma. If v&lt;sub&gt;exp&lt;/sub&gt; is sufficiently smaller than v&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt;, or in other words, if the Alfven crossing timescale is much smaller than the cross-sectional expansion timescale, the magnetostatic assumption can be
considered to be approximately valid inside the propagating ICMEs. We have taken a large
sample of well-observed ICMEs: 151 events close to the Earth (using the data from the WIND
spacecraft close to 1 AU) and 45 events in the interplanetary space between the Sun and the
Earth (using the Helios data from 0.29 AU to close to 1 AU). We estimate R&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt;, the ratio between v&lt;sub&gt;exp&lt;/sub&gt;
and v&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt; and found that the most probable values of are of R&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt; the order of 0.01. The statistical results
are described in Figure 5. Our findings show that the ICME cross-sections can be assumed to be
static (to a fairly good extent) over an Alfven crossing timescale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/massive_plasma_blob_sun_debesh/image5a.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/massive_plasma_blob_sun_debesh/image5b.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 5: Histograms of &lt;em&gt;R&lt;sub&gt;A&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;: the top panel shows the results for the WIND events while the bottom panel shows the results for the Helios events.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solar astrophysicists use a fluid-like prescription for plasma dynamics; it is known as magnetohydrodynamics (MHD). The conventional treatment assumes that the CME plasma obeys the ideal MHD, i.e., the magnetic field never diffuses and remains attached with the plasma particles. However, this assumption, too, had not been verified earlier. In the second part of our study, we ask: &lt;em&gt;How Good is the Ideal MHD Assumption for ICMEs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The estimation of the Lundquist number (S&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;) is one way to do this. S&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; is the ratio between the magnetic diffusion timescale (t&lt;sub&gt;𝜂&lt;/sub&gt;) and the Alfven crossing timescale (𝑡&lt;sub&gt;𝐴&lt;/sub&gt;). For the ideal MHD condition, t&lt;sub&gt;𝜂&lt;/sub&gt; (which means that the magnetic fields take infinite time to diffuse, in other words, they never diffuse), implying 𝑆0. So, the larger the magnitude of S&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;, the more the plasma will follow the assumptions of the ideal MHD. We have found that S&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; is significantly large inside the ICME plasma (≅10&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt; ), suggesting a good justification for the use of the ideal MHD approximations (see Figure 6) to describe the motion of the ICMEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/massive_plasma_blob_sun_debesh/image6a.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/massive_plasma_blob_sun_debesh/image6b.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 6: Histograms of &lt;em&gt;S&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/em&gt;: the top panel shows the results for the WIND events while the bottom panel shows the results for the Helios events.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, we have seen that the ICME plasma fairly obeys the assumptions of the ideal MHD. However, there is a cache! The ideal MHD assumes zero heating of the plasma. But numerous observations confirm that the temperature of the near-Earth ICME can reach as high as ≅10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;
K! Hence, the ideal MHD framework cannot explain the heating of CME plasma. Joule heating is the simplest type of heating mechanism we can investigate. In the last part of this study, we ask: &lt;em&gt;Can Joule Heating Meet the Heating Budget of ICME plasma?&lt;/em&gt;
To answer this question, we have evaluated the Joule heating (which is like the 𝐼&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;𝑅 heating inside an electrical wire, where I is the current and R is the resistance of the wire) rate inside all the ICMEs in our sample. We have found that the Joule heating rate (which we have found to be ≅10&lt;sup&gt;-6&lt;/sup&gt;𝐽𝑘𝑔&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;𝑠&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) is significantly smaller than the required heating budget (≅10&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;𝐽𝑘𝑔&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;𝑠&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;) of the CME plasma. It proves that the Joule heating is not the right candidate for CME heating! One needs to look for another heating mechanism. CME thermodynamics is one of the most exciting topics under solar astrophysics and to date, no one knows the exact mechanism of CME heating. There are important approaches like, whether the CMEs are expanding adiabatically or getting heated isothermally via the thermal conduction from the solar corona, or whether turbulence plays a role in the local heating of CME plasma. But overall, this remains an unsolved mystery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might wonder why we are so bothered about these giant plasma blobs. The reason is, Earth-directed ICMEs are the primary drivers of strong geomagnetic storms leading to space weather disturbances.  Such disturbances affect a wide range of technologies and communication systems we rely on. Starting from the damage to satellites, telecommunication systems, GPS, and electrical power supply to the radiation hazards on the human body. These disturbances can also cause red alerts for the astronaut’s safety. In order to mitigate these effects, we need to predict the arrival times and other important information (such as the strength and rotation of the magnetic field, ICME speed, their energy, etc.) of these ICMEs as realistically as possible. To do that, a good understanding of the CMEs is crucial. With the launch of the Aditya L1 mission, which is India’s first mission dedicated to solar astronomy, we hope to have a new milestone in the advancement of CME research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11207-022-01982-x&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;On Modeling ICME Cross-Sections as Static MHD Columns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt;  Debesh Bhattacharjee&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt;  Prasad Subramanian, Volker Bothmer, Teresa Nieves-Chinchilla &amp;amp; Angelos Vourlidas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Science Education and Research, Pune; Dr. Homi Bhabha Road, Pashan, Pune
411008, India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/massive_plasma_blob_sun_debesh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/massive_plasma_blob_sun_debesh</guid>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>&apos;Where’s the Shadow?&apos; - A workshop in preparation for Zero Shadow Day</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Cosmology Education and Research Training Centre (COSMOS) is an upcoming state-of-the-art planetarium, along with a data training centre and resource centre in Mysuru. The Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA) has formed an Education and Public Outreach Committee (EPOC) for COSMOS. In this article, the author has given a brief account of a unique workshop organised for both students and parents in preparation for Zero Shadow Day (ZSD). The article also highlights the various factors involved in a science outreach activity.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cosmosmysuru&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cosmology Education and Research Training Center (COSMOS)&lt;/a&gt; is an upcoming state-of-the-art planetarium along with a data training centre and resource center in Mysuru. The planetarium will come up at the Sri Jayachamaraja Wadiyar Center for Higher Learning (JWCHL) campus of the University of Mysore (UoM) at the foot of Chamundi Hill in Mysuru.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is funded by the MPLAD funds of Hon’ble FM Nirmala Sitharaman, the Department of Science and Technology and the Department of Atomic Energy, Government of India. The project is steered by the Principal Scientific Advisor, Government of India, and is managed by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Astrophysics&lt;/a&gt;, under an MoU between the &lt;a href=&quot;http://uni-mysore.ac.in/english-version/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;University of Mysore&lt;/a&gt; and the Indian Institute of Astrophysics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA) has formed an Education and Public Outreach Committee (EPOC) for COSMOS consisting of science communicators and researchers across the country. IIA has hired two employees who are posted at Mysuru, who work to ensure the successful implementation of the outreach activities. The author is the Project Associate who coordinates all outreach activities on the ground. A Project Assistant has also been hired for a project to locate, digitise, and analyse astronomy content in Kannada. Both of them work in coordination with the EPO committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s Zero Shadow Day was the first one for “COSMOS”. The outreach team of COSMOS, in association with the IIA, the University of Mysore (UoM), and Kutulali, came up with the idea of organising a workshop in preparation for Zero Shadow Day for the school students and their parents. Some people might be wondering, Why parents? In fact, that’s a valid question to ask! Considering the modern-day trends of parents getting involved in the activities of their children at school, music class, dance, karate, etc., we thought, why not give them a chance to involve themselves actively in a workshop? So, we sent out the posters to very few WhatsApp groups, asking interested people to register for the workshop and mentioning the fact that one of the parents should accompany the student on the day of the workshop. Interestingly, the response was overwhelmingly positive, with registrations from neighbouring cities and parents expressing their eagerness to attend the workshop over phone calls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should also mention the fact that because it was the summer holidays and the state election was around the corner, we could not access teachers and schools to participate in the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop was held on April 17, 2023, at Vijnana Bhavan, University of Mysore, Mysuru. The program began with a talk by Ravinder Banyal, Associate Professor, IIA, on the necessity of studying the ‘Sun’ and then he discussed topics such as the various activities of the sun’s atmosphere, the formation of the sun, space weather, etc. Dr. Banyal successfully captured the attention of both parents and students by discussing the various topics in a language that they could comprehend. This was followed by a talk by Niruj Mohan Ramanujam on the science behind Zero Shadow Day. He went a step ahead and invited the students to the dias to involve them actively in the various aspects of the talk. Mr. Kollegala Sharma, PI-Kutuhali, who is a famous science writer and communicator in Kannada, was also present in the workshop and helped us reach the students and the parents in the local language, which is indeed a very important aspect of science communication in our country. Then we took the students and parents to the terrace of Vijnana Bhavan to do hands-on experiments. To be precise, this was the real-action time of the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/wheres_the_shadow_amogh/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Image 1: Dr. Ravinder Banyal (on left) and Mr. Kollegala Sharma (on right) interacting with the participants. [&lt;em&gt;PC: Amoghavarsha. N&lt;/em&gt;]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had arranged three important experimental setups for the kids. The first one was a projection of the sun’s image onto the wall with the help of two IIA-made 4-inch reflector-type telescopes. The second one was finding the length of the shadow made by the Gnomon (Sanskrit/Kannada: Shankhu Yantra). The third and final one was the ball-mirror experiment. To our surprise, parents were engaging themselves in all the activities and experiments, matching the enthusiasm of an 8-year-old kid who was the youngest participant in our workshop!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/wheres_the_shadow_amogh/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Image 2: Dr. Niruj Mohan Ramanujam explaining the science behind Zero Shadow Day to the young participants. [&lt;em&gt;PC: Dr. Chrisphin Karthik&lt;/em&gt;]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the above three experimental setups, the participants could witness important scientific phenomena, which are mentioned below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Observation of Sunspots: The students were given a chance to fiddle with the telescopes (of course, with proper instructions) to try and get an image of the sun on the screen. After proper focusing, sunspots were visible, and students had fun counting the number of spots.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Movement of the Earth: As soon as the image was projected onto a screen, some students very distinctively noticed the movement of the sun’s image without any disturbance in the set-up. This helped in having a productive discussion regarding the earth’s movement around the sun.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Angular Size of the Sun: Students and parents were briefed on how to calculate the angular separation of the sun in the sky by measuring the diameter of the circle of the sun’s projection.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solar Energy: Some small kids picked up some waste paper and placed it in front of the eyepiece to observe the phenomenon of the conversion of solar energy to heat energy. They were very happy when they were able to completely burn the paper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;True North of Earth: With the help of Gnomon, the students were asked to note down the length of the shadow made by Gnomon every 10 minutes. The shortest shadow was observed at the local noon, and kids reported to us that after that point the shadow’s direction changed (you should know “why?”)! Using the points touching the concentric circles and drawing perpendicular to one of those circles, they could convince themselves that what they had found out was indeed the true direction of ‘North’. Please refer to image 4 for more details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/wheres_the_shadow_amogh/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Image 3: The participants measuring the length of the shadow made by the Gnomon (Shankhu Yantra) [&lt;em&gt;PC: Ms. Bhavani Joshi&lt;/em&gt;]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/wheres_the_shadow_amogh/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Image 4: Finding the true north of Earth using Shankhu Yantra / the method of equal altitudes [&lt;em&gt;Credits: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mysundial.ca/tsp/true_north_south.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Sundial Primer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program concluded with a wonderful feedback session from both the parents and students. The participants were also informed about the past and future activities of ‘COSMOS’ in and around the city before the dispersal. The Zero Shadow Day for Mysuru was on 23rd April 2023 at 12.22 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I should also mention the fact that most of the experiments that were done on the workshop day were low-cost, self-made ones (which made me run very often to the local stationary shops), unlike the usual fancy stuff. For example, the Gnomon was a pencil which was glued to a thermocol (Polystyrene) sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that (and I assume most of the people who are reading this will agree with me on this) we should encourage and promote more and more low-cost and self-doable experimental arrangements to be relevant to all sections of students and people in society. It must be realised that science communication and outreach activities are much more than putting a presentation through a projector! And also, doing science-related activities in non-metropolitan cities, rural areas, and remote places takes much more effort compared to those done in metropolitan cities due to various degrees of constraints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/wheres_the_shadow_amogh/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Image 5: Participants doing the Ball-mirror experiment [&lt;em&gt;PC: Ms. Bhavani Joshi&lt;/em&gt;]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank Dr. Niruj Mohan Ramanujam, SCOPE Head, IIA, for giving me enough freedom, constant support, and new ideas to carry out science communication and public outreach activities in Mysuru under the ‘COSMOS’ and IIA roofs. I also thank Prof. Annapurni Subramaniam, Director, IIA, for her encouragement and support. I must thank my friends and colleagues, Mr. Vikranth Pulamathi (SCOPE Associate, IIA), Mr. Vishaak K. B. (Intern at SCOPE, IIA), Mr. Punith. R. (Project Assistant, COSMOS), Ms. Bhavani (Intern at COSMOS, IIA), and all the volunteers of ‘COSMOS’ in Mysuru.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more details, you can follow us on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/cosmosmysuru/?hl=en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt;, Facebook [@Cosmos Mysuru] and Twitter. I hope you will also listen to our podcast on &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/show/4GmBrSmrXuxgd0y0cj11XQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt;. Thank you for your time and patience!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/wheres_the_shadow_amogh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/wheres_the_shadow_amogh</guid>
        
        <category>zeroshadowday</category>
        
        <category>outreach</category>
        
        <category>COSMOS Mysuru</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>India’s expanding Cosmology community</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;‘Frontiers in Cosmology’ was a five-day international conference held at Raman Research Institute (RRI) during February 20 – 24, 2023. More than 100 participants including researchers, scientists, students and faculties from around the world attended the meet.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/proceedings_rri_cosmology_anjali/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Speakers at the &apos;Frontiers in Cosmology&apos; conference. &lt;em&gt;Credits:&lt;/em&gt; ESO/ M. Kornmesser, RRI Newsletter PJC Special Issue - I
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;India&lt;/b&gt; has seen a slow but steady growth in the number of researchers pursuing Astronomy and Astrophysics, particularly in cosmology and instrumentation, during the past three decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such recent effort to unite the leading cosmologists was at the &lt;b&gt;‘Frontiers in Cosmology’&lt;/b&gt;, a five-day international conference held at the Raman Research Institute (RRI), Bengaluru, during February 20 – 24, 2023. The conference was one among the many celebrations to mark the platinum jubilee year of RRI, founded by Nobel laureate Sir CV Raman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Frontiers in Cosmology&lt;/b&gt; saw a participation from over 100 subject experts including researchers, scientists, students and faculties and turned out to be a global platform to discuss, deliberate and share the latest from the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference offered five broad themes - Inflation and Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB), Cosmic Dawn and Epoch of Reionisation, Low Redshift Cosmology, the Evolving Universe and the Next Generation Experiments. Young researchers used this platform to showcase the findings of their research, the best 25 posters were on display here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference hosted varied talks on CMB, characterization of galactic foregrounds, instrumentation, future astronomical facilities like the Simons Observatory, a ground-based CMB experiment located at Cerrro Toco in Chile, the Thirty Metre Telescope (TMT), the Square Kilometre Array (SKA), PRATUSH, some of which has active participation of RRI. Engaging and enlightening the audience about the telescope facilities like the South Pole Telescope (SPT) and the BICEP Array telescopes – both located in Antarctica – SARAS, CHIME, the young students got a flavour of the facilities, both existing and upcoming. The event saw serious deliberations revolving the ever-growing challenges faced by the astronomy community in getting land free from light pollution and human interferences. Experts stressed on the need for building improved instrumentation facilities and technological support besides designing facilities on larger and collaborative basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the speakers, Akito Kusaka, who spoke on ‘CMB – challenges and future prospects’, elaborated on the perfect conditions for installing the CMB detectors in the world. Further, his address highlighted the leakage of observations into polarization as one of the biggest hurdles in measuring CMB. The theories and scientific contributions of late Shivaramakrishnan Pancharatnam, (a noted student of Sir Raman), continue to be relevant even today, acknowledged Kusaka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving elaborate details, contributions and challenges of operating, Maclean Rouble, in her talk titled ‘S&amp;amp;T of SPT : Past, Present and Future’, underlined the need for having sensitive detectors in order to improve the CMB mapping efforts. She touched upon the likely possibilities of telescopes post the operations of SPT, including the mm-line intensity mapping and the idea of developing kinetic inductance detectors. Another operational telescope in the Southern polar region is the BICEP Array telescopes, which are small aperture telescopes deployed to measure CMB with highest precision. Ritoban Basu Thakur in his talk informed about the heightened capacities of the upgraded BICEP Array telescope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NenuFAR and the CoDEX Program initiated by the European Research Council were discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Josh Dillon’s address on ‘Recent progress in 21cm Cosmology with the hydrogen epoch of reionization array’ detailed on the necessity for co-designing compact instruments with greater sensitivity for effective measurements. Nichole Barry elaborated on the difficulties in taking observations and working at the Murchison Widefield Array, especially for the epoch of reionization science in her address titled ‘The dangers of Whitefield Observations for the EoR 21cm measurements’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing the SARAS experiment setup ‘Constraining high redshift astrophysics with SARAS’, by Saurabh Singh enlisted the multiple challenges, especially the bright foregrounds, and the shrinking radio-quiet zones in India for conducting continued observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing capabilities of CHIME, HIRAX and CHORD facilities, Shiv Sethi’s talk ‘Detecting HI in the post-reionizaiton’ suggested two potentially strong methods – stacking and cross-correction – that can produce good observations within the redshift 0.3 – 1.4 range. Hamsa Padmanabhan’s talk ‘A multi-messenger view of the baryonic Universe out to the Epoch Reionization’ underlined the requirement for strengthening the cross-co-relations for improving the 21cm HI intensity mapping in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/proceedings_rri_cosmology_anjali/image2.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Bringing together brilliant minds. Group photo of the conference attendees. &lt;em&gt;Credits:&lt;/em&gt; RRI
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when the country is sealing its position in Astronomy, senior scientists used this stage to inform the young attendees about the many next generation astronomy facilities, where India has major stakes. Yashwant Gupta spoke about the upgraded Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope (uGMRT) and presented an insight into the world’s largest radio telescope, the Square Kilometre Array (SKA). Another mega-science project participated by India, the Thirty Metre Telescope (TMT) – the proposed largest optical telescope – was spoken during a session by GC Anupama. She narrated the the numerous hardships faced in erecting the telescope at the designated Mauna Kea in Hawaii and years of continued efforts to locate a search alternate site, all for science!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video recordings of the conference talks are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLOT8qUzmOGqovk12OtW3lBM7yEe759dyp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; RRI YouTube channel.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cover image credits: ESA - C. Carreau&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgements&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CosmicVarta would like to thank the organizers of the “Frontiers in Cosmology” conference and Raman Research Institute (RRI) for their support and cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/proceedings_rri_cosmology_anjali</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/proceedings_rri_cosmology_anjali</guid>
        
        <category>Proceedings</category>
        
        <category>International</category>
        
        <category>Conference</category>
        
        <category>Cosmology</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Proceedings of the  National Seminar on  Advances in Astrophysics and Space Science Research (NSAAASSR) 2023</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Department of Physics and Electronics at CHRIST (Deemed to be University) in Bangalore, Karnataka, organised the National Seminar on Advances in Astrophysics and Space Science Research (NSAASSR) from February 13 to 15, 2023. The seminar was organised as part of the IUCAA Centre for Astronomy Research and Development (ICARD), CHRIST (Deemed to be University). We report the proceedings from the seminar.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department of Physics and Electronics at CHRIST (Deemed to be University) in Bangalore, Karnataka, organised the National Seminar on Advances in Astrophysics and Space Science Research (NSAASSR) from February 13 to 15, 2023. The seminar was organised as part of the IUCAA Centre for Astronomy Research and Development (ICARD), CHRIST (Deemed to be University). The primary functions of the ICARDs are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To contribute to the development of innovative teaching methods designed for Astronomy. This includes the development of upto date course structures and new kinds of experiment/data analysis sessions which can be a part of a starting or existing Astronomy course in a University. To hold frequent workshops/schools/meetings at various levels at the host University/College and nearby regions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To have an active public outreach program for Astronomy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To be visiting Centre where nearby Astronomers can visit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IUCAA accredited the Department of Physics and Electronics as ICARD on October 1, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/proceedings_report_nsaassr_robin/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three-day seminar aimed to provide postgraduate and motivated undergraduate students with insights and knowledge on current developments in Astronomy and Astrophysics under the ICARD activities. There is a dearth of conferences and seminars specifically tailored to meet the needs of undergraduate and postgraduate students. In light of this, a seminar has been thoughtfully planned to give students a unique opportunity to showcase and present their research work on an exclusive platform. It provided attendees with a comprehensive and interactive learning experience, featuring talks by prominent scientists, student contributions, and hands-on data analysis sessions. The students’ contributory talks were based on projects completed or currently in progress during their UG/PG programmes. The seminar saw active participation from over 40 students from different Institutes and Universities who were selected based on the submitted abstracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;proceedings-for-day-one&quot;&gt;Proceedings for Day One&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Inaugural session of the seminar was presided over by Dr Fr Jose CC, honourable Pro-Vice Chancellor, CHRIST (Deemed to be University). The chief guest for the occasion was Dr Annapurni Subramaniam, Director &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics&lt;/a&gt;. They shared great insight into the need and multifold applications of the field of astronomy in day-to-day life. After a brief tea break,  Dr Annapurni gave a plenary talk on “Astronomy from the ground and space-based telescopes”. The talk narrated the transition of astronomy from using the position of stars to navigate the night sky to using telescopes to unveil star formation in far-off galaxies. Attendees learned about accessing data from various space missions and using it for scientific purposes. They were also introduced to the country’s present and future space telescopes facilities, such as AstroSat and INSIST. The talk also briefly outlined the research works of the team led by Dr Annapurni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Ajith Parmeswaran, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icts.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; ICTS, Bangalore&lt;/a&gt;, delivered the second plenary talk. The topic was “Gravitational wave astronomy: A new window to the Universe”. Dr Ajith participated virtually in the seminar. The talk focussed on how the observational confirmation of gravitational waves has enabled us to understand our Universe better. Participants were introduced to the precise instruments to detect and study these waves. The discussion also included information on CMB Bharat, a consortium for Indian cosmology, and LIGO India, allowing for a new perspective on comprehending the cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Seminar then had 12 talks by the participants in extragalactic and stellar astronomy. The audience received the talks well, leading to many fruitful discussions. The first day concluded with informal discussions with the participants and resource persons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;proceedings-for-day-two&quot;&gt;Proceedings for Day Two&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day began with a plenary talk by Dr Shyama Naredranath, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ursc.gov.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; URSC, Bangalore&lt;/a&gt;. The topic was “Exploration of the Moon: paradigm shifts”. The talk discussed various theories that explain the origin of the Moon. The talk also narrated how the abundance of different volatile elements like sodium and oxygen will enable us to understand the formation scenario of the Moon. Dr Shyama also talked about India’s significant contribution to understanding the Moon, namely Chandrayaan 1 and 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Manoj Puravankara, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tifr.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; TIFR, Mumbai,&lt;/a&gt; delivered the second plenary talk. The title of the talk was “Exploring the invisible Universe: the story of Infrared Astronomy”. Dr Manoj joined the seminar online. The talk discussed the importance of infrared astronomy and how the field has helped us unravel the Universe that lies shrouded in the visible spectrum, such as the interstellar shocks, protoplanetary disks, and reddening due to interstellar dust, among others. The talk also highlighted the new age space telescope, JWST, and how the telescope has helped us achieve great insights into the far ends of the Universe. Dr Manoj then discussed his team’s research using the JWST facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Dipanjan Mukherjee, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iucaa.in/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; IUCAA, Pune&lt;/a&gt;, delivered the third plenary talk on “Understanding how jets from Supermassive Black Holes affect galaxy evolution”.  The talk started with the galaxy colour-magnitude diagrams and the three distributions seen: the blue cloud, the red sequence and the green valley. Then, various quenching mechanisms prevalent in galaxies were discussed. The talk then highlighted how the jets emanating from black holes influence the evolution of the host galaxies. After the lunch break, the seminar had a series of five cosmology and space science talks by the student participants. Discussions with the panel and audience gave more significant insights into their research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hands-on session on astronomical tools such as SAO DS9 and Topcat was scheduled next. The session was taken by Mr Akhil Krishna and Mr Suman Bhattacharya, PhD Scholars, CHRIST (Deemed to be University). The participants enthusiastically learnt to utilise these tools to visualise and analyse data from worldwide astronomical facilities. The participants were then led on a campus tour. They were introduced to the various facilities available in the University, including the Research and Development block and the different instruments such as the X-ray diffractometers, Electron Microscopy, UV- Visible spectrometer, Fluorometer, Microwave Synthesizer, Solar Simulator, and SEM, among others which the students can make use of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last event for the day was a public talk by Dr Dipankar Bannerjee, Director, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/aries-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; ARIES, Nainital&lt;/a&gt;. The lecture title was “India’s first Space Solar Observatory: Aditya L1”. The talk focussed on coronal mass ejections and sunspots. Dr Dipankar also discussed the upcoming first solar space mission from India, Aditya L1, and the various instruments to study our closest star. The mission’s main objective is to understand the coronal heating and solar wind acceleration, initiation of the coronal mass ejection, flares and near-Earth space weather, the coupling and dynamics of the Solar Atmosphere, and the solar wind distribution and temperature anisotropy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;proceedings-for-day-three&quot;&gt;Proceedings for Day Three&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third day began with a plenary talk by Dr Smitha Subramanian, IIA, Bangalore, on “An introduction to extragalactic astronomy”. The talk started with the Great Debate: Shapley-Curtis debate. The participants were then introduced to Hubble’s tuning fork diagram and the various types of galaxies known to us. Dr Smitha then proceeded to explain the formation of galaxies. The talk also emphasised galactic evolution and the various triggering mechanisms involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Vaidehi S Paliya, IUCAA, Pune, delivered the second plenary talk on “An introduction to Gamma-ray Universe”. The talk discussed the most extreme and energetic emissions, namely, Gamma-ray bursts. Several gamma-ray production mechanisms and detection techniques were discussed. The talk highlighted how gamma-ray studies were key in understanding various physical phenomena such as AGNs, blazars etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final plenary talk was delivered by Dr Tapas Baug, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bose.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; SNBNCBS, Kolkata,&lt;/a&gt; on the topic “Galactic massive star formation: Large-scale to small-scale view”.  The talk discussed massive stars and the various mechanisms involved in their formation. The talk also raised our current limitations in understanding this large-scale phenomenon entirely due to the limitations of telescopes. Dr Tapas briefly discussed his work during the talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the presentations, the seminar included networking opportunities, allowing attendees to connect with other scientists and researchers from around India. A hands-on session was conducted by Dr Arun Roy, IIA and Mr Shridharan Baskaran, Research Scholar, CHRIST (Deemed to be University), on various tools available in Python for astronomy. The module Astropy was discussed in detail. Participants were encouraged to write their codes using the discussed modules simultaneously. Participants could visualise several astronomical images by the end of the hands-on session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following panel discussion focused on answering queries put forward by the participants. The panellists included Dr Maheshwar Gopinathan, IIA, Bangalore, Dr Savithri H Ezhikode, Post-doctoral fellow, CHRIST (Deemed to be University), Mr Gourav Banerjee, Research Scholar, CHRIST (Deemed to be University) and Mr Cysil Tom Baby, Project Intern, CHRIST (Deemed to be University). Queries including how to apply for PhD positions, how to apply for projects, and how to approach professors for projects and internship opportunities were discussed in the panel discussion. It was well received by the participants and resource persons alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seminar concluded with the valedictory ceremony, where the best presentations were awarded. The chief guest of the ceremony was Dr Maheshwar Gopinathan. The event coordinator, Dr Sreeja S Kartha, gave a brief seminar report. The seminar concluded with great satisfaction and happiness from the participants. The seminar was a great success, bringing together leading scientists, researchers and students to share their latest findings and exchange ideas. The seminar highlighted the importance of collaboration and innovation in advancing scientific knowledge and understanding the field of astronomy and space science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find copies of the abstract books and the posters presented at the NSAASSR on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://indico.cern.ch/event/1245645/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; seminar website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/proceedings_report_nsaassr_robin</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/proceedings_report_nsaassr_robin</guid>
        
        <category>Proceedings</category>
        
        <category>seminar</category>
        
        <category>national level seminar</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why do some Active Galactic Nuclei Change their Look?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;An active galactic nucleus (AGN) is powered by the matter accreting onto the central supermassive black hole (SMBH) at the centre of a galaxy. Changing look (CL) AGNs are those sources that show rapid change in the column density of the X-ray absorber. CLAGNs show a complex shape in their X-ray spectra. The physical mechanisms responsible for these variations are unclear to date. In this article, we took an attempt to explain the CL phenomena on AGN and their possible origin. For that, we studied the spectral properties of NGC 1365 using joint XMM-Newton and NuSTAR observations. We used JeTCAF model to fit the X-ray spectra of the source. We found that the variable absorption column density correlates with the mass accretion rate and the geometry of the corona. The derived wind velocity was sufficiently low compared to the escape velocity to drive the wind away from the disk for the epochs during which column densities were high. This suggests that the high and variable absorption can be due to failed winds from the disk. Our study construed that the changing accretion rate, which is a fundamental physical quantity and the geometry of the corona are driving the CL phenomena in NGC 1365. The physical picture of this work connects both variable continuum and variable absorbing medium scenarios. Moreover, from the spectral fitting of the joint data, we found the mass of the central black hole to be constant 4.38 ± 0.34−4.51 ± 0.29 × 10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; M&lt;sub&gt;sun&lt;/sub&gt; , in accord with the optical observations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the visible stars that we see in the night sky, there is a hidden zoo of strange astronomical objects that are only visible as signals through high-tech telescopes in multiwavelengths from radio to gamma rays. Some are even Black Holes They are extremely dense, with such a strong gravitational attraction that not even light can escape their grasp. Therefore, black holes seem black! But the light which is coming from the accretion disk  makes them visible through different telescopes. Small black holes populate the universe, but their cousins, supermassive black holes, dominate. These enormous black holes are millions or maybe even billions of times as massive as the sun. Scientists aren’t certain how such large black holes spawn. Once these giants have formed, they gather mass from the dust and gas around them, material that is plentiful in the center of galaxies, allowing them to grow to even more enormous sizes. When such an active supermassive black hole is sitting at the center of a galaxy and illuminating the whole galaxy is called an active galactic nucleus or an AGN. They can launch energetic jets and winds and emit radiation in different wavelengths.  AGNs have an endless supply of fuel, allowing them to power the jets. The accretion of hot gas and dust from the host galaxy is one of the sources of such a seemingly unlimited fuel supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all AGNs appear similar to each other. They are classified depending on the presence or absence of jets, jet morphology, width of emission lines, luminosity, and the orientation in which these AGNs are viewed from the Earth. Depending on either the viewing angle or some intrinsic difference in structure, they can be classified into different spectral types. AGNs not only differ from one another but also change their flux and spectral type drastically in a timescale of hours to decades in both X-ray and optical/UV energy bands, which is why they are often called Changing Look AGNs. What makes them change their appearance has been the subject of much debate recently; however, two main processes are hypothesized to bring about this change: Changing Look due to obscuration and Changing Look due to change in state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often see stars twinkling on a moderately cloudy night. This twinkling behavior is observed due to the irregular movements of clouds in the atmosphere, which changes the amount of brightness seen in stars from time to time through time-dependent obscuration along the line of human sight. Changing obscuration AGNs also have a similar reason for changing their appearance. They show intense time-dependent variability of the line-of-sight intervening gas density/column density, primarily associated with clouds or outflows eclipsing the AGN. Change in the appearance of AGNs due to obscuration is observed mainly in the X-ray wavelength regime. Obscuration by neutral intervening gas can leave a clear imprint on the X-ray emission observed in AGN. At a high column density, obscuration becomes significant enough to suppress the primary continuum of X-rays and produce a secondary continuum through reflections within the gas. Such variations are typically observed in X-Rays as the region which makes these X-rays are small enough to be concealed by the neighboring gases.  Changes in gas densities that cause obscuration are driven by intrinsic AGN luminosity variations, which have an impact on the chemical state of the material. A higher AGN luminosity chemically modifies the obscuring material to become more transparent to X-rays and thereby allows a decrease in line-of-sight column density. Apart from neutral gas obscuration, absorbing gas usually associated with outflows can also strongly affect the X-ray spectrum and is routinely recorded by the detector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu/image1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu/image2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: (upper panel) &lt;em&gt;Credit:&lt;/em&gt; Robert Gendler and The Hubble Legacy Archive, KPNO/NOIRLab/NSF/AURA-Total view of NGC 1365, (lower panel) Cartoon diagram of the model (JeTCAF; jet in two component advective flow model) used to fit the X-ray data. &lt;em&gt;Credit:&lt;/em&gt; arXiv:2107.13808. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing look due to change in state in AGN may arise due to several processes. They are usually observed in the UV/Optical regime due to variability in the accretion phenomenon. In many cases, they can be separated from Changing Obscuration AGN, when a Change in the look of AGN happens in close succession to a change in some intrinsic property of black hole accretion. One such case is a failed wind scenario. Instabilities like thermal or magnetic instabilities can heat up the disk and cause variations in the disk surface temperature and density and thereby making chemical changes in the disk, which directly affects the X-ray radiation. Other events include tidal disruption events, where a star gets close to a black hole and gets torn apart by it. In the process, the debris of the dead star disrupts the gas in the accretion disk of the black hole, which in turn changes the accretion rate and significantly affects the disk along with the X-ray corona, which disappears after a point. Observations do see such effects in different wavebands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our study, we attempted to make a bridge between two main mechanisms, the intrinsic variability in the spectrum and the obscuration along the line of sight. For that purpose, we have analyzed a joint XMM-Newton and NuSTAR satellites’ data of the source NGC 1365 (shown in the left panel of Fig. 1). Here, we briefly explain the data analysis procedures and spectral fitting techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;data-analysis&quot;&gt;Data Analysis&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used joint &lt;em&gt;XMM-Newton&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;NuSTAR&lt;/em&gt; observations of NGC 1365 during 2012 and 2013.  To analyze the XMM-Newton data, we used the Science Analysis System (SAS) version 19.1.0 and followed the standard procedures given in the SAS data analysis threads. We first reprocessed the Observation Data Files (ODF) using the epproc routine to generate the calibrated and concatenated event lists. We filtered the concatenated event lists to remove the periods of high background activity. Furthermore, we extracted the source and background spectra using the evselect routine. We used a circular region with a radius of 32′′ for both the source and the background. We used rmfgen and arfgen tasks to generate the redistribution matrices (.rmf) and the ancillary (.arf) files. Finally, we rebinned the spectra using the task specgroup in order to have at least 25 counts in each bin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NuSTAR data were extracted using the standard NUSTARDAS version 1.3.12 software. We ran a nupipeline  task to produce cleaned event lists and nuproducts to generate the spectra. We used a region of 80′′ for the source and 100′′ for the background using ds9. The data were grouped by &lt;em&gt;grppha&lt;/em&gt; command, with a minimum of 30 counts in each bin. For the analysis of each epoch of observation, we used the data of both XMM-Newton and NuSTAR in the energy range of 0.5−75 keV. We used XSPEC version 12.11.0 for spectral analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;model-fitting&quot;&gt;Model Fitting&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each epoch of observation was fitted using an accretion-ejection-based JeTCAF model (see Right panel of Fig. 1). This model requires six parameters (if the mass is considered as a free parameter), which are (i) the mass of the BH, (ii) the disc accretion rate, (iii) the halo accretion rate, (iv) the size of the dynamic corona or the location of the shock, (v) the shock compression ratio, and (vi) the ratio of the solid angle subtended by the outflow to the inflow. We directly run this model in NASA’s XSPEC software using &lt;em&gt;initpackage&lt;/em&gt; command. Initially, we need to give some guess values of the parameters, then the fitting using the iterative method tries to find the best-fit values by minimizing the chi-square. Along with JeTCAF, we used the two-component absorption model (z)TBABS (Wilms et al. 2000) for both host galaxy and our Galaxy contributions, keeping the Galactic hydrogen column density (NH) fixed to 1.3 × 10&lt;sup&gt;22&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt; . We used chi-square statistics for the goodness of the fitting. A representative fit using JeTCAF is shown in Figure 2. The model-fitted parameters show that NH along the line of sight decreases with mass accretion rate. Using this dependence and considering that the central radiation is illuminating the disk, therefore, the outflow is launching, we have estimated the mass outflow velocity, which is less than the escape velocity of the outflows. This suggests that the winds or outflows that cannot go away from the gravitational well of the BH are blocking the central radiation and may cause the changing look phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: A representative best fit JeTCAF model spectrum of NGC 1365 in the 0.5-75 keV energy band. Different emission and absorption lines are clearly visible. A strong excess below 2 keV energy is also evidenced.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an additional test, we used photoionization simulation using CLOUDY to predict absorption and emission line spectra for the modeled intrinsic spectral energy distribution in JeTCAF. The gas properties used in CLOUDY are taken from JeTCAF model fitting. The simulated spectra for all epochs are shown in Figure 3. The red and blue lines correspond to the ionization parameter (ξ) = 100 and 1000 erg cms&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, respectively. The micro-turbulence of v&lt;sub&gt;turb&lt;/sub&gt;= 1000 km s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; is used in the simulations for all epochs. The CLOUDY simulations show that absorption features are stronger for the low mass accretion state, where N&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt; is high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: CLOUDY simulation of all epochs depicting the emission and absorption features. For the simulation, we used an ionization parameter of 100 (red) and 1000 (blue) erg cm s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, motivated by the observational results. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;our-key-findings-are-as-follows&quot;&gt;Our key findings are as follows:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The accretion rates and the geometry of the dynamic corona changed significantly during the observation period.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The maximum outflow rate estimated is ~12% of the inflow rate and confirmed the previous findings that the outflows are present in the system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The accretion-ejection model-fitted mass is placed within a range between 4.38 ± 0.34−4.51 ± 0.29 × 10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; M&lt;sub&gt;sun&lt;/sub&gt; and, remarkably, matches the optical observation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The outflow velocity is less than the escape velocity infers that the outflowing material could not go farther away from the gravitational potential of the black hole, which is called ‘failed wind’, that blocked the central radiation and caused the changing look phenomena.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, the study of a sample of Changing Look AGN using high-resolution spectroscopy can provide a clearer picture of how this phenomenon is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;acknowledgement&quot;&gt;Acknowledgement:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank Ms. M. Mukherjee for helping with the write-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022A%26A...662A..77M/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Variable mass accretion and failed wind explain changing look phenomena in active galactic nucleus NGC 1365&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Santanu Mondal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tek P. Adhikari, K. Hryniewicz, C. S. Stalin, A. Pandey&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Reference:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022arXiv221105132R/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Changing-look Active Galactic Nuclei&lt;/a&gt; for a review&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu</guid>
        
        <category>clagn</category>
        
        <category>blackholes</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
