<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> Welcome to CosmicVarta.</title>
    <description> Platform for promoting Indian astronomy research to the public.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 15:53:36 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 15:53:36 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bending/Flipping/Reorienting: Superheated plasma outflow from supermassive blackhole producing ‘X’-like fountains</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Embark on a cosmic journey as Gourab Giri explores the enigmatic X-shaped structures observed in radio galaxies, formed by the ejection of jets from supermassive black holes.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Galaxies which are made up of stars and gasses (primarily hydrogen and helium) typically extend over a hundred thousand light years. According to our current understanding of galaxies, it is believed that the majority of them possess a supermassive black hole at their center. In a small fraction of instances, supermassive black holes are observed to transition into an active phase (the reason for which is yet uncertain). During this phase, they not only accrete surrounding gas at an accelerated rate but also throw bits of this matter in the form of jets. These jets consist of super-heated plasma matter gathered from the accretion disc, which is a disc through which a black hole accretes surrounding gas. A part of this matter gets ejected along the black hole’s spinning axis due to strong magnetic disturbances near the accretion zone, helping to maintain the system’s momentum. These events are considered as some of the most powerful incidents in the universe, releasing energy higher than the explosion of a million stars. During these events, the ejected jets of matter travel at speeds approaching that of light, and can extend for distances of several millions of light-years. The ejected matter is expected to propagate along a predestined bidirectional straight path, following the spinning axis of the blackhole (Fig. 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/smbh_plasma_outflow_gourab/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 1: Artist&apos;s impression of what a black hole, its accretion system, and the ejected jets of plasma matter might look like. The black hole is presented in black as no light can escape its gravitational influence beyond a certain point known as the event horizon. The black hole accretes surrounding gas through an accretion disc, and some of the material flowing in this disk is thrown along the black hole&apos;s spinning axis in the form of jets (matter captured from outside the event horizon). The &apos;innermost stable orbit&apos; and &apos;photon sphere&apos; are the last stable orbits around a black hole where matter and light can remain in stable orbits without falling into the black hole, respectively. [Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.esa.int/&quot;&gt;ESO&lt;/a&gt; ]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s discuss the environment through which these jets travel. As mentioned earlier, these jets can cover distances of several million light-years, surpassing the extent of their host galaxies. So, the jets enter into a region known as the intergalactic medium, which lies between galaxies. These mediums are an integral part of the ‘galaxy groups’ or ‘galaxy clusters’, spanning sizes 10-100 times larger than a typical galaxy and housing tens of galaxies within them. In addition to galaxies, these cluster or group mediums are primarily filled with superheated gas, which is incredibly sparse (about 10-25 times less dense than Earth’s air). It’s important to emphasize here that the density of the jets is even lower than that of such surrounding medium. Therefore, when a jet travels through such a medium, it undergoes a significant collision and has to drill through it. This gas in clusters or groups exists in the form of superheated plasma at temperatures of around several million Kelvin, causing it to emit X-rays, which are at the high-energy end of the electromagnetic spectrum. Therefore, to detect their presence, we require X-ray telescopes. Whereas, the plasma outflow from the black hole primarily emits low-energy radio waves, and this emission occurs through a process called synchrotron radiation. In this process, plasma particles revolve around magnetic fields, producing electromagnetic radiation primarily in the form of radio waves. A very small number of these high-speed outflows do not follow their expected paths and instead create curved or bent shapes in the jets (topic of discussion here). Modern radio telescopes with advanced capabilities are now discovering more of these unusual sources. To illustrate one of these anomalies, we will focus on the radio galaxies featuring ‘X-like’ structures. In such sources, in addition to the usual two-directional jet flow, one observes another pair of jet lobes at an angle, forming an X- like shape. These shapes are so unique that we still don’t fully understand how they form. In Fig. 2, we highlight one such source recently discovered using a modern radio telescope in South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure style=&quot;display: flex; align-items: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/smbh_plasma_outflow_gourab/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; style=&quot;width: 75%;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption style=&quot;margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;Fig. 2: X-shaped Radio Galaxy &lt;br /&gt;The galaxy ‘PKS 2014-55’ has been observed using a radio telescope at 1.2 giga-Hertz. In the image, you see a faint gray structure representing a radio galaxy. Notably, there&apos;s a jet of plasma matter extending from the galaxy&apos;s center to a distance of several million light-years. This distance is much larger than the size of the host galaxy, marked by an elliptical shape. Initially, the jet moves in a straight line, indicated by a solid black line. However, it&apos;s clear that the main jet changes direction and splits into another pair of jet structures known as wings, creating an X-shaped pattern. [Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/495/1/1271/5831730&quot;&gt;Cotton et al 2020&lt;/a&gt; ]&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, as the lead author, along with a team of astronomers including Bhargav Vaidya from the Indian Institute of Technology Indore and Christian Fendt from the Max Planck Institute for Astronomy, conducted a study to investigate the formation process of the unusual morphology observed in radio wavelengths in space. To understand the origins and evolution of these unique systems, our focus was on generating these sources through robust computer simulations. This approach was necessary because the natural evolution of these structures typically spans millions of years. To create realistic computer models of these sources, we started by examining advanced radio telescope observations. Following that, we determined the initial conditions for our models using the observational insights related to the environment and sources in which they develop. Next, we implemented the physical processes believed to form these structures. Astronomers proposed two possibilities: (a) an ellipsoidal intergalactic medium causing automatic jet deflection (Backflow), or (b) a complex process near the black hole that forcefully changes the jet’s ejection axis (jet-reorientation). In our study, we explored these two scenarios by incorporating them into our initial conditions and conducting simulations over hundreds of millions of years. To note, we created an ellipsoidal intergalactic medium first, representing a galaxy cluster for the jet to propagate through (Fig. 3). Then, in the first set of simulations, we allowed the jet to propagate undisturbed along one particular direction to observe if it would result in an X-like morphology later on (Backflow case). In the second set, we initially let the jet propagate undisturbed for 70 million years, and then we flipped its direction by 70 to 90 degrees, leading to the formation of X-like structures (jet-reorientation case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/smbh_plasma_outflow_gourab/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 3: A cartoon figure illustrating the ellipsoidal environment representing a galaxy cluster, from the center of which a bidirectional jet begins to propagate (sub-fig (a)). Subfigure (b) depicts the physical process in which we allowed the jet to propagate undisturbed to test whether the tri-axial environment creates any X-like structures. In subfigures (c) and (d), we demonstrated the physical process in which the jet&apos;s propagation direction is forcefully changed to a newer angle of 90 and 70 degrees, respectively, to once again verify whether this model is also capable of generating the X-shaped patterns observed in the vast cosmos. [&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15733&quot;&gt;Refer to the paper&lt;/a&gt;]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through this computer modeling, we wanted to study two crucial aspects: (i) to verify whether there exists any universal formation process that can explain all the observed properties of such sources, and (ii) If not, then determine whether these different formation processes generate any distinguishing signatures that can be used to identify individual models. As we analyzed the outcomes of our simulations running for approximately hundred million years, we uncovered some surprising findings. We observed significant variations in the size and shape of the formed structures, despite all the models generating X-like structures as observed. These differences were particularly evident in the collimation of the arms of the X-shaped morphology, especially in the passive arms where a dying out jet or jet remnant, referred to as a ‘wing’ (see Fig. 2), evolves. Considering the shape, we noticed that when an X-shape formed due to the influence of an ellipsoidal ambient medium (Backflow case), the wings appeared broad and diffuse perpendicular to the jet material’s propagation axis. However, when the jet’s propagation axis was forcibly changed at the center of ejection (jet-reorientation case), the collimation of all four arms of the X-shape remained intact, i.e., they did not get diffused (Fig. 4). In terms of size, we found that the ratio of the length of the passive arm (wing) to the active arm (active lobe) of the X-shape could be less than, equal to, or even greater than one, as also observed in real-world cases in the cosmos. This could be explained by the natural phenomenon of jet reorientation. But it appeared challenging to explain this observational fact when the ambient medium primarily played a role in forming the X-shape by deflecting the jetted material laterally (Backflow model). We gathered similar evidence by studying the cluster environment using X-rays, through which the jet had traveled. As the high-speed jet penetrated the denser ambient medium, it drilled through it, leaving marks of its morphology in the cluster medium by forming less intense cavity regions, bearing the signature of the jet’s morphology imprinted upon them, significantly disrupting the medium. The key finding to note from all these results is that there may not exist any universal model that can naturally account for all the characteristics of X-shaped sources; We are in need of all the models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/smbh_plasma_outflow_gourab/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 4: After nearly a hundred million years of evolution, the ejected jets form X-like structures based on the individual model, each following a different physical process. The point to be noted here is that the structures still exhibit differences in their size (look at the linear and lateral sizes of the arms) and shapes (look at the collimation of the arms), which can serve as distinguishing characteristics for determining the underlying origin when studying X-shaped sources through observation. [&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15733&quot;&gt;Refer to the paper&lt;/a&gt;]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, this study not only demonstrates the computer modeling of likely formation processes and long-term evolution of such sources, but also highlights possible properties associated with X- shapes that can be further used to differentiate between different formation models. In a broader context, the study particularly showcases that the ambient medium through which these jets propagate has a strong interconnected nature. Therefore, any ambiguities appearing in jet morphology are also expected to leave their signature in the ambient environment. This, in turn, can serve as an alternative source of information in understanding the ambiguities occurring within the jet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15733&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Deciphering the morphological origins of X-shaped radio galaxies: Numerical modeling of Back-flow vs. Jet-reorientation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt;  Gourab Giri&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt;  Bhargav Vaidya, Christian Fendt&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Technology Indore, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/smbh_plasma_outflow_gourab</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/smbh_plasma_outflow_gourab</guid>
        
        <category>Active galaxies</category>
        
        <category>Plasma outflow</category>
        
        <category>Supermassive blackhole</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Revealing the mysteries of the Sun&apos;s coronal Magnetic Field using high energy spectropolarimetry</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This article explains the importance of the Sun’s coronal magnetic field. In view of this, this article elaborates the capability of spectral lines emitted in the extreme-ultraviolet and delineates the promising technique of the Hanle effect in deriving the coronal magnetic field.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Sun has one of the most complex magnetic systems, but at the same time it is also the most accessible star to study and model through observations via space-based and ground-based solar telescopes. Being the nearest star to us, the Sun acts as a reference for most of the stars in the universe in terms of luminosity, radius, temperature etc. The part/surface of the Sun that we see from the Earth is called the photosphere, which is actually a giant ball of hot plasma. Above the Sun’s photosphere lies the chromosphere, which is a thin transition region and the extensive corona (corona means “crown”). During the full solar eclipses, the crown-shape of the corona is highly conspicuous from the Earth. However, direct viewing is extremely hazardous to the eyes and therefore, should only be observed using eclipse glasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/high_energy_spectropolarimetry_raveena/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: The black spots are called the sunspots which were observed on July 14, 2023 using the instrument Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (HMI) on board the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO) [Credit: SDO]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presently, the Sun is undergoing the phase of solar maxima and therefore prominent features like sunspots can be seen (Figure 1). Giant explosions of energy and particles are commonly detected during this phase such as Solar flares and Coronal Mass Ejections (CME). The highly energetic particles propagate towards the Earth and, when they interact with the Earth’s outer atmosphere, result in the formation of the beautiful Northern lights, sometimes, also named as aurora borealis (Figure 2). Usually, high-latitude places, like Norway and Iceland, witness the aurorae. But recently, there was a rare sighting of the aurorae at the Indian Astronomical Observatory, Hanle (visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/?q=centres_iao.htm&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), around 23 April 2023, which occurred due to a powerful CME that hit the Earth. These energetic events are strongly driven by the coronal magnetic field, which also affects the Space weather. Therefore, it is important to measure the magnetic field vector and its evolution in the solar atmosphere, especially in the solar corona and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/high_energy_spectropolarimetry_raveena/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Aurorae captured at Fairbanks, Alaska [Credit: Wikipedia]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also an open question in solar physics: why is the solar corona, despite being the outermost layer, hotter than the other inner layers of the Sun? The answer(s) to this question is (are) yet to be determined. One of the potential explanations may be related to the magnetic field. However, there are very few attempts till today to directly measure the magnetic field at the solar corona (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1999A%26A...345..999R/abstract&quot;&gt;Raouafi et al. 1999&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2002A%26A...390..691R/abstract&quot;&gt;2002&lt;/a&gt;). Although the radiation from the Sun’s corona constitutes only 1% of the total radiation of the Sun, there is a treasure of highly ionized wavelengths which originate from the corona (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2004A%26A...427.1045C/abstract&quot;&gt;Curdt et al. 2004&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, scientists believe that building instruments, to observe the Sun at shorter wavelengths below 1200 Å, will help in revealing the secrets of those uncharted regions which have remained hidden in these wavelengths. Extreme ultraviolet (EUV; 100 to 1200 Å) and far-ultraviolet (FUV; 1200 to 2000 Å) radiation do not reach us on the Earth but constitute a major part of the coronal emissions. Therefore, we need to send instruments to space for observing the Sun at these shorter wavelengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few decades, there have been significant advances in EUV solar astronomy, thanks in part to the development of new observational techniques and instrumentation. One of the most important instruments for EUV solar astronomy is the Extreme Ultraviolet Imaging Telescope (&lt;a href=&quot;https://sci.esa.int/web/soho/-/12359-soho-eit&quot;&gt;EIT&lt;/a&gt;), which was launched aboard the Solar and Heliospheric Observatory (&lt;a href=&quot;https://soho.nascom.nasa.gov/&quot;&gt;SOHO&lt;/a&gt;) spacecraft in 1995. The EIT has provided high-resolution images of the Sun’s corona and has allowed astronomers to study the dynamics of the solar wind and the formation of CMEs. Another important development in EUV solar astronomy has been the use of spectroscopy to study the Sun’s EUV emissions. Spectroscopy allows astronomers to measure the wavelengths of light emitted by the Sun and to identify the elements and ions that are present in the Sun’s atmosphere. High-resolution spectroscopic observations by instruments such as, Solar Ultraviolet Measurements of Emitted radiation (SUMER) and the Coronal Diagnostic Spectrometer (CDS) onboard SOHO, have shown a treasure of spectral lines in EUV and FUV which are emitted by the corona. This triggered our interest in studying the magnetic sensitivity of the lines, in terms of the Zeeman effect (interested readers may refer to page 49 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/files/IIA_DOOT_Magazine_Issue_1.pdf&quot;&gt;my article&lt;/a&gt;) and the Hanle effect, to probe the coronal magnetic field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/high_energy_spectropolarimetry_raveena/image3_SUMER_instrument.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Pre-launch image of Solar Ultraviolet Measurements of Emitted radiation (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.mps.mpg.de/projects/soho/sumer/&quot;&gt;SUMER&lt;/a&gt;) instrument on board the ESA/NASA spacecraft Solar and Heliospheric Observatory (SOHO). [Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mps.mpg.de/en&quot;&gt;Max Planck Institute for Solar System Research&lt;/a&gt;]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before understanding the Hanle effect, we must understand the polarization of light.  Light consists of oscillating electric field vectors. When the electric field vector oscillates in all directions in a plane perpendicular to the direction of propagation, such type of light is known as unpolarized light. However, when unpolarized light passes through a filter as shown in Figure 4, the oscillations are confined along one line only. This phenomenon is known as polarization of light, or light is said to be linearly polarized. Now the Hanle effect occurs when, in the presence of an external weak magnetic field, there is a change in this linear polarization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/high_energy_spectropolarimetry_raveena/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: Unpolarized light becomes polarized after passing through a filter. [Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencefacts.net/polarization-of-light.html&quot;&gt;sciencefacts.net&lt;/a&gt;]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From our recent study, it is found that the circular polarization (refers to electric field oscillation in a circular path) signal due to the Zeeman effect is very poor (in the order of 10&lt;sup&gt;-4&lt;/sup&gt; to 10&lt;sup&gt;-5&lt;/sup&gt;) and is beyond the detection capability of the currently available instruments.  Therefore, we studied and identified the spectral lines which are sensitive to the Hanle effect. Due to the stronger linear polarization signals in the order of 10&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; to 10&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;, the Hanle sensitive lines are capable of diagnosing the coronal magnetic field. In order to identify these lines, we estimated essential parameters, such as, the lifetime of the upper atomic level and the polarizability coefficients (defined as the fraction of the linear polarization produced from the incoming light). Each of these calculated parameters have a characteristic value associated with each of the Hanle sensitive lines. Based on these parameters, we sorted out only those lines which are Hanle sensitive and have enough intensity so as to be detected by the future instruments in the weak coronal magnetic field strengths  (~ 1 to 100 Gauss). Figure 5 summarizes the magnetic sensitivity of the Hanle sensitive lines which can be used to calculate the coronal magnetic fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/high_energy_spectropolarimetry_raveena/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 5: Graphical representation of magnetic sensitivity of the spectral lines in the domain of Hanle effect. The domains are shown in rectangular boxes, each of which covers an approximate temperature range along the X-axis and magnetic field strength from 0.1 B&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt; to 5 B&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt; along the Y-axis (Not to be scaled). The middle of each rectangular box along the X-axis represents the peak line formation temperature. FUV spectral lines, having best estimated Stokes V signal, are shown using solid circles at a coronal field of 10 Gauss. [Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11207-022-02024-2&quot;&gt;this work&lt;/a&gt;]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many challenges in building a space-based instrument which need to be addressed with caution. Our study has helped in narrowing down the huge data set to only those magnetically sensitive lines which exist in the typical coronal temperatures of 0.3 to 4 million Kelvin. Most importantly, our work has helped in advancing towards the development of a spectropolarimeter in the EUV and FUV wavelengths, which will allow the entire solar community to tap into many of the unanswered questions about the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11207-022-02024-2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Spectral Lines in FUV and EUV for Diagnosing Coronal Magnetic Field&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt;  Raveena Khan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt;   K. Nagaraju&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/high_energy_spectropolarimetry_raveena</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/high_energy_spectropolarimetry_raveena</guid>
        
        <category>Extreme-ultraviolet polarimeter</category>
        
        <category>Hanle effect</category>
        
        <category>coronal magnetism</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rockets in the Interstellar Medium</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Space vehicles are propelled by rocket engines that generate thrust by expelling exhaust at extremely rapid speeds. As Newton’s third law states “For every action, there is an equal and opposite reaction”, the engines help to accelerate the rockets forward by the effect of the thrust. Interestingly, we can see a phenomenon similar to the motion of a rocket in the sky. The dense and cold molecular clouds are found to show the rocket effect in the presence of the nearby massive ionising stars. The ultraviolet photons emitted from the massive stars ionise the surfaces of the surrounding molecular clouds facing the stars. The hot and ionised material tends to photo-evaporate away from the clouds, accelerating them in the opposite direction, similar to the motion of a rocket. In this work, we found evidence of the rocket effect in several bright-rimmed clouds in the plane of sky.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motion of a rocket is solely based on Newton’s third law: “For every action, there is an equal and opposite reaction”. The engines propel rockets forward by expelling exhaust in the opposite direction at extremely rapid speeds. As the rocket engines ignite, the thrust from the rocket helps the rocket to ascend. Figure 1 (top) shows a rocket launching as an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, not only man-made rockets, one can visualise a phenomenon similar to the motion of a rocket in the interstellar medium (ISM), too. ISM is the area between the stars that often consists of dense clouds in molecular form. These molecular clouds can transform themselves into the birthplaces of young stellar objects (YSOs) through rapid contraction by the dominance of gravity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The birth and evolution of massive stars (mass &amp;gt;= 8M&lt;sub&gt;ⵙ&lt;/sub&gt;) can immensely affect the immediate ISM. Their strong stellar winds or supernova explosions at the end stage of life can compress nearby molecular clouds, turning into a shock that eventually develops non-uniform cloud structures, for example, Bright-Rimmed Clouds (BRCs), cometary globules (CGs), pillars, etc. The heating of the surface layer of the dense cold molecular clouds by the nearby massive star/s has a profound dynamical impact. If the temperature (T) of the surface rises by a factor of 100, the pressure (p) will also increase by the same for a fixed density (ρ), as P ∝ ρ and T. Because of this enhanced pressure the hot and ionised surface of the cloud would try to expand. The expansion will be stopped soon along the direction away from the massive star/s by a large amount of dense material because the density towards that direction is even higher. In contrast, along the direction towards the massive star/s, the cloud surface can “see” a low-density (low-pressure) medium. Therefore, the hot and ionised cloud material starts to flow out of the cloud surface towards the massive star/s, which is known as photo-evaporation flow. As a back reaction of the expelled ionised gas, the cloud starts escalating away from the massive ionising star/s, which is typically known as the ‘Rocket Effect’ (RE). In Figure 1 (bottom), we show an example of the rocket effect in the molecular cloud “Eagle Nebula”. We can see that the surface of the cloud facing the nearby ionising star is relatively bright because of the photo-evaporation, causing the cloud to propel away from the direction of the ionising star, similar to a rocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/rockets_in_interstellar_medium_piyali/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/rockets_in_interstellar_medium_piyali/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: (Top) An example of a rocket launch PSLV C-51 by ISRO from the Sriharikota spaceport. Image credit: &lt;em&gt;Twitter/@ISRO&lt;/em&gt;. (Bottom) An example rocket effect in the molecular cloud, Eagle Nebula. The bright surface facing the massive stars is being ionised and heated up, therefore photo-evaporating away from the cloud. Image credit: &lt;em&gt;NASA, ESA/Hubble and the Hubble Heritage Team&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YSOs forming within these accelerating clouds should share the kinematics similar to the clouds. Therefore, the YSOs would also accelerate radially away from the nearby massive star/s, which is/are responsible for ionising the cloud and triggering the star formation in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2 shows a cartoon diagram of a system consisting of a BRC and one ionising source, where we depict the angles used in our analysis. θ&lt;sub&gt;ip&lt;/sub&gt; and θ&lt;sub&gt;pm&lt;/sub&gt; represent the angle of ionising photons and the angle of the relative proper motion (PM) of YSOs, respectively. By relative proper motion, we mean the motion of the YSOs in the plane of the sky with respect to the ionising massive star/s. The θ&lt;sub&gt;pm&lt;/sub&gt; is estimated by the median angle made by the relative proper motion of the candidate YSOs, starting from the celestial north (the point about which all the stars in the northern hemisphere are seen to revolve) and increasing eastward. We estimate the θ&lt;sub&gt;ip&lt;/sub&gt; as the angle made by the line joining the ionising source and the central IRAS source residing in each BRC. The θ&lt;sub&gt;ip&lt;/sub&gt; values are also measured following the same convention as it was done for θ&lt;sub&gt;pm&lt;/sub&gt;. Considering an ideal RE scenario, θ&lt;sub&gt;ip&lt;/sub&gt; is expected to be similar to θ&lt;sub&gt;pm&lt;/sub&gt;, i.e. &lt;span style=&quot;white-space: nowrap;&quot;&gt;| θ&lt;sub&gt;ip&lt;/sub&gt; − θ&lt;sub&gt;pm&lt;/sub&gt; |~ 0&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, on the sky plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/rockets_in_interstellar_medium_piyali/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: An illustration of a system consisting of a BRC (blue cloud with a thick yellow-coloured rim) and an ionising source (blue star) (not to scale). The YSOs distributed towards the BRC are presented using red star symbols. The direction of photoevaporation flow of the cloud material is shown using yellow-coloured arrows. The black-coloured arrow, making an angle θip with respect to the north and directing away from the ionising star, is the direction of ionising photons. Another black-coloured arrow making an angle θpm with respect to the same and directing away from the YSOs presents the angle of their relative PM. Image credit:&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/513/2/2039/6580586&quot;&gt; Saha et al. (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-sources-studied-in-this-work&quot;&gt;The sources studied in this work&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the catalogue of &lt;a href=&quot;https://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/pdf/1991ApJS...77...59S&quot;&gt; Sugitani et al. 1991&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/pdf/1994ApJS...92..163S&quot;&gt; Sugitani et al. 1994&lt;/a&gt;, we collected a total of 89 BRCs. Among them, we selected 22 BRCs that are suitable for our analysis (please see &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/510/2/2644/6460503&quot;&gt; Saha et al. 2021&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnrasl/article/515/1/L67/6640430?login=true&quot;&gt; Saha et al. 2022&lt;/a&gt; for selection details). We conducted a pilot study in &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/510/2/2644/6460503&quot;&gt; Saha et al. 2021&lt;/a&gt; to investigate the θ&lt;sub&gt;ip&lt;/sub&gt; and θ&lt;sub&gt;pm&lt;/sub&gt; in BRC 18 as it is one of the closest BRCs and also a well-studied candidate. The YSOs towards BRC 18 are collated from literature, and their distances and proper motions were obtained from a space-based telescope named Gaia (for details, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/missions/gaia/in-depth/&quot;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;). We performed the same analysis for other BRCs in &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnrasl/article/515/1/L67/6640430?login=true&quot;&gt; Saha et al. 2022&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results-and-discussion&quot;&gt;Results and Discussion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Figure 3, we show the relative proper motions of the YSOs in BRC 18 on the Wide-field Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE) colour composite image using 3.6 (blue), 4.5 (green), and 12 (red) μm images. The arrows in yellow represent the relative proper motion vectors of the candidate YSOs with respect to the ionising source λ Ori. The dashed line in cyan represents the direction of the ionising radiation from λ Ori with respect to the IRAS (Infrared Astronomical Satellite) source (‘ + ’ symbol in green) embedded in BRC 18. The median value of the relative proper motions of the candidate YSOs (i.e. θ&lt;sub&gt;pm&lt;/sub&gt;) and the direction of ionising photons (i.e. θ&lt;sub&gt;ip&lt;/sub&gt;) are indicated using vectors in green and white, respectively. All the angles are measured from the celestial north.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/rockets_in_interstellar_medium_piyali/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: The relative proper motion properties of the YSOs in BRC 18 on the WISE colour composite image using 3.6 (blue), 4.5 (green), and 12 (red) μm images. The arrows in yellow represent the relative proper motion vectors of the candidate YSOs with respect to λ Ori. The dashed line in cyan represents the direction of the ionising radiation with respect to the IRAS source (‘ + ’ symbol in green) embedded in BRC 18. The median value of the relative proper motions of the candidate YSOs and the direction of ionising photons are indicated using vectors in green and white, respectively, in the lower right corner (not to scale). Figure credit: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/510/2/2644/6460503&quot;&gt; Saha et al. (2021)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found &lt;span style=&quot;white-space: nowrap;&quot;&gt;|θ&lt;sub&gt;ip&lt;/sub&gt; − θ&lt;sub&gt;pm&lt;/sub&gt;|=1&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt; ± 14&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in BRC 18, i.e. the directions of the ionising photons and the median relative proper motion of the YSOs are almost parallel. Motivated by this result, we tried to perform the same analysis on the remaining BRCs. As discussed in the previous section, we studied 21 more BRCs, excluding BRC 18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis found that ∼64% of the BRCs show &lt;span style=&quot;white-space: nowrap;&quot;&gt;| θ&lt;sub&gt;ip&lt;/sub&gt; − θ&lt;sub&gt;pm&lt;/sub&gt; |≤ 45&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. This is to note that, as the proper motion of the YSOs is along the plane of the sky, we miss the information of motion along the line of sight (radial component). Therefore, the &lt;span style=&quot;white-space: nowrap;&quot;&gt;| θ&lt;sub&gt;ip&lt;/sub&gt; − θ&lt;sub&gt;pm&lt;/sub&gt; |∼ 0&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt; might not always be satisfied because of the possible presence of a significant component of motion of the YSOs in the BRCs/ionising sources along the line of sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the lack of information about radial motion of the YSOs/ionising sources, we found that most of the BRCs follow our assumption, confirming the presence of the “Rocket Effect”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work has been published in the Letter of Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;acknowledgements&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors sincerely thank the reviewer, Dr. Alexander Slater Binks, for his constructive remarks, which significantly improved the manuscript. The authors also thank the CosmicVarta team for showing interest in this work and invitation to write about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnrasl/article/515/1/L67/6640430&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Investigation of rocket effect in bright-rimmed clouds using Gaia EDR3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt;  Piyali Saha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt;  G Maheswar, D K Ojha, Tapas Baug, Sharma Neha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Satyendra Nath Bose National Centre for Basic Sciences, Salt Lake, Kolkata 700 106, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/rockets_in_interstellar_medium_piyali</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/rockets_in_interstellar_medium_piyali</guid>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Collisions between galaxies: A frequent phenomenon than we expected earlier</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Initially, early-type galaxies were considered aged, evolved systems with a reddish appearance, primarily comprising older stars and lacking young star formation due to limited gas and dust resources. However, contemporary techniques, such as integral field spectroscopy for studying star motion within galaxies and advanced telescopes with heightened sensitivity, have brought forth surprising discoveries. These discoveries have unveiled significant reservoirs of gas and dust, as well as intricate stellar structures hidden beneath the seemingly uniform distribution of stars in many of these galaxies. This article explores the potential origins of these intriguing phenomena occurring on a galactic scale.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A galaxy constitutes a collection of stars, often numbering in the hundreds of billions, accompanied by gases such as hydrogen, helium, heavier dust particles, and a minor proportion of super-heated plasma matter generated by cosmic phenomena. Using observation from different telescopes, we explore these constituents to understand their origins, spatial organization, and how galaxies transform over billions of years. Every galaxy also possesses an exotic substance called dark matter. This enigmatic matter doesn’t engage with light, yet we understood its existence as they impart gravitational force (very important for the galaxy to remain gravitationally bound). With modern optical telescope technology, we can observe galaxies in different colour filters such as green or red. This essentially enables us to see the distribution of galaxy light arising from arrangements of different types of stars, since different stars emit more in different colours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of galaxies arose in 1926, when Hubble made a groundbreaking discovery that there are entities beyond our home, the Milky Way. These turned out to be other galaxies scattered across the immense cosmos. Hubble’s close examination of these galaxies led to the identification of two primary types: (a) Spiral galaxies, characterized by arms resembling spiral shapes, and (b) Elliptical galaxies, whose arrangement of stars results in an ellipsoidal shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/collisions_between_galaxies_gourab/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 1: The picture on the left is a cartoon of a spiral galaxy. Its centre is whitened to highlight the region, and has arms that spiral outward, creating the galaxy&apos;s spiral shape. The image shows different varieties of spiral structures that are actually observed in the cosmos. On the right, there&apos;s a drawing of an elliptical galaxy. The white part in the centre is the core, and the stars in this galaxy are spread out in a shape like a stretched circle, which is known as an ellipse. These galaxies are actually 3D structures, but when we observe them in the sky, they appear to be projected 2D images (as presented). [Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/galactic-explorer/en/&quot;&gt;NASA Science&lt;/a&gt; ]
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Fig. 1, such galaxies have been demonstrated via a schematic diagram. In this article, only early-type galaxies, which constitute elliptical galaxies and S0 galaxies will be in focus. S0 galaxies are a transition phase between an elliptical and a spiral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early-type galaxies were initially considered to be older, evolved galaxies with a reddish appearance. They are mainly composed of older stars and lack young star formation due to their limited gas and dust content, which are necessary components needed to trigger the formation of stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern techniques like integral field spectroscopy (used to determine star motion within galaxies), and advanced sensitive telescopes have uncovered surprising findings. They show that there is a significant amount of gas and dust, along with complex stellar structures, hidden beneath the apparent uniform distribution of stars in many of these galaxies. This suggests that such galaxies are not merely old and static entities drifting in space; rather, they possess vibrant and dynamic structures that undergo continuous evolution. In-depth examinations of these complex structures over the course of around five decades have unveiled their origin as a result of collisions or mergers between galaxies (Fig. 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This silent collision process usually takes over a billion years to reach completion; this time is of course lesser than the age of the universe (current estimated age is 13.7 billion years). Detecting these underlying complex structures remains difficult due to the fact that their typical intensity is nearly 10% of the entire galaxy’s intensity. Hence, this remains a hazy topic of galaxy evolution research. Gaining insight into the process by which early-type galaxies transform into their present form through collision of galaxies, particularly within the local universe, remains a puzzle to astrophysicists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/collisions_between_galaxies_gourab/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 2: Real images of galaxies that are currently undergoing collision, forming asymmetric star distribution around the bigger galaxy. These galaxies are identified as NGC 474 (left) and M 51 (right). [Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022A%26A...660A..28B/abstract&quot;&gt;Bilek.2022&lt;/a&gt;  (left) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.astrobin.com/7hwtz0/&quot;&gt;Astrobin&lt;/a&gt;  (right)]  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to gain a better understanding of the impact of galaxy collisions on the evolution of early-type galaxies, a research team from India, with myself as the lead author, along with Sudhanshu Barway (Scientist at the Indian Institute of Astrophysics) and Somak Raychaudhury (currently Vice Chancellor at Ashoka University), conducted a study. This study involved gathering deep-exposure optical (in the red filter) images of local early-type galaxies (within roughly 600 Mega-light years of us), and then utilizing advanced techniques to identify any indications of recent merger activity through the presence of such sophisticated structures. The galaxy images were gathered using an optical telescope situated in a desert area in New Mexico, known as the ‘Sloan Digital Sky Survey’. This project’s motivation was to create a detailed map of galaxies in that region of the sky through long exposure, achieved by combining multiple scans of the same sky region and subsequently stacking them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the remarkable capability of these deep exposure galaxy images to reach an incredibly low surface brightness limit of 28.5 magnitudes per square arcsecond, allowing us to spot objects that are an astounding 20.7 quadrillion times fainter than the Moon, there’s still a need for specialized image processing.  It helps in revealing merger structures with even fainter intensity, extracting hidden richness from these remarkably faint images. These methods are known as ‘Unsharp Masking’ and ‘Model Subtraction’ in the scientific terms. In a naive language, they do the following: they create a slightly blurred version of the galaxy image and then subtract it from the original one. This helps bring out less intense features in the image, particularly those with weaker intensity. Think of it like a trick photographers use to make pictures pop by boosting contrast, a technique that is quite familiar to photographers for enhancing image quality (see Fig. 3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/collisions_between_galaxies_gourab/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 3: The left picture displays a section of the Moon captured using a 12-inch telescope. In the middle, the same image is shown after undergoing a blurring process. The blurred image is subtracted from the original, resulting in a residual image in the right. This final image exhibits enhanced contrast, helping in identifying a greater number of structures on the Moon&apos;s surface.  [Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.astronomy.ohio-state.edu/pogge.1/Ast350/Unsharp/&quot;&gt;Ohio-state.edu&lt;/a&gt; ] 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon utilizing the techniques mentioned above on our galaxy images, a rather unexpected discovery unfolded. We found that a significant number, nearly 85%, of the early-type galaxies within our sample of 202 exhibited merger structures. This figure appears to be higher than the findings from various past studies, indicating the significance of conducting such investigations with deep exposure images. Most importantly, when we combine what we have observed with predictions from computer simulations designed to understand how galaxies evolve, we expect this percentage to increase even more. This leads us to the conclusion that most, if not all, early-type galaxies in our nearby universe are constantly changing as they interact, collide, merge, and accrete other nearby galaxies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thereafter, our attention shifted towards examining the morphology of merger structures – essentially, how they appear in terms of their size and shape. We aimed to determine if each of these geometries could provide us with specific story about the past processes of galaxy assembly. Even though the structures looked non-linear, their shapes are unique, which allowed us to classify 11 types of merger debris around the early-type galaxies. These shapes include geometries like tails, shells, disks, boxes, thin threads, rings, dusty formations, and even complex structures that don’t fit into any specific category (see Fig. 4 for some of the examples).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/collisions_between_galaxies_gourab/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 4: A collection of galaxy images displays discovered merger remnants, showcasing shapes such as a shell (a), a fan-type extension (b), a stream of stars (c), a stellar tail (d), and the presence of dusty in the galaxy (e). These are a few selected examples in which the merger structures are notably bright and can be identified in the original galaxy image. This presentation serves to showcase the complex geometry of these merger structures. For sharper merger features follow our paper: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/520/4/5870/7036778&quot;&gt;MNRAS_520.5870.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study aimed to do more than just identify merger structures and determine their availability in our nearby universe. We additionally planned to categorize these merger structures into different groups. This approach would help us gain a clearer understanding of their likely formation history solely by analysing their shapes. After four years of determined effort, we have successfully developed a classification system for such structures (Fig. 5). The classification is divided into four main categories based on the mass ratios of colliding galaxies in a collision event: recent minor mergers (mass ratio ≤ 10:7), recent major mergers (mass ratio &amp;gt; 10:7), relaxed galaxies (evolving passively without recent mergers), and galaxies undergoing collisions (interacting class). To refine this, we have also split recent early-type galaxies with minor merger features into three sub-groups based on colliding galaxy mass ratios. Similarly, recent major merger types are divided into two subgroups based on post-merger galaxy masses. In easy words, we can say that the complicated shapes we see in merged galaxies might actually point towards certain physical processes that likely caused these intricate features. This finding is a crucial advancement in the study of galaxy mergers and their evolution. It serves as a fundamental checkpoint for astrophysicists to quickly grasp the type of physical processes behind the systems they’re investigating. This step is also affordable to carry out since data from various telescopes’ extensive surveys is readily available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/collisions_between_galaxies_gourab/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 5: The way we classified the merger structures is based on the sizes of the galaxies involved in a collision process. We used a parameter called ‘r’, which is the ratio of the smaller galaxy’s mass to the bigger one’s (with ‘r’ being less than or equal to 1). We labelled the structures for each category in the classification tree, shown in the right. Because there are different ways some structures can form, therefore they are placed into more than one group in our classification system. [Refer to: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/520/4/5870/7036778&quot;&gt;MNRAS_520.5870&lt;/a&gt;] 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/520/4/5870/7036778&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Remnants of recent mergers in nearby early-type galaxies and their classification&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt;  Gourab Giri&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt;  Sudhanshu Barway, Somak Raychaudhury&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Technology Indore, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/collisions_between_galaxies_gourab</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/collisions_between_galaxies_gourab</guid>
        
        <category>Galaxy Collision</category>
        
        <category>Galaxy Evolution</category>
        
        <category>Structures of Galaxy Mergers</category>
        
        <category>Galaxy Interaction Rate</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aditya-L1: India&apos;s Array of Instruments on a Journey Closer to the Sun, Continuing a Legacy of Space Excellence</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Sun has fascinated mankind since the dawn of civilization. From famines to fertile farms, every aspect of life on Earth was defined by it. Unaware of the true nature of the Sun, humans have worshipped this mighty celestial being for thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was not until 400 years ago, when Galileo first looked at the Sun through his telescope, that humans realized the Sun is very dynamic and has its style of fluctuations. This triggered the genesis of observing the Sun by the ‘scientific method’. Over this time, we have realized that the Sun has several layers in its atmosphere and that they look very different when observed at different wavelengths. This led us to the pursuit of understanding the sun’s activity in its various layers, from the photosphere to the outer atmosphere and further out in space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable these studies, several organizations all over the globe have established telescopes on the ground and in space. India has been a part of this huge network of observatories, with contributions from telescopes like MAST at Udaipur Solar Observatory, radio observations with the Ooty Radio Telescope and Gauribandur Radio Observatory, and the rich historical data of the Sun from the Kodaikanal Observatory, spanning over three solar cycles. India is next venturing into space to observe the Sun with its first dedicated space-based solar observatory, Aditya-L1. It will be traveling to the Sun-Earth Lagrange 1 point, making the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO) the third space agency to send a spacecraft to L1, after NASA, ESA, and the Chinese CNSA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spacecraft will be placed in a halo orbit around L1, located 1.5 million km from the Earth towards the Sun. One might wonder why there’s a need to observe the Sun from space when it’s feasible to do so from the Earth. While ground-based observations rely on the prevailing atmospheric conditions at the observation site, they are also limited in continuous monitoring. The Earth’s atmosphere scatters the incoming sunlight, causing the day sky to be bright and blue, making the million times fainter corona of the Sun invisible from the Earth’s surface. The corona is made visible by a total solar eclipse, however, restricting the duration of observation to a couple of minutes. Moreover, the atmosphere cuts a significant portion of UV light and charged particles from the Sun, necessary to support life on the surface of the Earth. Therefore, uninterrupted observation of the solar corona and UV radiance and detection of the charged particle flux from the Sun justify the need for a space-based vantage point at L1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/aditya_l1/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: A schematic diagram of Aditya-L1 Payloads (credits: ISRO)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aditya-l1-payloads&quot;&gt;Aditya-L1 Payloads&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aditya-L1 has a collection of 7 instruments to study various aspects of the Sun. ASPEX, PAPA and MAG are in-situ in nature, which detects multiple conditions happening locally at the L1 vantage point. In contrast, VELC, SUIT, SoLEXS and HEL1OS detect the real-time activity on the Sun, making them ex-situ in nature. The significance and functionality of the various payloads are discussed in detail in the coming sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;visible-emission-line-coronagraph-velc&quot;&gt;Visible Emission Line Coronagraph (VELC)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visible Emission Line Coronagraph (VELC) is a payload on Aditya-L1 with simultaneous imaging and spectroscopic diagnostics capability. VELC contains a multi-slit spectrograph that will perform spectral observation in three visible emission lines, 5303 Å, 7892 Å, and 10747 Å, which are emitted at very high temperatures when iron loses many of its electrons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/aditya_l1/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 2: The imaging (3 Rⵙ) and spectroscopic (1.5 Rⵙ) field of view of VELC along with the slits. (Credits: IIA)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field of view of VELC starts from 1.05 Rⵙ (1.05 Solar Radius), close to the solar limb, and it can perform spectroscopic measurement in corona up to 1.5 Rⵙ. Furthermore, VELC can diagnose temperature at slit positions, using intensity ratio of spectral lines and magnetic field using spectropolarimetry observations. These unique capabilities of VELC will help us to understand the initiation mechanism of Coronal Mass Ejections (CMEs) and the forces responsible for their evolution in the corona, which still needs to be fully understood. Apart from that, the process responsible for heating the corona and propelling the fast solar wind remains enigmatic. The corona’s electron temperature and density values influence several theoretical frameworks aiming to clarify this process. Consequently, temperature and density above the polar coronal hole can provide limits and restrictions for theoretical mechanisms elucidating the heating of coronal plasma and the acceleration of the fast solar wind.
VELC can also provide thermal and non-thermal components of velocities from spectroscopic observations. The variation of the non-thermal velocity component with distance in the corona can also indicate the processes responsible for coronal heating. The capabilities of VELC are sufficient to achieve these goals and provide a new view on these long-standing problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solar-ultraviolet-imaging-telescope-suit&quot;&gt;Solar Ultraviolet Imaging Telescope (SUIT)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Solar Ultraviolet Imaging Telescope (SUIT) is an off-axis Ritchey-Chretien type telescope built to observe the sun in eight narrow and three broad bandpasses within the 200-400 nm wavelength spectrum. The specific scientific targets of these filters are tabulated below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table style=&quot;width:100%; border-collapse: collapse;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;th style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Spectral Channel (nm)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Solar Feature&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Bandpass (nm)&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB1- 214&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Photosphere&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;11.55&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB2- 276.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Wing of MgII K line&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;~0.4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB3- 279.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Mg II k line&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;~0.4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB4- 280.3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Mg II h line&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;~0.4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB5- 283.2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Wing of Mg II h line&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;~0.4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB6- 300&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Sunspots&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB7- 388&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Lower Photosphere&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;NB8- 396.85&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Ca II line&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;0.1&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;BB1- 200-242&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;Continuum&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;BB2- 242-300&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;O3v Hartley Band&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;58&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr style=&quot;border: 1px solid black; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;BB3- 320-360&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;O3 Hartley-Huggins Band&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&quot;border: 1px solid black;&quot;&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SUIT is designed to continuously take images of the sun in all of its 11 scientific bandpasses every two hours. Additionally, SUIT has the capability for 2x2 on-chip binning and shall take binned full disk images in the Mg-II h band every minute for a more dynamic view. It also enables user-defined region of interest (RoI) selection, enabling the possibility for a faster cadence while observing a small area of the Sun. SUIT has a pixel resolution of 0.7”/pixel, comparable to that of SDO/AIA (0.6”/pixel) and SDO/HMI (0.5”/pixel), making it easy to co-align them without much rescaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SUIT electronics offer high flexibility and come packed with a “Flare mode” dedicated to observing the emergence of a solar flare in NUV. So, it has the means to detect a solar flare in its early stages and image them as they develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aditya-solar-wind-particle-experiment-aspex&quot;&gt;Aditya Solar Wind Particle EXperiment (ASPEX)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ASPEX is an in-situ payload with multi-directional data acquisition capabilities. Within ASPEX, there are two distinct subsystems: SWIS (Solar Wind Ion Spectrometer) and STEPS (SupraThermal and energetic Particle Spectrometer), comprising two and six units, respectively. The principal research aim of SWIS is to analyze solar wind plasma particles, while STEPS focuses on examining suprathermal and solar energetic particles (Goyal et al. 2018). Multiple units of these spectrometers are strategically mounted across the spacecraft to enable simultaneous measurements from various directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novelty of ASPEX lies in its multi-directional, high-cadence, and proton-alpha differentiated measurements. SWIS will continually monitor low-energy (100 eV - 20 keV) proton and alpha particles individually in radial and azimuthal directions and integrated flux in the meridional direction. It possesses an extensive field of view (FOV) of 360 degrees in and across the ecliptic plane, along with a modest latitudinal coverage of 6 degrees. Conversely, STEPS will measure higher-energy (20 keV/n - 5 MeV/n) ion flux from six directions: Sun-radial, Intermediate, Parker Spiral, North Pointing, South Pointing, and Earth Pointing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This unique payload, developed by the Physical Research Laboratory (PRL), Ahmedabad, will contribute to our understanding of solar wind ion variations and aid in identifying their source mechanisms. It will be especially valuable in studying the variation in ion abundance ratios during transient events like CME, CIR, and interplanetary shocks. Additionally, it will effectively examine the variations and disparities in the thermal anisotropy of protons and alpha particles. Moreover, it will be crucial to explore the origins of suprathermal particles in the solar wind and their association with SEPs. Its specialized design will also allow for the assessment of the role of Earth’s bow shock in generating suprathermal particles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plasma-analyser-package-for-aditya-l1-papa&quot;&gt;Plasma Analyser Package for Aditya L1 (PAPA)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PAPA is another in-situ payload on the spacecraft and is engineered by the Space Physics Laboratory (SPL) at VSSC, Thiruvananthapuram. This payload consists of two subsystems: the Solar Wind Electron Energy Probe (SWEEP) and the Solar Wind Ion Composition Analyser (SWICAR). Both sensors are mounted perpendicularly to each other and share a unified processing unit within the same chassis. PAPA will be instrumental in studying the composition and energy distribution of solar wind particles. The payload is specifically designed to investigate the velocity distribution and temperature anisotropy of solar wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;magnetometer-mag&quot;&gt;Magnetometer (MAG)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fluxgate Magnetometer (MAG) is one of three in-situ payloads on the Aditya L1 spacecraft, alongside ASPEX and PAPA. This triaxial magnetic sensor is mounted on a 6-meter, 5-segment deployable boom and is situated on the Sun-facing deck of the spacecraft. One set of MAG sensors is located at the tip of the boom, while a second set is positioned midway along the boom, 3 meters from both the tip and the spacecraft. This payload was developed by the Laboratory of Electro-Optics Systems (LEOS) in Bangalore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This apparatus renders the Aditya L1 spacecraft a comprehensive observational platform. It enhances the data collected by other in-situ payloads on board, providing measurements of both the magnitude and direction of the interplanetary magnetic field. The primary aim of MAG is to investigate the magnetic characteristics of the surrounding solar wind as well as transient phenomena like Corotating Interaction Regions (CIR) and Coronal Mass Ejections (CME) at the Sun-Earth L1 point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solexs&quot;&gt;SoLEXS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoLEXS is a soft X-ray spectrometer built to detect an energy range of 1 keV to 22 keV at a resolution of 250 eV (at 6 keV and &amp;lt; 0 deg C). This signifies that spectral features separated by 250 eV can be distinctly detected. Two apertures of 10 mm^2 and 0.1 mm^2 provide a field of view of 1.8 sq deg and 1.3 sq deg, respectively, with two separate silicon drift detectors to cover from A class to X class flares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hel1os&quot;&gt;HEL1OS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HEL1OS, on the other hand, operates in the 10-150 keV range, with a significant spectral overlap with SoLEXS. Aimed at detecting hard X-rays, it offers a spectral resolution of 1 keV at 13.81 keV through its CdTe detector and ~7 keV at 59.5 keV through its CZT detector. The X-rays are collimated by a stainless steel collimator, giving the payload a field of view of 6 x 6 degrees. It is the only payload mounted inside the panels of the satellite, increasing the criticality severalfold. It was necessary to first mount HEL1OS and close the satellite body. Other payloads and equipment could be mounted on the panels. Thus, any modifications in the HEL1OS would require removing all the payloads and sensitive equipment on the satellite and opening the satellite body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoLEXS and HEL1OS shall operate both as independent payloads, and their functionality shall be augmented with SUIT for early detection of solar flares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If seen in a broader sense, all the payloads on board Aditya-L1 shall simultaneously observe the Sun and make in-situ and ex-situ measurements. The data from SUIT can be combined with VELC to get a broad view of the Sun, from the photosphere to the corona. Additionally, augmentation of SoLEXS and HEL1OS triggers with SUIT electronics can help detect flares at an early stage for faster imaging and flare emergence (Sarkar et al., Poster, ASI 2022). This nature of several instruments augmenting the functionality of several others gives us the ability to generate scientifically exclusive data, keeping the true spirit of an observatory class mission alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/aditya_l1/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 3: Field of view of VELC and SUIT. Correlation of NUV solar photosphere and chromosphere with solar corona (Credits: Sreejith P., SUIT Team/ MCNS.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/strong&gt; The authors are thankful to Abhilash Sarwade of the Space Astronomy Group, URSC, ISRO, one of the prime members of the SoLEXS team, for helping them with critical information about SoLEXS and HEL1OS. Prateek extends his gratitude for the invaluable support received from Dr. Dibyendu Chakrabarty of PRL, Ahmedabad, the Principal Investigator of ASPEX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/aditya_l1</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/aditya_l1</guid>
        
        <category>International</category>
        
        <category>India</category>
        
        <category>ISRO</category>
        
        <category>Aditya-L1</category>
        
        <category>Sun</category>
        
        <category>Solar exploration</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Utilization of Navigation with Indian Constellation (NavIC) for space weather and upper atmospheric studies </title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Ionospheric irregularity studies are important aspects for understanding ionospheric physics and related processes, especially near the low-latitude regions. This work, for the first time, shows the nature of the ionospheric irregularities present during these observation days and sets a path forward for further studies of the other scintillation causing irregularities over the dynamic low-latitude regions of the globe. This work is beneficial to the space physics community and pertinent to the radio astronomy community, where understanding the nature of the ionospheric variabilities and their corresponding mitigations becomes important for fruitful astronomical studies of radio sources.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ionosphere is the ionized (where an atom or a molecule acquires a negative/positive charge by gaining/losing electrons, with the resultant being an ion) region of our planet’s atmosphere, extending from 60 km to beyond 1000 km above the surface of the Earth, with the equatorial and low-latitude regions, confined within ±30° latitude, accounting for nearly one-third of the total global ionization. It has deleterious effects (loss of communication, loss of signal, error in precise positioning, etc.) on high frequency (MHz to GHz range) radio communications, and global navigation satellite systems (GNSS) (like the GPS). As long-range radio waves (about 30-500 kHz) are significantly affected by the ionosphere, constant observation of the ionospheric uncertainties is crucial for communication and navigational systems to work with higher efficiency. The ionosphere, in addition to daily variation, becomes perturbed due to the geomagnetic storms, which are responses of our planet’s magnetosphere to solar eruptions like the Coronal Mass Ejections (CMEs) and the solar flares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important phenomenon related to the equatorial and low-latitude ionosphere is the scintillation of satellite signals. One can imagine these scintillations to be analogous to the stars that twinkle in the night sky as a result of variations in the density of the atmosphere. More scientifically, the process of post-sunset plasma instabilities in the equatorial ionosphere generates irregularities and large-scale depletions in the electron density (the plasma bubbles). Radio waves propagating through these irregularities experience the processes of diffraction and scattering, which cause random fluctuations, in the Very High Frequencys’ (30-300 MHz) and L-band’s (1-2 GHz) signal amplitude, phase, the direction of propagation and polarization referred to as scintillations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)-developed Navigation with Indian Constellation or NavIC (motivated by the word: नाfवक) is a satellite constellation consisting of geostationary orbit (GEO) and geosynchronous orbit (GSO) satellites in its space segment at an altitude of about 36000 km above the surface. It is designed and developed to provide positional accuracy information to Indian users and extends to about 1500 km region from its boundary (https://www.isro.gov.in/SatelliteNavigationServices.html). These satellites broadcast signals in 24 MHz bandwidth of spectrum in the L5 (117.45 MHz) and the S1 (2492.028 MHz) frequencies. The broad applications of NavIC are transportation: terrestrial, aerial as well as marine, location-based services, personal mobility, resource monitoring, surveying and geodesy, time dissemination and synchronization, safety-of-life alert dissemination, and scientific research related to the upper atmosphere and space weather impacts on communication and navigational systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/space_weather_and_upper_atmospheric_studies_sumanjit/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: The schematic of the GEO and the GSO satellites of NavIC.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Credits: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unoosa.org/documents/pdf/icg/2022/Tokyo2022/NavIC_GNSS_Training2022.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.unoosa.org/documents/pdf/icg/2022/Tokyo2022/NavIC_GNSS_Training2022.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current publication presents an effort to calculate the scale sizes of these ionospheric irregularities to have caused scintillations in the L-band NavIC and GPS under geomagnetically quiet and disturbed conditions. Ionospheric observations from GPS and NavIC receivers placed at the locations Indore (near the equatorial ionization anomaly (EIA)) and Hyderabad (in between EIA and the magnetic equator) are selected for this purpose. They are located in and around the low-latitude region (which by itself is highly dynamic in terms of variability in the ionization, especially due to the presence of the EIA) over India. One of the fundamental parameters of any GPS receiver is the signal intensity from which the carrier-to-noise (C/No in dB-Hz) and the corresponding scintillations are observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this work, data were from a GNSS receiver, operational at the Department of Astronomy, Astrophysics and Space Engineering (DAASE), Indian Institute of Technology Indore (IITI), capable of receiving GPS L1 (1575.42 MHz), L2 (1227.60 MHz), and L5 (1176.45 MHz) signals and specialized for ionospheric monitoring and space weather research. Here, the amplitude and phase samples get generated at 50 Hz to calculate the C/No. We followed a similar procedure as shown in (https://doi.org/10.1016/j.asr.2019.12.019). Data were also taken from the NavIC receivers, capable of receiving L5 and S1 (2492.028 MHz) signals along with the GPS L1 signal. both operational at the DAASE, IITI and the Department of Electronics and Communication Engineering, Osmania University, Hyderabad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2 shows how this C/No varied with respect to the time of the day (in Universal Time, UT) for the 7 satellites of NavIC (PRNs 2-7) during the strong space weather event on 08 September 2017 over Indore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/space_weather_and_upper_atmospheric_studies_sumanjit/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 2: The C/No (dB-Hz) variation during the disturbed day of September 8, 2017, as observed by the L5 signal of NavIC satellite PRNs 2-7 over Indore.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Credits: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.02218&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.02218&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For analysis of the irregularity scale sizes responsible for the drops observed in PRNs 5 and 6 in the above figure, we use the power spectral analysis which is motivated by the ionospheric phase screen model (https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1029/RS014i006p01135). The following figure shows the power law behavior of the 1-hour time bin (number of data points in 1 bin = 3600) around the C/No drops observed earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;

  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/space_weather_and_upper_atmospheric_studies_sumanjit/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/space_weather_and_upper_atmospheric_studies_sumanjit/image4.png&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 3: The power spectral density variations with the least square fit (black solid line) corresponding to the bins of intense C/No variation of Figure 2&lt;br /&gt; &lt;em&gt;Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.02218&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.02218&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the phase screen theory, we then calculate the slope and the corresponding irregularity scale sizes responsible for the variations in the C/No observed in Figure 2. We have validated this with a similar observation using the GPS receiver over this location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we performed the same analysis for two other cases (under quiet and moderate geomagnetic activity) and calculated the slopes (p) and the probable scale sizes (L) of irregularities that were present and have caused C/No drops or scintillations in the NavIC satellite signals. The tables (Credit: https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.02218) below show the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/space_weather_and_upper_atmospheric_studies_sumanjit/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work, for the first time, shows the nature of the ionospheric irregularities present during these observation days and sets a path forward for further studies of the other scintillation causing irregularities over the dynamic low-latitude regions of the globe. This work is beneficial to the space physics community and pertinent to the radio astronomy community, where understanding the nature of the ionospheric variabilities and their corresponding mitigations becomes important for fruitful astronomical studies of radio sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.02218&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;First results of Low-latitude Ionospheric Irregularities measured by NavIC and GPS near the Anomaly Crest and the Magnetic Equator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Sumanjit Chakraborty&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Abhirup Datta, Deepthi Ayyagari&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; 
Physical Research Laboratory (PRL), Ahmedabad, India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/space_weather_and_upper_atmospheric_studies_sumanjit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/space_weather_and_upper_atmospheric_studies_sumanjit</guid>
        
        
        <category>Earth and Planetary Astrophysics</category>
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Origin of ultra-bright blazar emissions: An astronomer’s glimpse into cosmic volcanoes</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Blazars are a rare class of active galactic nuclei (AGN), in which the jets are pointed directly toward our line of sight, making them one of the brightest yet extremely compact sources. Relativistic effects such as beaming makes the jet emission the dominant component. Blazars exhibit multiwavelength variability across several timescales (varying from hours to years). However, the location of the emission region with respect to the central engine is an open question. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.515.1655B/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barat et. al (2022)&lt;/a&gt; try to address this question by combining information from multiwavelength variability of a sample of 11 blazars. Comparing the energy of the detected flares in multiple wavelength bands to state-of-the-art numerical models we put constraints on the location of the emission region.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-blazars&quot;&gt;What are blazars?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blazars are the most luminous non-transient objects known in the universe; they often emit across all electromagnetic bands from radio all the way to gamma-rays, which is unlike any other astrophysical source studied till date. Blazars also exhibit multiwavelength variability over timescales of a few hours to months and years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every galaxy is known to host a super massive black hole (SMBH, weighing a million to billion times more than our Sun) at its center. Sometimes, these giant monsters can feed off gas in the interstellar medium by forming large accretion disks. These accretion disks convert the gravitational potential energy of the infalling material to electromagnetic radiation, making them extremely bright, outshining the entire galaxy consisting of billions of stars. The inner compact region of a galaxy hosting a supermassive black hole is only a few astronomical units (AU) in size (roughly the scale of the solar system), which is negligible compared to the rest of the galaxy, which can be tens of thousands of light years across (1 ly = 63421 AU). Thus, a compact yet extremely luminous inner region of a galaxy, powered by the accretion of the SMBH at its heart is called an Active Galactic Nucleus (AGN). It has been observed that in roughly 10% of the cases, these AGNs are accompanied by large scale jets or outflows, orthogonal to the accretion disk which can extend as far out as thousands of light years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Artists’ impression of accretion black hole. &lt;em&gt;Credits: European Space Agency (ESA)&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the unification model proposed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1995PASP..107..803U/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Urry and Padovani (1995)&lt;/a&gt;, blazars are a sub-class of AGNs, where the jets are pointed towards our line of sight (see Figure 1). The jets are composed of ultra-relativistic plasma powered by the accretion energy and are launched very close to the SMBH. The situation is comparable to staring down the vent of an active volcano; because of relativistic effects, the radiation from the jet is beamed towards us making it extremely bright and outshining the contribution from any other region of the SMBH. Infact, most of the extragalactic high energy (gamma-ray) radiation we detect can be attributed to blazars. Till date, we have detected over 2000 blazars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: A schematic diagram showing the AGN unification model &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1995PASP..107..803U/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Urry and Padovani (1995)&lt;/a&gt;. The central Super Massive Black Hole (SMBH) is powered by the infalling material through the accretion disk. The AGN is also accompanied by fast and slow moving gas clouds in its vicinity (Broad-Line and Narrow-Line regions respectively) and a relativistic plasma jet launched close to the SMBH. The existence of a distant gas-dust envelope, called the torus is also known for such objects. Depending on the orientation of the SMBH with respect to our line of sight, we perceive it as a different object. In blazars, the jet is oriented along our line of sight, the entire emission is dominated by the beamed radiation from the jet, making them the brightest non-transient objects in the universe. &lt;em&gt;Image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1412.1177&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Reynolds et. al (2014)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;characterizing-a-blazar&quot;&gt;Characterizing a blazar&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two generic characteristics of blazar emissions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blazars are known to be highly variable sources, exhibiting variability across all wavelengths and a wide array of timescales starting from hours to months and years. A typical time-series of blazars (see Figure 2) shows `flares’ or sporadic outbursts of varying amplitudes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blazars have a characteristic double-peaked spectral energy distribution (SED), with a lower energy peak around optical-UV frequencies and a higher energy peak around X-rays and gamma rays (see Figure 3).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variability seen in blazar light curves is explained by the rapid energization of the underlying plasma. The reason for such rapid acceleration is an active area of research. However, the rapid acceleration and subsequent cooling of the plasma can explain the ‘outbursts’ we observe in the blazar lightcurves. The shape of the SED points towards non-thermal modes of emission (i.e., not like a blackbody spectrum which results from a thermalized object like a star).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lower energy peak in the SED can be explained by synchrotron emission by the relativistic plasma particles (electrons, positrons or possibly even protons).  In the presence of a magnetic field, charged particles are known to ‘gyrate’ due to Lorentz force, and as a result emit electromagnetic radiation (Maxwell’s laws predict that charged particles produce electromagnetic radiation). In the relativistic limit, this radiation due to charged particles is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.exul.ru/education/1/Note3f.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;synchrotron emission&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The higher energy peak is produced due to inverse-Compton scattering of low energy photons by the same ultra-relativistic particles in the plasma which produce the synchrotron emission. As photons interact with charged particles, there is an exchange of energy and momentum between them. In the low energy regime, the photon imparts energy to the charged particle (Compton scattering), however if the charged particle is ultra-relativistic, it can upscatter the low energy photon to very high energies &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.exul.ru/education/1/Note3f.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Inverse Compton scattering)&lt;/a&gt;. In this process, low energy optical photons can be energized to X-rays/gamma-rays producing the second peak in blazar SEDs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 2: Gamma-ray time-series observations of well known blazars 3C-279 (upper panel), PKS-1510-089 (middle panel) and PKS 2155-304 (bottom panel) taken using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fermi.gsfc.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fermi telescope&lt;/a&gt;. The red circles represent the observed flux. The time series is characterized by multiple sporadic outbursts or flares of varying sizes and durations. The entire lightcurve can be decomposed into a cumulative effect of a number of such flares (green spikes) and each flaring activity could be connected to an energy injection event within the jet. Blazars exhibit such variability across a wide range of electromagnetic frequencies (radio, IR, optical and X-rays) and often such multiwavelength variability is found to be correlated. &lt;em&gt;Image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/482/1/743/5126366&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Roy et. al (2019)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 3: The observed spectral energy distribution (SED) of the blazar Mrk 421 &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2011ApJ...736..131A/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Abdo et. al 2011)&lt;/a&gt;. The lower energy peak around the optical-UV wavelengths is attributed to synchrotron emission and the higher energy peak (X-ray/𝝲-ray) can be explained using the inverse-Compton mechanism (See text for detailed explanation).  This double humped SED is a universal characteristic of all blazars. &lt;em&gt;Image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.08401&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tavecchio 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;where-does-the-blazar-emission-originate&quot;&gt;Where does the blazar emission originate?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The location of the emission site within a blazar jet is an open question; several astronomers have suggested that the emission region is located near the Broad Line Region (BLR) within ~1 parsec (3.26 lightyears) of the central SMBH. However, there is also strong evidence suggesting that the emission site could be located further downstream (1-10 parsec), for e.g., the detection of extremely high energy gamma-rays from these sources which would have been absorbed within the BLR and never made it to our telescopes. Therefore, a constraint on the location of the emission zone within a jet would be extremely important for refining our theoretical understanding of blazars and their emission mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.515.1655B/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Barat et. al (2022)&lt;/a&gt; proposed a new and complimentary prescription to constrain the location of the emission region within the blazar’s jet. The same population of ultra-relativistic particles is responsible for both the synchrotron (low energy) and inverse-Compton (high energy) emission. Therefore, any outburst in high energy gamma-rays can be accompanied by a similar outburst in lower energies such as optical and such events can be considered to have originated at the same location. Such simulatemous outburst events are termed ‘flare pairs’ (see Figure 4). In this paper, we analyzed simultaneous gamma-ray light curves from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fermi.gsfc.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fermi space telescope&lt;/a&gt; and optical light curves from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.astro.yale.edu/smarts/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yale-SMARTS program&lt;/a&gt; for 11 blazars and identified 25 flare pairs. We found that the ratio of the energy dissipated in the optical to gamma-ray flares roughly varies between 1-10% (Figure 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high energy emission, coming from Inverse Compton scattering, requires a supply of low energy photons. This seed photon field could either be provided by the synchrotron photons produced within the jet itself, or could be externally supplied from the Broad-Line Region (BLR) and/or the molecular torus (See Figure 1). For lower energy blazars, up-scattering of the external seed field dominates the gamma-ray emission. The density and energy of the seed photon field is strongly distance dependent, therefore the location of the emission region with respect to the BLR and molecular torus determines the total energy output in the gamma-rays compared to optical frequencies.  We developed detailed numerical models to simulate blazar outbursts from optical to gamma-ray energies. The ratio of the optical to gamma-ray flare energies were estimated from the simulated light curves for a range of distances from near the BLR up to 10 parsecs (Figure 5). From this, we were able to conclude that for most of the flare pairs identified, the emission region was likely to be located farther away compared to the BLR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constraining the emission site of blazars has important implications for the underlying physics of these extreme objects. In this paper, we develop an idea to constrain the location of emission by comparing the energy dissipated in gamma-rays and optical frequencies for outburst events where we have simultaneous optical and gamma-ray flare detections. Our numerical models suggest that most of the events we detected are likely to have originated beyond the BLR region, close to the molecular torus. This approach is a novel and complementary approach to determine the emission location and application to a broader sample of blazar flare pairs is necessary to validate this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image6.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 4: Top: Simultaneous gamma-ray (upper panel) and optical (lower panel) light curves of the blazar PKS 2326-502 observed using the Fermi space telescope and in the Yale-SMARTS program, respectively (orange points). The decomposed flares in both the light curves are shown with red lines and the identified flare pairs are numbered. Bottom: Raxtio of observed energy ratio of optical and gamma-ray flares identified as ‘flare pairs’ for the sample of 11 blazars analyzed in this study. The ratio varies between 1-10% approximately. &lt;em&gt;Image:&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.515.1655B/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Barat et. al (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata/image7.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 5:  Dependence of optical to gamma-ray outburst energy ratio for ‘flare pairs’ simulated for the blazar PKS 2326-502. The position of the BLR and the molecular torus have been shown with blue dashed lines. The green dotted line shows the median value of the energy ratio observed for this blazar (Figure 4, right panel). The simulated light curves were generated using detailed numerical models of dominant emission mechanisms like synchrotron and inverse-Compton scattering. The simulations show that the observed energy ratio of the flare pairs is more consistent with an emission region located farther downstream of the jet from the BLR. &lt;em&gt;Image:&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.515.1655B/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Barat et. al (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Further resources&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fspas.2017.00006/full&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fspas.2017.00006/full&lt;/a&gt;
, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1986rpa..book.....R/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rybycki Lightman (1986)&lt;/a&gt;
, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2020mbhe.confE..35C/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Costamate 2020&lt;/a&gt;
, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mdpi.com/2075-4434/10/1/35&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Prandini 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022MNRAS.515.1655B/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Locating the GeV emission region in the jets of blazars from months time-scale multiwavelength outbursts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Saugata Barat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ritaban Chatterjee, Kaustav Mitra&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; 
Anton Pannekoek Institute for Astronomy, University of Amsterdam, Netherlands
Presidency University, Kolkata, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/ultra-bright_blazar_emissions_suagata</guid>
        
        <category>Active galactic nuclei</category>
        
        <category>jets</category>
        
        <category>blazars</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Ghost of a Star Screams 6 Days After Its Death</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dying heavy stars forms black holes and sometimes emit jets, producing very narrow-angle flashes of gamma rays known as Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs). This article summarises the findings from the follow-up of such a GRB 210204A. The GRB showed typical afterglow decaying behaviour while seen in optical bands for up to a week. However, about a week later, we detected some unusual brightening in the emission from this GRB. We investigate possible causes for this flaring and conclude that the most likely cause is a refreshed shock in the jet. The high energy properties suggest that GRB 210204A might not have any special properties that caused late-time flaring. Our analysis of the GRB 210204A shows that the late time bump in the light curve is likely due to the late time flaring activity. The flare of GRB 210204A is the latest flare detected to date.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A certain class of massive stars end their life in a violent explosion. As these massive stars end their life, they sometimes launch powerful jets during this process (~1.3 out of every 100) as if they are screaming as they take their last breath. These jets are very narrow-angle flashes of gamma rays known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma-ray_burstGamma-Ray&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs)&lt;/a&gt;. GRBs were discovered accidentally in 1967 while Vela satellites were looking for traces of nuclear tests on Earth and rather detected a very short duration burst (~10 sec) of gamma rays coming from space. Within a few years, astronomers were able to conclude that these events do not belong to our neighbourhood, nor to our solar system, nor to our Galaxy. GRBs are extragalactic and are detected from all directions in the universe. These jets are extremely powerful and emit as much energy as the Sun would emit in its entire lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last 20 years, various gamma-ray satellites have baeen launched to study these events. To date, we have detected over five thousand GRB events. The study of the full sample suggests that there exist two types of these GRBs: 1) Short Gamma-ray Bursts and 2) Long Gamma-ray bursts. 
As the name suggests, Short GRBs are very short in duration  (less than 2 seconds). Compact object merger events are mainly responsible for the majority of these bursts. These are mainly found in the outskirts of elliptical galaxies, where there is a high population of compact binary objects. On the other hand, Long Gamma-ray bursts originate from the death of massive stars. Arms of spiral galaxies where new stars are formed are the common sites of Long GRBs. In such regions, new stars are born and die (usually as a supernova) very quickly and thus have higher chances of being a promising site of Long GRBs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 4th Feb 2021, one such event, ‘GRB 210204A’, was detected by various gamma-ray satellites, including the first Indian multi-wavelength astronomy satellite ‘AstroSat’. A team of Indian astronomers studied this unusual event to explain its behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ghost_of_a_star_harsh/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: An artistic impression of Gamma-ray burst. &lt;em&gt;Credits: Anna Serena Esposito&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GRBs are among the brightest electromagnetic events in the Universe since the Big Bang. These bursts are highly energetic flashes of gamma rays and radiate ~10&lt;sup&gt;51-53&lt;/sup&gt; erg of energy within a few seconds. Interaction of these jets with the nearby interstellar medium (ISM) creates an afterglow that shines in all electromagnetic bands. As an analogy, you can think of the main GRB jet as burning coal with flames and the remaining embers as the afterglow, which shines for a longer time. The afterglow usually becomes fainter with time as the central engine stops. However, in some cases, a re-brightening in the afterglow is seen due to chaotic central engines. Such events are typically seen between seconds to hours after the main burst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GRB 210204A started looking like an ordinary GRB - steadily fading for a few days. But, after ~7 days, it showed rebrightening by a magnitude, not once but twice. This is very unusual for GRBs as there is no way a central engine could be active at this time. It is like a Diwali firecracker that goes boom and shows flashes again after an hour when no one is expecting it to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ghost_of_a_star_harsh/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 2 shows the luminosity decline (light curve) of GRB 210204A based on data from various Indian facilities. The re-brightening at ~12 days after the event is clear in the inset image when it deviates significantly from the expected power-law behaviour (red-dashed line).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team of astronomers from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iitb.ac.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IITB)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Astrophysics Bengaluru (IIA)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/aries-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES)&lt;/a&gt; and National Centre for Radio Astrophysics (NCRA), led by Harsh Kumar, PhD student at the Department of Physics of IITB, came together, with other international collaborators, to study GRB 210204A. They used various Indian facilities like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/growthindia/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GROWTH-India Telescope (GIT)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/?q=telescope_iao&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Himalayan Chandra Telescope (HCT)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/facilities/astronomical-telescopes/360cm-telescope/telescope&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Devasthal Optical Telescope (DOT)&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/facilities/astronomical-telescopes/130cm-telescope&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Devasthal Fast Optical Telescope (DFOT)&lt;/a&gt; for optical data, AstroSat for gamma-ray data and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gmrt.ncra.tifr.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope (GMRT)&lt;/a&gt; for radio data to find plausible reasons behind the re-brightening of the afterglow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ghost_of_a_star_harsh/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 3 shows a comparison of the re-brightening time (along the y-axis) and relative flux of re-brightening in GRB 210204A, marked in red, with previously known GRB re-brightening events. It clearly indicates that GRB 210204A is the most delayed flaring detected so far.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors detected the most delayed flaring ever from a GRB event, explained as being caused by “Refreshed Shock”, where two shells with different speeds that were emitted almost simultaneously collided at later times. The findings are highly significant as they highlight complex behaviour in GRB events. This research, published in the Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society (MNRAS) journal, emphasised late-time monitoring and the need for multi-wavelength data to understand the nature of these events in further detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.07587&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The long-active afterglow of GRB 210204A: Detection of the most delayed flares in a Gamma-Ray Burst&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt;  Harsh Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt;  Rahul Gupta, Divita Saraogi, Tomás Ahumada, Igor Andreoni, G.C. Anupama, Amar Aryan, Sudhanshu Barway, Varun Bhalerao, Poonam Chandra, Michael W. Coughlin, Dimple, Anirban Dutta, Ankur Ghosh, Anna Y. Q. Ho, E. C. Kool, Amit Kumar, Michael S. Medford, Kuntal Misra, Shashi B. Pandey, Daniel A. Perley, Reed Riddle, Amit Kumar Ror, Jason M. Setiadi &amp;amp; Yuhan Yao&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (IITB);  Main Gate Rd, IIT Area, Powai, Mumbai, Maharashtra 400076&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/ghost_of_a_star_harsh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/ghost_of_a_star_harsh</guid>
        
        <category>GRBs</category>
        
        <category>Optical</category>
        
        <category>Black Hole</category>
        
        <category>Compact Objects</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Looking at five radio-quiet AGN through the polarization lens</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This article discusses the results from our combined radio polarization and emission line study of five type-2 radio-quiet quasars. We investigate the origin of radio emission in these sources and understand what impact the local gaseous environments have on the nature of radio outflows in them. Our work further sheds light on the potential of using radio polarization as an efficient tool to look for signatures of AGN feedback in the relatively understudied class of radio-quiet AGN.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AGN are amongst the most energetic and extraordinarily radiant phenomena in the Universe. They are powered by supermassive black holes (SMBHs; with masses ranging between 106 − 1010 solar masses (M⊙)) that are actively accreting matter through an accretion disk and releasing tremendous amounts of energy in the form of radiation and outflows. While AGN exhibits a variety of classes, such as quasars, Seyfert galaxies, radio galaxies, blazars, etc., they all share some fundamental constituents, which include (see Figure 1): a SMBH at the center, an accretion disk, an X-ray emitting corona presumably located above the accretion disk, fast moving, dense gas clouds giving rise to the broad optical emission lines (broad line region or BLR), slow moving, relatively less dense gas clouds giving rise to the narrow optical emission lines, (narrow line region or NLR) and a doughnut-shaped torus of gas and dust (&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781139170901&quot;&gt;Peterson, 1997&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1086/133630&quot;&gt;Urry &amp;amp; Padovani, 1995&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/five_agn_polarization_silpa/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: The standard model of AGN by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1086/133630&quot;&gt;Urry &amp;amp; Padovani, 1995&lt;/a&gt;. Figure taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1010.6281&quot;&gt;Khassen (2010)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AGN are classified as type-1 and -2 based on their optical spectra: type-1 AGN exhibit both broad and narrow emission lines while type-2 AGN exhibit only narrow emission lines. These differences have been suggested to arise as a result of the different viewing angles of the central engine (see Figure 1). The torus is believed to surround the central engine and obscure the BLR clouds from certain lines of sight (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.aa.31.090193.002353&quot;&gt;Antonucci, 1993&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1086/133630&quot;&gt;Urry &amp;amp; Padovani, 1995&lt;/a&gt;). The sources viewed edge-on (i.e, when the observer’s line of sight intersects the torus) are recognized as type-2 AGN while the sources viewed face-on are recognized as type-1 AGN. Quasars, which are known to be an extremely luminous and highly accreting class of AGN, have been traditionally associated with type-1 class. However, recent studies have identified a few type-2 quasars as well based on their optical spectra (for e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1086/133630&quot;&gt;Reyes et al., 2008&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1086/133630&quot;&gt;Mullaney et al., 2013&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, powerful and collimated structures of relativistic plasma, known as jets, are launched perpendicular to the black hole-accretion disk interface. In 10-20% of the AGN population, these jets extend over scales ranging from a few hundred kiloparsecs (kpc) to several megaparsecs (Mpc); this class is called radio-loud (RL) AGN. On the other hand, a vast majority of the AGN population (80−90%) launch weak and small-scale radio jets of typically less than 10 kpc in extent. They may, alternatively, host poorly collimated wind-like or bubble-like, diffuse radio outflows. These constitute the radio-quiet (RQ) class of AGN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/five_agn_polarization_silpa/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2. Diagram of synchrotron emission (https://emmaalexander.github.io/resources.html) by Emma Alexander/ CC BY 4.0 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AGN jets emit synchrotron radiation at radio frequencies. Synchrotron radiation is produced by relativistic charged particles spiraling around magnetic field lines, and is concentrated within a narrow cone pointing in the direction of the particle motion (see Figure 2). Synchrotron radiation is intrinsically linearly polarized in the plane perpendicular to the magnetic fields. Radio polarization observations can, therefore, provide information about the orderliness and orientation of the magnetic fields giving rise to the synchrotron emission. According to the synchrotron theory, the magnetic fields are inferred to be parallel to the electric polarization vectors for optically thick regions like the core, and perpendicular for optically thin regions like jets, lobes and hotspots. For ordered magnetic fields and optically thin regions, the maximum theoretical fractional polarization of synchrotron emission is expected to be 75%. However, in reality, since the magnetic fields also consist of a random component, the fractional polarization is observed to be typically lower than this intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, as the electromagnetic radiation passes through the region between the source and the observer, it interacts with the intervening magneto-ionic medium that consists of free charges and magnetic fields, resulting in the rotation of the plane of polarization of the electromagnetic wave. This effect is known as Faraday rotation (see Figure 3), which when coupled with other factors such as observing bandwidth and telescope beam could cause a further drop in the fractional polarization. The mechanisms causing depolarization (i.e., drop in the fractional polarization) of the radio emission can be broadly categorized as external and internal. The former (latter) refers to the case where the Faraday rotating medium is extrinsic (intrinsic) to the synchrotron emitting plasma (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/133.1.67&quot;&gt;Burn 1966&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-8711.1998.01782.x&quot;&gt;Sokoloff et al. 1998&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/five_agn_polarization_silpa/image3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Faraday rotation of a polarized electromagnetic wave as it propagates through the magneto-ionic medium. Figure taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stab1641&quot;&gt;Ferri`ere et al. (2021)&lt;/a&gt;.			 				 		
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘AGN feedback’ is a process by which AGN impact and regulate the growth and evolution of their host galaxies (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-astro-081811-125521&quot;&gt;Fabian, 2012&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-astro-082214-122316&quot;&gt;King &amp;amp; Pounds, 2015&lt;/a&gt; for details). AGN feedback is believed to shape the black hole-bulge mass relation, which is the correlation between the black hole mass and the luminosity (and mass) of the bulge component of the host galaxies. AGN feedback can have both positive and negative impacts on galaxy evolution. AGN feedback could either suppress star formation and thereby prevent inordinate growth of massive galaxies (called ‘negative feedback’) or could enhance star formation locally (called ‘positive feedback’). Traditionally, AGN feedback is known to come in two modes: (i) quasar-mode, which is typically associated with quasars that drive high-velocity winds capable of removing the star-forming fuel from host galaxies, and ultimately resulting in the shut-down of star-formation, and (ii) jet-mode, which is associated with low accretion rate AGN that launch large-scale jets capable of transferring the power mechanically and regulating star-formation. In order to develop a comprehensive picture of galaxy formation and evolution in the Universe, an in-depth understanding of AGN feedback is indispensable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AGN feedback has become an important constituent in the cosmological simulations of galaxy formation and evolution. However, finding observational signatures of this phenomenon is a challenging task and an active area of ongoing research. One way AGN can influence the gas in the host galaxies is through galactic-scale outflows that can transport matter and energy from the central engine to the host environments. It is widely believed that these outflows are driven by large-scale, powerful jets in RL AGN. However, whether these outflows are prevalent in RQ AGN, and if so, what drives them is still an unsettled question. Over these years, a lot of progress has been made in understanding how AGN feedback operates in RL AGN, but not so much in case of RQ AGN, with only a handful of them having been looked at so far. Yet, what is exciting even from these minimal studies is that despite lacking large-scale, powerful radio outflows, RQ AGN could be efficient agents of AGN feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limited AGN feedback studies in RQ AGN is a major setback in our attempts towards understanding how the Universe is working, since the majority of the AGN in the Universe are RQ. Probing AGN feedback in RQ AGN has been difficult because the radio emission in these sources can arise from a wide range of mechanisms like star formation, low-powered small-scaled jets, AGN/starburst winds, coronal emission, or even a combination of them with each of them being able to impact the interstellar medium (ISM) differently (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1038/s41550-019-0765-4&quot;&gt;Panessa et al. 2019&lt;/a&gt;, for details). Therefore, AGN feedback in RQ AGN becomes a two-fold problem: first probing the relative radio contributions from different emitters, and then determining their relative roles in driving galaxy-wide outflows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we have presented results from our 5 GHz B-array (resolution∼1 arcsec) Karl Jansky Very large Array (VLA) polarimetric observations in conjunction with the archival [O iii] images from the Hubble Space Telescope (HST) of five type-2 RQ quasars selected from the Quasar Feedback Survey sample (QFeedS; find out more about this survey at  &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.ncl.ac.uk/quasarfeedbacksurvey/&quot;&gt;the project website&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stab549&quot;&gt;Jarvis et al. 2021&lt;/a&gt;). This paper aims to establish the origin of radio emission (jet or wind) in these sources and the impact of the local gaseous environments on the nature of the radio outflows in them. This paper also explores the potential of using radio polarization as a tool to look for signatures of AGN feedback in these sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 5 sources that constitute our sample are: J0945+1737, J1000+1242, J1010+1413, J1356+1026, J1430+1339. These sources, from their previous studies of spatially resolved radio and [O iii] observations, are known to exhibit powerful and galactic-scale [O iii] outflows, prominent kpc-scale radio structures that are likely to be dominated by jet emission and a close association between radio emission and [O iii] emission. These sources, therefore, can serve as potential candidates to study the interplay of jets, winds and emission-line gas in the poorly studied class of RQ AGN. We used the Astronomical Image Processing System (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-astro-081811-125521&quot;&gt;AIPS&lt;/a&gt; ) and Common Astronomy Software Applications (&lt;a href=&quot;https://casaguides.nrao.edu/index.php/VLA_Continuum_Tutorial_3C391-CASA4.6&quot;&gt;CASA&lt;/a&gt; ) software to reduce and analyze the VLA data of our sources (see for details of the analysis &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stac1044&quot;&gt;Silpa et al. 2022 &lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results-and-discussion&quot;&gt;Results and Discussion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We detect polarization in 4 sources, viz. J0945+1737, J1000+1242, J1356+1026 and J1430+1339. This is a good detection fraction given that the sample is RQ. J1010+1413 is the only unpolarized source in our sample. The lack of polarization in this source could either be due to limited sensitivity of our observations or due to strong depolarization effects. In Figures 4 and 5, we present the VLA images of J0945+1737 and J1430+1339 (popularly known as “Teacup” quasar) respectively, at 5 GHz in the B-array configuration. The black contours represent VLA 5 GHz B-array total intensity image (with ~1 arcsec resolution), the red ticks represent the  polarization electric vectors (whose lengths are proportional to the linear polarized intensity), the gray-scale background represents HST [O iii] image and the cyan contours represent higher resolution (~0.25 arcsec) VLA 6 GHz A-array total intensity image (taken from &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stz556&quot;&gt;Jarvis et al. 2019 &lt;/a&gt;). Please refer to the original paper (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stac1044&quot;&gt;Silpa et al. 2022 &lt;/a&gt;) for similar images of other sources. Polarization is detected as discrete knots in these sources. The polarization vectors have the same orientation within each knot while they are different between the knots (see Figures 4 and 5). The polarized emission seems to be arising from compact regions with ordered B-fields. The radio cores exhibit about 0.5 − 1% fractional polarization, which is also typically expected for RL AGN, while the lobes reveal higher fractional polarization (10 − 30%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The higher resolution (i.e., ~0.25 arcsec) images of J0945+1737, J1000+1242, J1010+1413 and J1430+1339 show radio structures that resemble jets and hotspots. However, in the case of J1356+1026, the higher resolution imaging has only revealed a radio core. In addition, all 5 sources possess radio cores and lobes with steep to ultra-steep radio spectrum. The 4 sources that show polarization display complexities in their polarization structures as well as in the orientation of their inferred magnetic fields. Based on these results, we can deduce that the radio emission in J0945+1737, J1000+1242, J1010+1413 and J1430+1339 is likely to be originating from low power jets. These jets possess kinetic powers in the range of 10&lt;sup&gt;43&lt;/sup&gt; − 10&lt;sup&gt;44&lt;/sup&gt;  erg s&lt;sup&gt;−1&lt;/sup&gt; . However, we cannot fully discern the origin of radio emission (among jet or wind) in J1356+1026 with the current data. Please see Table 1 where we summarize the results for our individual sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Source name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Possible origin of radio emission&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Polarization detected?&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;J0945+1737&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Jet&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;J1000+1242&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Jet&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;J1010+1413&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Jet&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;J1356+1026&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Uncertain&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;J1430+1339&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Jet&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
Table 1: Summary of the results for individual sources.			 				 		
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/five_agn_polarization_silpa/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: VLA 5 GHz B-array (resolution∼ 1 arcsec) total intensity contours in black for J0945+1737 superimposed with polarization electric vectors (whose lengths are proportional to linear polarized intensity) in red, HST [O iii] image in gray-scale and VLA 6 GHz A-array (resolution∼ 0.25 arcsec) total intensity contours in cyan. 			 				 		
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/five_agn_polarization_silpa/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 5: Same as Figure 4, but for J1430+1339. 			 				 		
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous studies of these sources have shown that the radio emission spatially overlaps with [O iii] emission in them (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stz556&quot;&gt;Jarvis et al. 2019 &lt;/a&gt;). Our study suggests that the polarized knots more often do not spatially overlap with the [O iii] emission. Polarization is predominantly seen in regions of jets and lobes that have a dearth of [O iii] emission while it is mostly absent in regions dominated by [O iii] emission. Such a spatial anti-correlation between polarized radio emission and [O iii] emission has been observed in some of the RL AGN in the literature, and is often explained as a result of the depolarization of radio emission by the emission line gas. As already mentioned in the Introduction, this can happen in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(i) external depolarization, where the radio lobes of the source are surrounded by emission line gas clumps/clouds, with the typical sizes of these clumps being smaller than the telescope beam, (ii) internal depolarization, where the emission line gas entrained inside the radio lobes mixes with the synchrotron lobe plasma and depolarizes the lobe emission. In order to study the depolarization effects in greater detail, we modeled different depolarization mechanisms acting in the lobe of one of the sources: J0945+1737. This was done by fitting the sub-band polarization data for this source with the equations given in &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/133.1.67&quot;&gt;Burn 1966&lt;/a&gt; (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stac1044&quot;&gt;Silpa et al. 2022 &lt;/a&gt;, for details on fitting and analysis). This source was chosen since it was the only one (out of 4) that showed significant polarization in individual sub-band images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By modeling external depolarization of the lobe emission in J0945+1737, we obtained the size of the emission line gas clumps/clouds to be of the order of 10&lt;sup&gt;-5&lt;/sup&gt; pc. Interestingly, we also found that the range of the cloud sizes obtained for RQ AGN from our work (10&lt;sup&gt;-5&lt;/sup&gt; pc - 1300 pc) broadly spans the range derived for the lobes of the radio galaxies (which are RL AGN) in the literature (10&lt;sup&gt;-5&lt;/sup&gt; pc - 300 pc). By modeling internal depolarization of the lobe emission in J0945+1737, we estimated the amount of the thermal gas mixed with the synchrotron plasma in its lobe to be of the order of 106 M⊙. Similar studies have not been extensively carried out for RQ AGN in general, and this sample, in particular. However, our result agrees with the estimates of the ionized gas masses (∼ 10&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt; − 10&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt; M⊙) obtained for some of the Seyfert galaxies (which are RQ AGN) in the literature from optical spectroscopic and imaging studies. For comparison, in the lobes of the radio galaxies, much higher estimates of the mixed thermal gas masses (∼ 10&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;− 10&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; M⊙) have been derived using X-ray and CO observations as well as radio polarization studies. We note that although there may be other reasons contributing to the spatial anti-correlation observed between the polarized radio emission and [O iii] emission, such as lack of telescope sensitivity and beam depolarization effects, the broad consistency found between the values derived from our work and the values reported in the literature gives us confidence in our argument regarding the role of the emission line gas in depolarizing the lobe emission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One caveat in this study is that while we find a clear spatial anti-correlation between polarized radio emission and [O iii] emission in most regions, we also find regions showing a correlation between them. Nevertheless, the number of polarized knots that spatially anti-correlate with [O iii] emission (8/12) is more than the number of knots that correlate (4/12). In Figures 4 and 5, we have only annotated the polarized knots that show an anti-correlation (i.e., J1 and J2 in J0945+1737 and J3, CJ1 and CJ2 in J1430+1339). The correlation could be explained as a result of the clump sizes of the depolarizing media being larger than the telescope beam or there not being enough mixing between the emission line gas and the synchrotron lobe plasma. It is also important to note that deeper multi-frequency and multi-resolution observations are needed to distinguish between internal and external depolarization effects more rigorously. Therefore, the current work using ∼ 2 GHz bandwidth data has limited implications. Yet, this study is promising in that it provides a first-order treatment of the depolarization mechanisms at play in the poorly studied class of RQ AGN and provides lower limits on the derived parameters, such as the cloud sizes and the mixed gas masses. We emphasize that the system is much more complex than the models used here, and more rigorous methods must be used instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this work, we have presented the results from our joint radio polarization and emission line study of 5 type-2 radio-quiet quasars. We find that the radio emission in J0945+1737, J1000+1242, J1010+1413 and J1430+1339 is likely to be jet-based depending on their morphological, spectral and polarization properties. However, the origin of radio emission (among jet or wind) in J1356+1026 cannot be ascertained with the current data. Polarization is detected in 4 out of 5 sources (J1010+1413 is unpolarized) as discrete knots with ordered magnetic fields. From previous studies, our sources are known to show a spatial coincidence between radio emission and [O iii] emission. Our study suggests that the polarized knots more often do not spatially coincide with [O iii] emission, similar to that seen in some of the radio-loud AGN in the literature. This suggests that the radio emission is likely to be depolarized by the emission line gas clouds surrounding the radio lobes, or by the emission line gas that has entrained inside the radio lobes and mixed with the synchrotron lobe plasma. For the case of J0945+1737, the size of the emission line gas clouds is found to be of the order of 10−5 pc, and the amount of the mixed thermal gas in its lobe is found to be of the order of 106 M⊙. An important insight from this study is the signature of the jet/wind-gas interaction, suggested by the spatial anti-correlation observed between the polarized radio emission and the emission line gas. This in turn could be interpreted as tentative evidence for AGN feedback. Our work also demonstrates that the interplay of jets, winds and emission line gas might have a significant impact on the nature of the radio outflows in radio-quiet AGN. In addition, all sources in our sample show evidence for ongoing galactic mergers, such as the presence of double optical nuclei, or morphological distortions in the host galaxy. We, therefore, note that the merger scenario may also influence the overall interpretation of AGN feedback in these sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stac1044&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Quasar Feedback Survey: revealing the interplay of jets, winds, and emission-line gas in type 2 quasars with radio polarization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Silpa Sasikumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt;   P Kharb, C M Harrison, A Girdhar, D Mukherjee, V Mainieri, M E Jarvis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; National Centre for Radio Astrophysics (NCRA) - Tata Institute of Fundamental Research (TIFR), Pune, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/five_agn_polarization_silpa</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/five_agn_polarization_silpa</guid>
        
        <category>AGNs</category>
        
        <category>Blackhole</category>
        
        <category>Galaxies</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chandrayaan-3 : A 14 day lunar cruise</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;India’s ambitious space program reaches new heights as Chandrayaan-3, the eagerly anticipated lunar exploration mission, prepares for launch. Get ready to witness history in the making as India embarks again on an extraordinary journey towards the Moon, marking a remarkable milestone for the nation and igniting a wave of excitement across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Chandrayaan-3&lt;/b&gt; is the planned 3rd lunar exploration mission by the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO), with the aim of demonstrating the end-to-end capability in safe landing and roving on the lunar surface along with the development and demonstration of new technologies intended towards inter-planetary missions. The developed system for the mission consists of an indigenous Lander module (Vikram), a Rover (Pragyan) and a Propulsion module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/chandrayaan_3_cysil/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: A schematic illustration of the Integrated Module. &lt;em&gt;Credits:&lt;/em&gt; ISRO
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launcher identified for Chandrayaan-3 is LVM3-M4 (Launch Mark 3 - Mission 4), which will place the integrated module in an Elliptic Parking Orbit (EPO). The pri- mary function of the Propulsion module is to transport the Lander from the launch vehicle injection till its entry into the lunar polar orbit at an altitude of 100 kms from the lunar surface, after which the Lander separates from the Propulsion module and begins its descent. The Lander is equipped with the capability to perform a soft land at a specified lunar site (69.367621 S, 32.348126 E) and deploy the Rover which will then carry out in-situ chemical analysis of the lunar surface during the course of its planned lifetime of 14 Earth days (1 Lunar Day). The Propulsion Module also has one scientific payload as a secondary function which will be operated post separation of Lander module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/chandrayaan_3_cysil/image2a.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/chandrayaan_3_cysil/image2b.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: A schematic illustration of the Chandrayaan-3 Lander (Top) and Rover (Bottom). &lt;em&gt;Credits:&lt;/em&gt; ISRO
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mission objectives of Chandrayaan-3 are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To demonstrate Safe and Soft Landing on Lunar Surface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To demonstrate Rover roving on the moon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To conduct in-situ scientific experiments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Propulsion module, the Lander and the Rover hosts a total of 7 scientific payloads
in order to carry out experiments on the lunar surface and atmosphere. They are listed
below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Radio Anatomy of Moon Bound Hypersensitive ionosphere and Atmosphere
(RAMBHA)&lt;/b&gt; - [Lander] - This experiment makes use of a Langmuir Probe in order to measure the near surface plasma density and its changes with time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Chandra’s Surface Thermo physical Experiment (ChaSTE)&lt;/b&gt; - [Lander] - To measure the thermal conductivity and temperature of the lunar surface.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Instrument for Lunar Seismic Activity (ILSA)&lt;/b&gt; - [Lander] - An experiment to measure the seismicity of the lunar surface and delineating the structure of the lunar crust and mantle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Laser Retroreflector Array (LRA)&lt;/b&gt; - [Lander] - A passive experiment to understand the dynamics of Moon system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Alpha Particle X-Ray Spectrometer (APXS)&lt;/b&gt; - [Rover] - To determine the elemental composition of the surface in the immediate vicinity of the landing site.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Laser Induced Breakdown Spectroscope (LIBS)&lt;/b&gt; - [Rover] - To infer the mineralogical composition of the lunar surface through elemental analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Spectro-polarimetry of HAbitable Planet Earth (SHAPE)&lt;/b&gt; - [Propulsion module] - To observe the Earth in reflected light in an attempt to decipher future discoveries of Exo-planets which would qualify for habitability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the predecessors to the Chandrayaan-3, Chandrayaan-2 boasted a ‘significant technological leap’ compared to the Chandrayaan-1. The Vikram Lander onboard the Chandrayaan-2 accomplished its intended descent trajectory, smoothly transitioning from an orbit of 35 km to a position slightly below 2 km above the lunar surface. During this phase, all systems and sensors of the Lander operated flawlessly, demonstrating the successful utilization of groundbreaking technologies, such as the innovative variable thrust propulsion system. Unfortunately, communication with the Lander was lost during the final descent phase. Subsequent investigations confirmed that the lander experienced a hard landing on the lunar surface, resulting in the loss of the lander itself. Chandrayaan-3 aims to address the challenges of its predecessors and enhance the current understanding of the Moon. On successful landing at the specified site, India will immortalise herself as the fourth country to land its spacecraft on the surface of the Moon and the first country to land near the South Pole of the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The launch of Chandrayaan-3 has been scheduled for &lt;b&gt;July 14, 2023, at 2:35 pm IST&lt;/b&gt; from the &lt;b&gt;Satish Dhawan Space Centre, Sriharikota&lt;/b&gt;. The spacecraft is expected to reach the moon by the 23rd − 24th August.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live telecast of the launch can be viewed on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/live/q2ueCg9bvvQ?feature=share&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; official ISRO YouTube channel.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/chandrayaan_3_cysil</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/chandrayaan_3_cysil</guid>
        
        <category>International</category>
        
        <category>India</category>
        
        <category>ISRO</category>
        
        <category>Chandrayaan</category>
        
        <category>moon</category>
        
        <category>lunar exploration</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
