<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> Welcome to CosmicVarta.</title>
    <description> Platform for promoting Indian astronomy research to the public.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 19:14:50 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 19:14:50 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>India’s expanding Cosmology community</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;‘Frontiers in Cosmology’ was a five-day international conference held at Raman Research Institute (RRI) during February 20 – 24, 2023. More than 100 participants including researchers, scientists, students and faculties from around the world attended the meet.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/proceedings_rri_cosmology_anjali/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Speakers at the &apos;Frontiers in Cosmology&apos; conference. &lt;em&gt;Credits:&lt;/em&gt; ESO/ M. Kornmesser, RRI Newsletter PJC Special Issue - I
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;India&lt;/b&gt; has seen a slow but steady growth in the number of researchers pursuing Astronomy and Astrophysics, particularly in cosmology and instrumentation, during the past three decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such recent effort to unite the leading cosmologists was at the &lt;b&gt;‘Frontiers in Cosmology’&lt;/b&gt;, a five-day international conference held at the Raman Research Institute (RRI), Bengaluru, during February 20 – 24, 2023. The conference was one among the many celebrations to mark the platinum jubilee year of RRI, founded by Nobel laureate Sir CV Raman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Frontiers in Cosmology&lt;/b&gt; saw a participation from over 100 subject experts including researchers, scientists, students and faculties and turned out to be a global platform to discuss, deliberate and share the latest from the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference offered five broad themes - Inflation and Cosmic Microwave Background (CMB), Cosmic Dawn and Epoch of Reionisation, Low Redshift Cosmology, the Evolving Universe and the Next Generation Experiments. Young researchers used this platform to showcase the findings of their research, the best 25 posters were on display here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference hosted varied talks on CMB, characterization of galactic foregrounds, instrumentation, future astronomical facilities like the Simons Observatory, a ground-based CMB experiment located at Cerrro Toco in Chile, the Thirty Metre Telescope (TMT), the Square Kilometre Array (SKA), PRATUSH, some of which has active participation of RRI. Engaging and enlightening the audience about the telescope facilities like the South Pole Telescope (SPT) and the BICEP Array telescopes – both located in Antarctica – SARAS, CHIME, the young students got a flavour of the facilities, both existing and upcoming. The event saw serious deliberations revolving the ever-growing challenges faced by the astronomy community in getting land free from light pollution and human interferences. Experts stressed on the need for building improved instrumentation facilities and technological support besides designing facilities on larger and collaborative basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the speakers, Akito Kusaka, who spoke on ‘CMB – challenges and future prospects’, elaborated on the perfect conditions for installing the CMB detectors in the world. Further, his address highlighted the leakage of observations into polarization as one of the biggest hurdles in measuring CMB. The theories and scientific contributions of late Shivaramakrishnan Pancharatnam, (a noted student of Sir Raman), continue to be relevant even today, acknowledged Kusaka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving elaborate details, contributions and challenges of operating, Maclean Rouble, in her talk titled ‘S&amp;amp;T of SPT : Past, Present and Future’, underlined the need for having sensitive detectors in order to improve the CMB mapping efforts. She touched upon the likely possibilities of telescopes post the operations of SPT, including the mm-line intensity mapping and the idea of developing kinetic inductance detectors. Another operational telescope in the Southern polar region is the BICEP Array telescopes, which are small aperture telescopes deployed to measure CMB with highest precision. Ritoban Basu Thakur in his talk informed about the heightened capacities of the upgraded BICEP Array telescope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NenuFAR and the CoDEX Program initiated by the European Research Council were discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Josh Dillon’s address on ‘Recent progress in 21cm Cosmology with the hydrogen epoch of reionization array’ detailed on the necessity for co-designing compact instruments with greater sensitivity for effective measurements. Nichole Barry elaborated on the difficulties in taking observations and working at the Murchison Widefield Array, especially for the epoch of reionization science in her address titled ‘The dangers of Whitefield Observations for the EoR 21cm measurements’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing the SARAS experiment setup ‘Constraining high redshift astrophysics with SARAS’, by Saurabh Singh enlisted the multiple challenges, especially the bright foregrounds, and the shrinking radio-quiet zones in India for conducting continued observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introducing capabilities of CHIME, HIRAX and CHORD facilities, Shiv Sethi’s talk ‘Detecting HI in the post-reionizaiton’ suggested two potentially strong methods – stacking and cross-correction – that can produce good observations within the redshift 0.3 – 1.4 range. Hamsa Padmanabhan’s talk ‘A multi-messenger view of the baryonic Universe out to the Epoch Reionization’ underlined the requirement for strengthening the cross-co-relations for improving the 21cm HI intensity mapping in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/proceedings_rri_cosmology_anjali/image2.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Bringing together brilliant minds. Group photo of the conference attendees. &lt;em&gt;Credits:&lt;/em&gt; Ritik Shah
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when the country is sealing its position in Astronomy, senior scientists used this stage to inform the young attendees about the many next generation astronomy facilities, where India has major stakes. Yashwant Gupta spoke about the upgraded Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope (uGMRT) and presented an insight into the world’s largest radio telescope, the Square Kilometre Array (SKA). Another mega-science project participated by India, the Thirty Metre Telescope (TMT) – the proposed largest optical telescope – was spoken during a session by GC Anupama. She narrated the the numerous hardships faced in erecting the telescope at the designated Mauna Kea in Hawaii and years of continued efforts to locate a search alternate site, all for science!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video recordings of the conference talks are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLOT8qUzmOGqovk12OtW3lBM7yEe759dyp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; RRI YouTube channel.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cover image credits: ESA - C. Carreau&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgements&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CosmicVarta would like to thank the organizers of the “Frontiers in Cosmology” conference and Raman Research Institute (RRI) for their support and cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/proceedings_rri_cosmology_anjali</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/proceedings_rri_cosmology_anjali</guid>
        
        <category>Proceedings</category>
        
        <category>International</category>
        
        <category>Conference</category>
        
        <category>Cosmology</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Proceedings of the  National Seminar on  Advances in Astrophysics and Space Science Research (NSAAASSR) 2023</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Department of Physics and Electronics at CHRIST (Deemed to be University) in Bangalore, Karnataka, organised the National Seminar on Advances in Astrophysics and Space Science Research (NSAASSR) from February 13 to 15, 2023. The seminar was organised as part of the IUCAA Centre for Astronomy Research and Development (ICARD), CHRIST (Deemed to be University). We report the proceedings from the seminar.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department of Physics and Electronics at CHRIST (Deemed to be University) in Bangalore, Karnataka, organised the National Seminar on Advances in Astrophysics and Space Science Research (NSAASSR) from February 13 to 15, 2023. The seminar was organised as part of the IUCAA Centre for Astronomy Research and Development (ICARD), CHRIST (Deemed to be University). The primary functions of the ICARDs are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To contribute to the development of innovative teaching methods designed for Astronomy. This includes the development of upto date course structures and new kinds of experiment/data analysis sessions which can be a part of a starting or existing Astronomy course in a University. To hold frequent workshops/schools/meetings at various levels at the host University/College and nearby regions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To have an active public outreach program for Astronomy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To be visiting Centre where nearby Astronomers can visit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IUCAA accredited the Department of Physics and Electronics as ICARD on October 1, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/proceedings_report_nsaassr_robin/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three-day seminar aimed to provide postgraduate and motivated undergraduate students with insights and knowledge on current developments in Astronomy and Astrophysics under the ICARD activities. There is a dearth of conferences and seminars specifically tailored to meet the needs of undergraduate and postgraduate students. In light of this, a seminar has been thoughtfully planned to give students a unique opportunity to showcase and present their research work on an exclusive platform. It provided attendees with a comprehensive and interactive learning experience, featuring talks by prominent scientists, student contributions, and hands-on data analysis sessions. The students’ contributory talks were based on projects completed or currently in progress during their UG/PG programmes. The seminar saw active participation from over 40 students from different Institutes and Universities who were selected based on the submitted abstracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;proceedings-for-day-one&quot;&gt;Proceedings for Day One&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Inaugural session of the seminar was presided over by Dr Fr Jose CC, honourable Pro-Vice Chancellor, CHRIST (Deemed to be University). The chief guest for the occasion was Dr Annapurni Subramaniam, Director &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics&lt;/a&gt;. They shared great insight into the need and multifold applications of the field of astronomy in day-to-day life. After a brief tea break,  Dr Annapurni gave a plenary talk on “Astronomy from the ground and space-based telescopes”. The talk narrated the transition of astronomy from using the position of stars to navigate the night sky to using telescopes to unveil star formation in far-off galaxies. Attendees learned about accessing data from various space missions and using it for scientific purposes. They were also introduced to the country’s present and future space telescopes facilities, such as AstroSat and INSIST. The talk also briefly outlined the research works of the team led by Dr Annapurni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Ajith Parmeswaran, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icts.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; ICTS, Bangalore&lt;/a&gt;, delivered the second plenary talk. The topic was “Gravitational wave astronomy: A new window to the Universe”. Dr Ajith participated virtually in the seminar. The talk focussed on how the observational confirmation of gravitational waves has enabled us to understand our Universe better. Participants were introduced to the precise instruments to detect and study these waves. The discussion also included information on CMB Bharat, a consortium for Indian cosmology, and LIGO India, allowing for a new perspective on comprehending the cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Seminar then had 12 talks by the participants in extragalactic and stellar astronomy. The audience received the talks well, leading to many fruitful discussions. The first day concluded with informal discussions with the participants and resource persons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;proceedings-for-day-two&quot;&gt;Proceedings for Day Two&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day began with a plenary talk by Dr Shyama Naredranath, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ursc.gov.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; URSC, Bangalore&lt;/a&gt;. The topic was “Exploration of the Moon: paradigm shifts”. The talk discussed various theories that explain the origin of the Moon. The talk also narrated how the abundance of different volatile elements like sodium and oxygen will enable us to understand the formation scenario of the Moon. Dr Shyama also talked about India’s significant contribution to understanding the Moon, namely Chandrayaan 1 and 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Manoj Puravankara, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tifr.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; TIFR, Mumbai,&lt;/a&gt; delivered the second plenary talk. The title of the talk was “Exploring the invisible Universe: the story of Infrared Astronomy”. Dr Manoj joined the seminar online. The talk discussed the importance of infrared astronomy and how the field has helped us unravel the Universe that lies shrouded in the visible spectrum, such as the interstellar shocks, protoplanetary disks, and reddening due to interstellar dust, among others. The talk also highlighted the new age space telescope, JWST, and how the telescope has helped us achieve great insights into the far ends of the Universe. Dr Manoj then discussed his team’s research using the JWST facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Dipanjan Mukherjee, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iucaa.in/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; IUCAA, Pune&lt;/a&gt;, delivered the third plenary talk on “Understanding how jets from Supermassive Black Holes affect galaxy evolution”.  The talk started with the galaxy colour-magnitude diagrams and the three distributions seen: the blue cloud, the red sequence and the green valley. Then, various quenching mechanisms prevalent in galaxies were discussed. The talk then highlighted how the jets emanating from black holes influence the evolution of the host galaxies. After the lunch break, the seminar had a series of five cosmology and space science talks by the student participants. Discussions with the panel and audience gave more significant insights into their research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hands-on session on astronomical tools such as SAO DS9 and Topcat was scheduled next. The session was taken by Mr Akhil Krishna and Mr Suman Bhattacharya, PhD Scholars, CHRIST (Deemed to be University). The participants enthusiastically learnt to utilise these tools to visualise and analyse data from worldwide astronomical facilities. The participants were then led on a campus tour. They were introduced to the various facilities available in the University, including the Research and Development block and the different instruments such as the X-ray diffractometers, Electron Microscopy, UV- Visible spectrometer, Fluorometer, Microwave Synthesizer, Solar Simulator, and SEM, among others which the students can make use of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last event for the day was a public talk by Dr Dipankar Bannerjee, Director, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/aries-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; ARIES, Nainital&lt;/a&gt;. The lecture title was “India’s first Space Solar Observatory: Aditya L1”. The talk focussed on coronal mass ejections and sunspots. Dr Dipankar also discussed the upcoming first solar space mission from India, Aditya L1, and the various instruments to study our closest star. The mission’s main objective is to understand the coronal heating and solar wind acceleration, initiation of the coronal mass ejection, flares and near-Earth space weather, the coupling and dynamics of the Solar Atmosphere, and the solar wind distribution and temperature anisotropy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;proceedings-for-day-three&quot;&gt;Proceedings for Day Three&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third day began with a plenary talk by Dr Smitha Subramanian, IIA, Bangalore, on “An introduction to extragalactic astronomy”. The talk started with the Great Debate: Shapley-Curtis debate. The participants were then introduced to Hubble’s tuning fork diagram and the various types of galaxies known to us. Dr Smitha then proceeded to explain the formation of galaxies. The talk also emphasised galactic evolution and the various triggering mechanisms involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Vaidehi S Paliya, IUCAA, Pune, delivered the second plenary talk on “An introduction to Gamma-ray Universe”. The talk discussed the most extreme and energetic emissions, namely, Gamma-ray bursts. Several gamma-ray production mechanisms and detection techniques were discussed. The talk highlighted how gamma-ray studies were key in understanding various physical phenomena such as AGNs, blazars etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final plenary talk was delivered by Dr Tapas Baug, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bose.res.in/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; SNBNCBS, Kolkata,&lt;/a&gt; on the topic “Galactic massive star formation: Large-scale to small-scale view”.  The talk discussed massive stars and the various mechanisms involved in their formation. The talk also raised our current limitations in understanding this large-scale phenomenon entirely due to the limitations of telescopes. Dr Tapas briefly discussed his work during the talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the presentations, the seminar included networking opportunities, allowing attendees to connect with other scientists and researchers from around India. A hands-on session was conducted by Dr Arun Roy, IIA and Mr Shridharan Baskaran, Research Scholar, CHRIST (Deemed to be University), on various tools available in Python for astronomy. The module Astropy was discussed in detail. Participants were encouraged to write their codes using the discussed modules simultaneously. Participants could visualise several astronomical images by the end of the hands-on session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following panel discussion focused on answering queries put forward by the participants. The panellists included Dr Maheshwar Gopinathan, IIA, Bangalore, Dr Savithri H Ezhikode, Post-doctoral fellow, CHRIST (Deemed to be University), Mr Gourav Banerjee, Research Scholar, CHRIST (Deemed to be University) and Mr Cysil Tom Baby, Project Intern, CHRIST (Deemed to be University). Queries including how to apply for PhD positions, how to apply for projects, and how to approach professors for projects and internship opportunities were discussed in the panel discussion. It was well received by the participants and resource persons alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seminar concluded with the valedictory ceremony, where the best presentations were awarded. The chief guest of the ceremony was Dr Maheshwar Gopinathan. The event coordinator, Dr Sreeja S Kartha, gave a brief seminar report. The seminar concluded with great satisfaction and happiness from the participants. The seminar was a great success, bringing together leading scientists, researchers and students to share their latest findings and exchange ideas. The seminar highlighted the importance of collaboration and innovation in advancing scientific knowledge and understanding the field of astronomy and space science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may find copies of the abstract books and the posters presented at the NSAASSR on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://indico.cern.ch/event/1245645/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; seminar website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/proceedings_report_nsaassr_robin</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/proceedings_report_nsaassr_robin</guid>
        
        <category>Proceedings</category>
        
        <category>seminar</category>
        
        <category>national level seminar</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why do some Active Galactic Nuclei Change their Look?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;An active galactic nucleus (AGN) is powered by the matter accreting onto the central supermassive black hole (SMBH) at the centre of a galaxy. Changing look (CL) AGNs are those sources that show rapid change in the column density of the X-ray absorber. CLAGNs show a complex shape in their X-ray spectra. The physical mechanisms responsible for these variations are unclear to date. In this article, we took an attempt to explain the CL phenomena on AGN and their possible origin. For that, we studied the spectral properties of NGC 1365 using joint XMM-Newton and NuSTAR observations. We used JeTCAF model to fit the X-ray spectra of the source. We found that the variable absorption column density correlates with the mass accretion rate and the geometry of the corona. The derived wind velocity was sufficiently low compared to the escape velocity to drive the wind away from the disk for the epochs during which column densities were high. This suggests that the high and variable absorption can be due to failed winds from the disk. Our study construed that the changing accretion rate, which is a fundamental physical quantity and the geometry of the corona are driving the CL phenomena in NGC 1365. The physical picture of this work connects both variable continuum and variable absorbing medium scenarios. Moreover, from the spectral fitting of the joint data, we found the mass of the central black hole to be constant 4.38 ± 0.34−4.51 ± 0.29 × 10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; M&lt;sub&gt;sun&lt;/sub&gt; , in accord with the optical observations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the visible stars that we see in the night sky, there is a hidden zoo of strange astronomical objects that are only visible as signals through high-tech telescopes in multiwavelengths from radio to gamma rays. Some are even Black Holes They are extremely dense, with such a strong gravitational attraction that not even light can escape their grasp. Therefore, black holes seem black! But the light which is coming from the accretion disk  makes them visible through different telescopes. Small black holes populate the universe, but their cousins, supermassive black holes, dominate. These enormous black holes are millions or maybe even billions of times as massive as the sun. Scientists aren’t certain how such large black holes spawn. Once these giants have formed, they gather mass from the dust and gas around them, material that is plentiful in the center of galaxies, allowing them to grow to even more enormous sizes. When such an active supermassive black hole is sitting at the center of a galaxy and illuminating the whole galaxy is called an active galactic nucleus or an AGN. They can launch energetic jets and winds and emit radiation in different wavelengths.  AGNs have an endless supply of fuel, allowing them to power the jets. The accretion of hot gas and dust from the host galaxy is one of the sources of such a seemingly unlimited fuel supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all AGNs appear similar to each other. They are classified depending on the presence or absence of jets, jet morphology, width of emission lines, luminosity, and the orientation in which these AGNs are viewed from the Earth. Depending on either the viewing angle or some intrinsic difference in structure, they can be classified into different spectral types. AGNs not only differ from one another but also change their flux and spectral type drastically in a timescale of hours to decades in both X-ray and optical/UV energy bands, which is why they are often called Changing Look AGNs. What makes them change their appearance has been the subject of much debate recently; however, two main processes are hypothesized to bring about this change: Changing Look due to obscuration and Changing Look due to change in state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often see stars twinkling on a moderately cloudy night. This twinkling behavior is observed due to the irregular movements of clouds in the atmosphere, which changes the amount of brightness seen in stars from time to time through time-dependent obscuration along the line of human sight. Changing obscuration AGNs also have a similar reason for changing their appearance. They show intense time-dependent variability of the line-of-sight intervening gas density/column density, primarily associated with clouds or outflows eclipsing the AGN. Change in the appearance of AGNs due to obscuration is observed mainly in the X-ray wavelength regime. Obscuration by neutral intervening gas can leave a clear imprint on the X-ray emission observed in AGN. At a high column density, obscuration becomes significant enough to suppress the primary continuum of X-rays and produce a secondary continuum through reflections within the gas. Such variations are typically observed in X-Rays as the region which makes these X-rays are small enough to be concealed by the neighboring gases.  Changes in gas densities that cause obscuration are driven by intrinsic AGN luminosity variations, which have an impact on the chemical state of the material. A higher AGN luminosity chemically modifies the obscuring material to become more transparent to X-rays and thereby allows a decrease in line-of-sight column density. Apart from neutral gas obscuration, absorbing gas usually associated with outflows can also strongly affect the X-ray spectrum and is routinely recorded by the detector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu/image1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu/image2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: (upper panel) &lt;em&gt;Credit:&lt;/em&gt; Robert Gendler and The Hubble Legacy Archive, KPNO/NOIRLab/NSF/AURA-Total view of NGC 1365, (lower panel) Cartoon diagram of the model (JeTCAF; jet in two component advective flow model) used to fit the X-ray data. &lt;em&gt;Credit:&lt;/em&gt; arXiv:2107.13808. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing look due to change in state in AGN may arise due to several processes. They are usually observed in the UV/Optical regime due to variability in the accretion phenomenon. In many cases, they can be separated from Changing Obscuration AGN, when a Change in the look of AGN happens in close succession to a change in some intrinsic property of black hole accretion. One such case is a failed wind scenario. Instabilities like thermal or magnetic instabilities can heat up the disk and cause variations in the disk surface temperature and density and thereby making chemical changes in the disk, which directly affects the X-ray radiation. Other events include tidal disruption events, where a star gets close to a black hole and gets torn apart by it. In the process, the debris of the dead star disrupts the gas in the accretion disk of the black hole, which in turn changes the accretion rate and significantly affects the disk along with the X-ray corona, which disappears after a point. Observations do see such effects in different wavebands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our study, we attempted to make a bridge between two main mechanisms, the intrinsic variability in the spectrum and the obscuration along the line of sight. For that purpose, we have analyzed a joint XMM-Newton and NuSTAR satellites’ data of the source NGC 1365 (shown in the left panel of Fig. 1). Here, we briefly explain the data analysis procedures and spectral fitting techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;data-analysis&quot;&gt;Data Analysis&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used joint &lt;em&gt;XMM-Newton&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;NuSTAR&lt;/em&gt; observations of NGC 1365 during 2012 and 2013.  To analyze the XMM-Newton data, we used the Science Analysis System (SAS) version 19.1.0 and followed the standard procedures given in the SAS data analysis threads. We first reprocessed the Observation Data Files (ODF) using the epproc routine to generate the calibrated and concatenated event lists. We filtered the concatenated event lists to remove the periods of high background activity. Furthermore, we extracted the source and background spectra using the evselect routine. We used a circular region with a radius of 32′′ for both the source and the background. We used rmfgen and arfgen tasks to generate the redistribution matrices (.rmf) and the ancillary (.arf) files. Finally, we rebinned the spectra using the task specgroup in order to have at least 25 counts in each bin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NuSTAR data were extracted using the standard NUSTARDAS version 1.3.12 software. We ran a nupipeline  task to produce cleaned event lists and nuproducts to generate the spectra. We used a region of 80′′ for the source and 100′′ for the background using ds9. The data were grouped by &lt;em&gt;grppha&lt;/em&gt; command, with a minimum of 30 counts in each bin. For the analysis of each epoch of observation, we used the data of both XMM-Newton and NuSTAR in the energy range of 0.5−75 keV. We used XSPEC version 12.11.0 for spectral analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;model-fitting&quot;&gt;Model Fitting&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each epoch of observation was fitted using an accretion-ejection-based JeTCAF model (see Right panel of Fig. 1). This model requires six parameters (if the mass is considered as a free parameter), which are (i) the mass of the BH, (ii) the disc accretion rate, (iii) the halo accretion rate, (iv) the size of the dynamic corona or the location of the shock, (v) the shock compression ratio, and (vi) the ratio of the solid angle subtended by the outflow to the inflow. We directly run this model in NASA’s XSPEC software using &lt;em&gt;initpackage&lt;/em&gt; command. Initially, we need to give some guess values of the parameters, then the fitting using the iterative method tries to find the best-fit values by minimizing the chi-square. Along with JeTCAF, we used the two-component absorption model (z)TBABS (Wilms et al. 2000) for both host galaxy and our Galaxy contributions, keeping the Galactic hydrogen column density (NH) fixed to 1.3 × 10&lt;sup&gt;22&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt; . We used chi-square statistics for the goodness of the fitting. A representative fit using JeTCAF is shown in Figure 2. The model-fitted parameters show that NH along the line of sight decreases with mass accretion rate. Using this dependence and considering that the central radiation is illuminating the disk, therefore, the outflow is launching, we have estimated the mass outflow velocity, which is less than the escape velocity of the outflows. This suggests that the winds or outflows that cannot go away from the gravitational well of the BH are blocking the central radiation and may cause the changing look phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: A representative best fit JeTCAF model spectrum of NGC 1365 in the 0.5-75 keV energy band. Different emission and absorption lines are clearly visible. A strong excess below 2 keV energy is also evidenced.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an additional test, we used photoionization simulation using CLOUDY to predict absorption and emission line spectra for the modeled intrinsic spectral energy distribution in JeTCAF. The gas properties used in CLOUDY are taken from JeTCAF model fitting. The simulated spectra for all epochs are shown in Figure 3. The red and blue lines correspond to the ionization parameter (ξ) = 100 and 1000 erg cms&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, respectively. The micro-turbulence of v&lt;sub&gt;turb&lt;/sub&gt;= 1000 km s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; is used in the simulations for all epochs. The CLOUDY simulations show that absorption features are stronger for the low mass accretion state, where N&lt;sub&gt;H&lt;/sub&gt; is high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: CLOUDY simulation of all epochs depicting the emission and absorption features. For the simulation, we used an ionization parameter of 100 (red) and 1000 (blue) erg cm s&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;, motivated by the observational results. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;our-key-findings-are-as-follows&quot;&gt;Our key findings are as follows:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The accretion rates and the geometry of the dynamic corona changed significantly during the observation period.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The maximum outflow rate estimated is ~12% of the inflow rate and confirmed the previous findings that the outflows are present in the system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The accretion-ejection model-fitted mass is placed within a range between 4.38 ± 0.34−4.51 ± 0.29 × 10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; M&lt;sub&gt;sun&lt;/sub&gt; and, remarkably, matches the optical observation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The outflow velocity is less than the escape velocity infers that the outflowing material could not go farther away from the gravitational potential of the black hole, which is called ‘failed wind’, that blocked the central radiation and caused the changing look phenomena.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, the study of a sample of Changing Look AGN using high-resolution spectroscopy can provide a clearer picture of how this phenomenon is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;acknowledgement&quot;&gt;Acknowledgement:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank Ms. M. Mukherjee for helping with the write-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022A%26A...662A..77M/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Variable mass accretion and failed wind explain changing look phenomena in active galactic nucleus NGC 1365&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Santanu Mondal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tek P. Adhikari, K. Hryniewicz, C. S. Stalin, A. Pandey&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Reference:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022arXiv221105132R/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Changing-look Active Galactic Nuclei&lt;/a&gt; for a review&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/active_galactic_nuclei_change_look_santanu</guid>
        
        <category>clagn</category>
        
        <category>blackholes</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Solar cycle 25 is going to be a bit stronger than cycle 24!</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Forecasting the strength of the solar cycle is of the utmost importance because it affects space weather and our technology-based society. By a riveting feature of the solar cycles, i.e. Waldmeier effect (WE2), we find a linear relationship between the solar cycle rise rate and cycle amplitude. Also, the previous cycle’s poloidal field (PF) rise rate is physically related to the next cycle’s rise rate and amplitude. Using this physical connection, we predicted the strength of Solar Cycle 25 to be 137+/-23, which extends the temporal range of the solar cycle prediction to much earlier than what previous studies were able to do. Also, this prediction is very close to what we got by direct application of the Waldmeier effect (WE2). Currently, solar cycle 25 is in progress, which is following our forecast quite well.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun is our nearest star, which generates an incredible amount of energy in different forms like light and heat, charged particles, magnetic fields, gamma, and X- rays. The Sun’s dynamic magnetic field is responsible for energetic events like solar flares and coronal mass ejections (CMEs). The sunspots (Fig. 1), regions of strong magnetic fields on the solar surface, are also the result of the Sun’s dynamic magnetic field. The number of sunspots varies periodically in about a 11-year cycle. This cycle is popularly known as the solar cycle or the sunspot cycle. The strength of the solar magnetic field is strongly coupled with the activity level of the solar cycle. These events concertedly create weather in space (“space weather”), which affects the interplanetary medium and planetary atmosphere. Sometimes this space weather has hazardous impacts on our technology-dependent society. In a strong solar cycle, many more such energetic events are observed and thus have huge effects on the space weather. Space weather interferes with the Earth’s atmosphere and disrupts radio communications, power grids, and satellites. Thus, space weather is currently a vital issue and a novel field of exploration. The scientific community is actively trying to understand space weather phenomena and its impact on us. Therefore, the prediction of the dynamic solar cycle strength is of the utmost importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us have seen the bulb turning on in the headlight of the bicycle at night. This bulb used to give more light when the paddles of the bicycle went fast and when the paddles stopped the bulb was extinguished, right? There was a small dynamo in the bicycle which used to produce current when the bicycle was moving. Inside the dynamo, a permanent magnet is rotated in the middle of some coils of wire. The rotating magnet produces a changing magnetic field and thus magnetic flux. By Faraday’s law, it gives an e.m.f. and generates current in the coils of wire. The top of the dynamo is touched against the rim of the bicycle which rotates when the bicycle is moving. Similarly, the solar dynamo is the action of different flows inside the sun and produces currents, and these currents give the dynamic magnetic field. The Sun has two types of magnetic fields, one is a toroidal field, and the other is a poloidal field (see Fig. 2). In 1955, Parker suggested that the sunspot cycle is produced by an oscillation between the poloidal and the toroidal magnetic fields, resulting in a 11-year periodic magnetic cycle. In this theory, the poloidal field gives a toroidal field and vice versa by the dynamo process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this magnetic cycle follows a specific property i.e. the Waldmeier effect (WE). In 1935, Waldmeier showed that the rise time of the solar cycles is inversely proportional to the cycle’s amplitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This effect is known as the Waldmeier effect (WE1). Also, a strong correlation was found between the rise rate and the amplitude of the cycle, and this is known as the Waldmeier effect (WE2). Further, the feature of the Waldmeier effect (WE2) enables us to establish a linear relationship between the rise rate of the cycle and the amplitude of the cycle. Motivated by this relationship, we analyzed the observational data of Sunspot number (SSN) and sunspot area (SSA) for the solar cycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/solar_cycle25_stronger_cyle24_pawan/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1. Sunspots ( black dots ) on the surface of the sun. (Image credit: NASA/SDO) 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the data from the past 13 solar cycles, we found a strong linear correlation between the rise rate and the strength of the solar cycles. Thus, we can predict the solar Cycle 25’s amplitude by applying the linear fit between these two parameters. Using this method, we predicted the solar Cycle 25’s peak amplitude to be 138 +/- 26, even though it started just two years ago. We also expect this cycle to attain its peak around mid-2024. For checking the robustness and reliability of this method, we also predicted the amplitudes of a few past cycles, which agree quite well with the corresponding observations, as shown in Fig. 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/solar_cycle25_stronger_cyle24_pawan/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2. Sketches of the poloidal and toroidal field of the sun
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/solar_cycle25_stronger_cyle24_pawan/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3. The plot shows the comparison of predicted amplitudes (using WE2) with observed solar cycle amplitudes. The blue curve shows the temporal variation of the observed sunspot number (SSN). Squares show the predicted amplitudes based on the WE2, and vertical lines their errors. The vertical dotted line and the horizontal arrow show the time of the predicted peak of Cycle 25 and the error in that time’s prediction respectively. Prediction of Cycle 25&apos;s amplitude using the rise rate of the previous cycle&apos;s poloidal field is shown by a &lt;i&gt;dark red-filled circle&lt;/i&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, the scientific community uses a highly robust physics-based method to predict the upcoming solar cycle strength at solar cycle minimum, called the polar precursor method. In this method, the amplitude of the poloidal field at the solar cycle minimum is taken as the seed to predict the amplitude of the next solar cycle. Motivated by this, we analyzed the poloidal field at cycle minima and the rise rate of the next cycle, and obtained a high linear correlation between them for both observational and model data. This strong correlation indicates that a strong poloidal field at cycle minima certainly makes the following cycle rise faster and it also becomes stronger complying with the Waldmeier effect (WE2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, since we found that the polar field at cycle minima is strongly correlated with the rise rate of the cycle, therefore going one step backward in their evolution, we find a fascinating feature. This feature reveals that the rise rate of the poloidal field after polarity reversal (north pole to south pole or vice versa) is strongly correlated to the rise rate and amplitude of the next cycle (see Fig. 4). Moreover, we also found a strong correlation between the poloidal field build-up rate and the peak poloidal field. These features can be explained with the help of the solar dynamo process. Thus, these results suggest a physical link between the poloidal field build-up rate and the rise rate of the next cycle. Therefore, WE2 enables us to predict the amplitude of the next cycle from the rise rate of the poloidal field calculated from the data a few years after the polarity reversal of the previous cycle. By applying a linear fit between the poloidal field rise rate and amplitude of the next cycle for the data of previous cycles, we predicted the peak of cycle 25 will be around 137 +/- 23 This value is very close to the value we got directly from WE2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our work shows a strong physical connection between the polar field build-up rate and the amplitude of the next solar cycle. Further, it also shows the crucial physical link between the polar field rise rate and the Waldmeier effect (WE2), since our prediction of the peak amplitude of the current solar cycle based on WE2 (138 +/- 26) is very close to that based on the polar field rise rate (137 +/- 23). Thus, using our novel method allows us to make a reliable prediction of the amplitude of a solar cycle as early as about 9 years before it actually reaches its peak !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/solar_cycle25_stronger_cyle24_pawan/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4. Scatter plots between the rise rate of the polar field with the rise rate of the next cycle and cycle amplitude. (a) and (b) are obtained from observational data (black and red colors are for the northern and southern hemispheres of the sun respectively), while (c) and (d) are for the dynamo model. ‘r’ denotes the extent of correlation between the values on the y-axis and values on the x-axis. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, solar Cycle 25 activity was in the news, and it has been observed that its activity has quickly ramped up. Even though the sun has not yet reached its peak activity level, it has already exceeded many predictions. Until now, the sun is following the same pattern we predicted based on the polar field rise rate. Thus, our technique will further increase the temporal range of prediction of the solar cycle strength and will also help to understand the dynamo process more physically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnrasl/slac043&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Physical link of the polar field buildup with the Waldmeier effect broadens the scope of early solar cycle prediction: Cycle 25 is likely to be slightly stronger than Cycle 24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Pawan Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Akash Biswas, Bidya Binay Karak&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Technology (Banaras Hindu University), Varanasi 221005, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/solar_cycle25_stronger_cyle24_pawan</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/solar_cycle25_stronger_cyle24_pawan</guid>
        
        <category>Solar cycle</category>
        
        <category>Sunspot</category>
        
        <category>Space weather</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nuclear Pasta in the crust of neutron star</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The article discusses the structure of the neutron star crust. In the neutron star’s crust, exotic structures commonly known as “nuclear pasta” are believed to exist. The pasta structure impacts various structural, thermal and transport properties of the crust and therefore needs to be investigated. Using a simple nuclear model, the present article estimates the content of pasta structures in the crust and its implication on the neutron star properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/nuclear_pasta_vishal/figure1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pictorial representation of the Crab Pulsar (PSR B0531+21) in the centre of the Crab Nebula (a remnant of the supernova SN 1054), which was discovered in 1968. Pulsars are rapidly spinning neutron stars with very strong magnetic fields which funnel jets of particles out along the two magnetic poles. The image combines optical data from Hubble (in red) and X-ray images from Chandra (in blue). Adopted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.nasa.gov/spinning-pulsar-crab-nebula&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1934, a few years after the discovery of the neutron,  astronomers Baade and Zwicky, in their pioneering work, coined the term “supernova” and hypothesised the existence of neutron stars. It took another 30 years for astronomers to discover the first neutron star in 1968. The discovery of the neutron star unfolded a new era of science with nuclear astrophysics as its main focus. A neutron star is formed from the collapsed core of a massive star that has undergone a supernova explosion. The massive stars, during their lifetime, ignite their core elements up to the Iron (Fe), after which fusion stops as it is the most stable element in the periodic table. This results in the gravitational collapse of the star due to the unavailability of the fuel to counter gravity, giving rise to the supernova explosion. During the supernova, the outer layers of the star are blown away while the core collapses in on itself, causing the protons and electrons in the core to combine and form neutrons. This creates a dense, compact object consisting almost entirely of neutrons compressed into a radius of only about 10 km.  The density of a typical neutron star material is 10&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt; times that of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, the origin, structure and dynamics of neutron stars have played a central role in multi-messenger and gravitational-wave astronomy. It has provided us with the opportunity to understand the behaviour of fundamental forces, especially strong and weak nuclear forces, in extreme environmental situations. In the last few decades, enormous efforts have been applied to understand the structure of the neutron star, which is limited by our understating of nuclear many-body force. However, with the available variety of data from various astrophysical observations, we can now better constrain the neutron star observables such as mass, radius, tidal deformity (how deformable neutron star is) etc., and the behaviour of the equation of state (EoS) over a wide density range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;structure-of-neutron-star&quot;&gt;Structure of Neutron Star&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/nuclear_pasta_vishal/figure2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: Schematic diagram of a neutron star with its interior and surface. &lt;em&gt;Adopted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nphys2663&quot;&gt;( Nature Physics  9, 396–397 (2013))&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structure of a typical neutron star can be divided into three distinct parts below its thin atmosphere:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Outer crust:-&lt;/strong&gt; The ground state of the outer crust of a neutron star  can be described by  a body-centred cubic (BCC) lattice of atomic nuclei embedded in the sea of electrons, making it globally charge neutral. With increasing star depth, more and more neutron-rich nuclei appear until the onset of the inner crust, where neutrons start dripping (i.e. nuclei are unbounded with respect to the neutron emission). The BCC structure is preferred due to its smallest lattice energy as compared to the face-centred cubic (FCC) and simple cubic (SC) lattices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/nuclear_pasta_vishal/figure3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Inner Crust:-&lt;/strong&gt; The inner crust is marked by the assembly of the clusters formed by neutrons and protons along with the unbound dripped neutrons making the neutron gas. The dripped neutrons stay confined in the unit cell due to the large gravitational pressure. Such a system is so extreme that it is not possible to mimic it in any laboratory on earth. The system is made neutral by the electron gas, which is distributed uniformly over the cluster and neutron gas. At high densities, i.e., near the crust-core transition density, the system becomes “frustrated” as a result of competition between the nuclear and Coulomb interactions. The frustration leads to the system arranging itself into various exotic geometries (spheres/gnocchi, rods/spaghetti, slabs/lasagna, cylindrical voids/anti-spaghetti and spherical voids/anti-gnocchi) commonly known as “nuclear pasta.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Core:-&lt;/strong&gt; As the density increases, the size of the cluster in the inner crust increases, and at a density called transition density, the inhomogeneities disappear, and we enter the liquid core of the star. The core is further divided into the outer and inner cores. While the outer core consists of an admixture of neutrons and protons along with the leptons ensuring charge neutrality and β–equilibrium (the chemical potential of neutron equals the chemical potential of proton and electron), the exact composition of the inner core is not yet fully understood. Various estimations in the form of Quark plasma, Kaon condensate, etc., have been formulated for the inner core in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the core of the neutron star predominantly determines the global properties of a neutron star, it is hidden behind a thin shell in the form of the crust. Therefore, to accurately determine the core structure and dynamics, it is crucial to understand the physics of the crust. It is not only relevant in the context of neutron star physics but acts as a highly sophisticated  laboratory to test nuclear theories and models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of various structural aspects of the crust, the presence of pasta in the denser region of the inner crust has long been debated. Although there exists no direct and robust observational evidence of nuclear pasta, various tantalising observations indicate its existence. These observations include the information of magnetic field decay of neutron stars, corresponding spin evolution, quasi-periodic oscillations (QPOs) in soft gamma repeaters (SGRs) (astronomical object which emits large bursts of gamma-rays and X-rays at irregular intervals), quasi-periodic oscillations in giant flares etc. The amount of these pasta structures in the inner crust plays a pivotal role in the explanation of various neutron star properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results-and-discussions&quot;&gt;Results and Discussions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To investigate the possible presence of the pasta structures in the inner crust of a neutron star, we use the &lt;em&gt;Compressible Liquid Drop Model(CLDM)&lt;/em&gt; in association with the &lt;em&gt;Effective Relativistic Mean Field(E-RMF)&lt;/em&gt; theory. CLDM is a modified version of the conventional liquid drop model, which is one of the oldest, most groundbreaking and simplistic formalisms to explain the binding energy of an atomic nucleus. It takes the motivation from molecular physics, where the behaviour of a classical liquid drop is found to be analogous with the behaviour of an atomic nucleus. This is due to the fact that the forces binding both a liquid drop (Van-der Waals force)  and a nucleus (residual strong force) are qualitatively similar. Therefore assuming the nucleus to be incompressible, the energy of a nucleus can be simply written in the form of its volume, surface and Coulomb energy. The CLDM modifies it for the case of neutron star crust and  takes into account the compressibility of nuclear matter, negative lattice Coulomb energy, and the suppression of surface tension by the surrounding neutron gas. Using the Wigner-Seitz(WS) approximation, the energy of the system in the inner crust of a neutron star can simply be written as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/nuclear_pasta_vishal/figure4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above equation, the surface, curvature and the coulomb energy correspond to the finite size correction to the bulk energy, i.e. the volume energy in case of liquid drop model. The bulk energy of nuclear matter and energy of the neutron gas is extracted from E-RMF formalism which is a state-of-the-art framework based on quantum chromodynamics (QCD), which is the fundamental theory of strong nuclear interaction. The QCD itself cannot be applied to explain the nuclear matter at low-density, which is one of its unresolved limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parameter sets of E-RMF theory are designed to satisfy various ground state properties of atomic nuclei, such as binding energy, charge, radius, as well as constraints derived from astrophysical and laboratory observations  of mass and radius of  neutron stars, and flow data from &lt;em&gt;Heavy-Ion Collisions(HIC)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our calculations, we use thirteen E-RMF sets, which satisfy the recent observational constraints on the maximum mass and radius of the neutron star. These sets differ in the bulk nuclear matter properties such as symmetry energy (characterises the variation of the binding energy as the neutron to proton ratio of a nuclear system is varied), incompressibility, the binding energy of infinite nuclear matter etc. These properties characterise a particular parameter set, and a large amount of research is undergoing to put stringent constraints on them. However, there are still uncertainties on their exact values, and therefore, the nuclear matter properties become model dependent. In this study, utilising various parameter sets gives us the flexibility to investigate these model dependencies on the existence of pasta structure in the inner crust of the neutron star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the experience from molecular dynamics simulation, we consider five shapes of pasta structures, namely: spheres, rods, slabs, tubes and bubbles. At a given baryon density, energy minimization leads to the identification of the most favourable pasta structure. We see that the spheres occupy the shallower region of the inner crust and are subsequently accompanied by rods, slabs, tubes and bubbles. The number of unique pasta structures occurring in the inner crust of the neutron star depends essentially on the equation of state or the nuclear model considered. Out of various bulk matter properties, the symmetry energy governs the pasta content in the crust. An equation of state with larger symmetry energy in the subsaturation density  regions (⍴&amp;lt; 0.1 fm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;) estimate a thicker crust with more unique pasta layers. The transition (transition from heterogeneous crust to the homogenous core) pressure and density also depend on the symmetry energy. These parameters are crucial inputs to calculate the crust profile of the neutron star. Accurate knowledge of these parameters, in association with the determination of symmetry energy from various Heavy Ion Collision  experiments, can give us the opportunity to understand nuclear interaction in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical thickness of the inner crust of a neutron star is approximately 1 km. We see that pasta layers constitute almost 50% of the crust mass and account for 20% of its thickness. These results are important as the pasta structure impacts various phenomena in the neutron star crust, such as its cooling, rotation, Quasiperiodic Oscillations (QPOs) etc. QPOs (related to the vibrations of the neutron star crust) provide us with much-needed information on the neutron star crust structure.  In our calculations, we found that the pasta structure significantly impacts the fundamental frequency mode of these oscillations. In addition, they also alter the shear response of the crust. The pasta structure does not affect the global properties of the neutron star, yet it profoundly impacts the microphysics of the crust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of the present work need to be confirmed by future measurements of neutron star observables. Moreover, modern theoretical Bayesian analysis methods also serve as an aid in determining these results, and our results are in agreement with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevD.106.023031&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Pasta properties of the neutron star within effective relativistic mean-field model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Vishal Parmar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; H. C. Das, Ankit Kumar, Ankit Kumar, M. K. Sharma, P. Arumugam, and S. K. Patra&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Thapar Institute of Engineering and Technology, Patiala 147004, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/nuclear_pasta_vishal</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/nuclear_pasta_vishal</guid>
        
        <category>Neutron star crust</category>
        
        <category>Pasta Structure</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Imploding Cometary Clouds: An Astronomer&apos;s Perspective</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The interstellar molecular clouds are the high-density regions between the stars having elements in the molecular phase. These clouds usually come up with different structures based on the influence of nearby massive ionizing stars. Also, these stars can either hinder or trigger the star formation in the molecular clouds. The ambient magnetic field towards these clouds also found to regulate the star formation and structural evolution. In our work we study the magnetic field structure (projected on the plane -of-sky) of a molecular cloud shaped as a comet in the Orion region of the sky. We found the evidence that the magnetic field is dragged away by the pressure of the nearby massive ionizing source and shaping the curvy structure of the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region in between the stars is called the interstellar medium which is mainly composed of clouds of gas and dust. In interstellar clouds, starlight cannot pass through the highly dense area, which is why hydrogen can preserve its molecular state (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;). Also, other chemical elements, for example, carbon monoxide (CO), ammonia (NH&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;), water (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O), etc. exist in the form of molecules. Therefore, high-density interstellar clouds are called molecular clouds. Typically, the molecular clouds have an average density of 100-300 molecules cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;. These molecular clouds are considered to be the potential sites of birth of young stellar objects (YSOs), through collapse under the influence of gravitational force, which tends to drive the cloud material inward towards the center of gravity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massive OB stars (Mass &amp;gt;= 8M&lt;sub&gt;sun&lt;/sub&gt;, with spectral types O and B) are considered to affect their surrounding molecular clouds significantly. The energetic photons emitted from these massive stars promptly ionize the immediate vicinities, resulting in a shock which eventually results in non-uniform cloud structures, such as Bright-Rimmed Clouds (BRCs), Cometary Globules (CGs), the Elephant’s Trunk Nebula, etc (examples are shown in Figure 1) based on their appearances. BRCs consist of a compact, dusty edge similar to a narrow, bright-rimmed head along with a faint elongated tail-like structure extending from the head, which is towards the side of the nearby massive OB stars. Many of the BRCs display more collimated structure, looking like a comet, which are named as CGs. Also, we can see elongated structures resembling an elephant’s head and trunk, which are designated as Elephant’s Trunk Nebula. Despite their structures, these clouds are invariably aligned with their long axes almost parallel to the direction of the ionizing sources, for example, nearby OB stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/imploding_cometary_clouds_piyali/figure1.png&quot; alt=&quot;figure1&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/imploding_cometary_clouds_piyali/figure2.png&quot; alt=&quot;figure2&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/imploding_cometary_clouds_piyali/figure3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;figure3&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: (Left) Bright-rimmed cloud named SFO 18, &lt;em&gt;Credit: Jim Thommes&lt;/em&gt;, (Middle) Cometary globule named CG 12, &lt;em&gt;Credit: Sebastian Volmer&lt;/em&gt;, (Right) Elephant’s Trunck nebula named IC 1396A, &lt;em&gt;Credit: Spitzer space telescope&lt;/em&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shocks taking place in these cloud structures can trigger the star formation, by possibly compressing the inner dense cores and eventually tend to gravitational collapse. The evolution of these elongated molecular clouds and the star formation in them are found to be regulated by the orientation and strength of the ambient magnetic fields. An initially perpendicular magnetic field of weak and medium strengths is dragged and made to orient following the cloud structure during the dynamical evolution of the globule by the photoionizing radiation from the nearby ionizing source (see Figure 2). However, a strong perpendicular field remains in its initial alignment. Therefore, an investigation of the magnetic field geometry surrounding the molecular clouds is important to study the structures and the dynamics of the globules. Polarimetry (a tool to measure the polarization of the electromagnetic wave, e.g., starlight) is a great tool that is widely used to investigate the magnetic field structure projected on the plane-of-sky (B&lt;sub&gt;POS&lt;/sub&gt;) around the molecular clouds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/imploding_cometary_clouds_piyali/figure4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 2: Illustration of a photoevaporating magnetized molecular cloud. The purple lines are the magnetic field lines (with an orientation of ∼80&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt; to the direction of ionizing photons). The molecular cloud is shown in green. The ionized gas is also presented in red. &lt;em&gt;Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2009MNRAS.398..157H/abstract&quot;&gt;Henney et al. (2009)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-source-studied-in-this-work&quot;&gt;The source studied in this work&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We focused on a CG named L1616, that resides at an angular distance of about 8&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt; west of the Orion OB1 associations, which is a group of massive OB stars at the Orion constellation. It shows evidence of ongoing star formation activity. An older population towards the north–eastern edge of the cloud (directed towards the Ori OB1 association) and a younger population towards the head region has been noticed, which means a trend of small-scale sequential star formation is present towards L1616. In Figure 3, we show the locations of L1616 and the nearby massive OB stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/imploding_cometary_clouds_piyali/figure5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 3: Positions of the bright Orion stars near L1616 plotted over the Planck 10&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt; × 12&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt; 857 GHz image. Area of our study of L1616 is indicated by a red colored box of size 1.5&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt; × 1.5&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt;. The x and y axes show the right ascension (RA) and declination (Dec) of this region, respectively, which are used to mark the position of any object in the equitorial coordinate system. Details can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://astronomy.swin.edu.au/cosmos/e/equatorial+coordinate+system&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Image credit:&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/513/2/2039/6580586&quot;&gt; Saha et al. (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/imploding_cometary_clouds_piyali/figure6.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 4: The optical polarization vectors (yellow lines) plotted over the color-composite image using the Wide-field Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE) 3.5 (blue), 4.6 (green), and 12 (red) micron images of 1.5&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt; × 1.5&lt;sup&gt;◦&lt;/sup&gt; size. The reference vector with 2% polarization is also shown. The x and y axes show the right ascension (RA) and declination (Dec) of this region, respectively. &lt;em&gt;Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/513/2/2039/6580586&quot;&gt; Saha et al. (2022)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results-and-discussion&quot;&gt;Results and Discussion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to study the B&lt;sub&gt;POS&lt;/sub&gt; towards L1616, we carried out optical polarimetric observations of this cloud using ARIES IMaging POLarimeter (AIMPOL) attached with 104 cm Sampurnanand Telescope, located at Aryabhatta Research Institute of observational sciencES (ARIES), India &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/jeewan/Reprints/RautelaBS_2004_BASI_32_159.pdf&quot;&gt;(see this link for details)&lt;/a&gt;. In Figure 4, we show our optical polarimetric results. The orientation of the yellow polarization vectors indicates the angle of B&lt;sub&gt;POS&lt;/sub&gt; from the celestial north (the point about which all the stars in the northern hemisphere are seen to revolve). A curvature in the B&lt;sub&gt;POS&lt;/sub&gt; can be noticed in the head region of L1616. Also, the polarization vectors are found to show the trend of being twisted along the curvy tail. Overall, the B&lt;sub&gt;POS&lt;/sub&gt; is found to be more chaotic in the head region, which might be a result of the disintegration of cloud material by the energy input from the associated young stars. The presence of the massive OB stars can also impact the B&lt;sub&gt;POS&lt;/sub&gt;. From our results we conclude that possibly the ambient B&lt;sub&gt;POS&lt;/sub&gt; had an initial alignment perpendicular to the major axis of L1616. This alignment might be dragged away from the source of ionization following the structure of the globule, resulting in the twist of B&lt;sub&gt;POS&lt;/sub&gt; in the head area of the globule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also made an attempt to investigate the pressure and the extent of the impact of the massive stars on L1616. The pressure exerted by epsilon Ori (the most massive star among the others in the Orion OB1 association) is estimated to be the highest, therefore epsilon Ori seems to be the main source to influence L1616. Also, the proper motion (motion of the objects projected on the sky plane) of the associated YSOs with respect to epsilon Ori shows evidence that most of them are moving away from the direction of epsilon Ori (main ionizing source). Based on the assumption that the motion of the YSOs follow the motion of the parental cloud, we can say that the cloud L1616 is currently being pushed away by the impact of epsilon Ori.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work has been published in the Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;acknowledgments&quot;&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors sincerely thank the reviewer, Dr. Davide Gandolfi, for his constructive remarks which significantly improved the manuscript. The authors acknowledge all the supporting staff at ARIES, Nainital, who made the polarimetric observations possible. The authors also thank the CosmicVarta team for showing interest in this work and invitation to write about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/513/2/2039/6580586&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Magnetic fields and young stellar objects in cometary cloud L1616&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Piyali Saha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Archana Soam, Tapas Baug, Maheswar Gopinathan, Soumen Mondal and Tuhin Ghosh&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Satyendra Nath Bose National Centre for Basic Sciences (SNBNCBS), Salt Lake, Kolkata 700 106, India (former)
National Astronomical Observatory of Japan (NAOJ), Mitaka, Tokyo 181 8588, Japan (current)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/imploding_cometary_clouds_piyali</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/imploding_cometary_clouds_piyali</guid>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Can missing physics in gravitational waveforms mimic false violations of general relativity?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;General theory of relativity proposed by Albert Einstein in 1915 has passed all the experimental and observational tests with flying colors. Gravitational waves from the merger of compact binaries such as black holes and neutron stars provide a unique opportunity to test general relativity in the strong-field regime of gravity. Missing physics in the modeling of gravitational waves can appear as a false violation of general relativity.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gravitational_waveforms_pankaj/image_cover.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: The SXS simulation of colliding black holes distorting spacetime around them. &lt;i&gt; Image Credit: The SXS project.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General theory of relativity predicts that if two black holes are orbiting around each other, the orbit of the binary will shrink due to the emission of gravitational waves. As black holes come closer and closer, their orbital speed increases. The black holes move close to the speed of light in their final orbits, dragging spacetime around them. Finally, two black holes collide and merge, releasing an enormous amount of energy in the form of gravitational waves and leaving behind a more massive spinning black hole. The emitted gravitational waves from these mergers carry information about the nature of gravity in these extreme regions of spacetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1974, Hulse and Taylor discovered a pulsar orbiting around a neutron star. According to general relativity, the binary system must be losing energy due to the emission of gravitational waves. By observing the orbital period of the binary, they found that the orbit of the binary was shrinking and the rate of shrinking was in excellent agreement with the predictions of general relativity. This observation proved the existence of gravitational waves and tested general relativity in strong gravitational fields where the theory had never been tested before. This discovery of gravitational waves earned the Nobel Prize in physics in 1993.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 14, 2015, gravitational waves from the merger of two black holes were detected by Laser Interferometer Gravitational-wave Observatory (LIGO), nearly 100 years after Einstein’s discovery of general relativity. This first direct observation of gravitational waves opened a new window to the unexplored dark universe. The observation won the Nobel Prize in 2017. Till now, nearly 90 gravitational wave signals from merging black holes have been detected. Each new gravitational wave observation helps physicists test general relativity. No evidence of physics beyond general relativity has been found in any of these observations. However, it is possible that beyond general relativity effects are minuscule and not visible in current-generation gravitational wave detectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General relativity is currently our best understanding of gravity. However, there are unsolved problems in cosmology such as the nature of dark matter and dark energy, that cannot be explained by general relativity alone. Many &lt;em&gt;modified theories of gravity&lt;/em&gt; have been proposed as an alternative to general relativity to address these unsolved problems. The ideal way to test the true theory of gravity would be to match the observed gravitational wave signals against the predictions of various theories of gravity and see which theory is best supported by the data. However, waveform modeling in modified theories of gravity is still in the infant stage. Hence we use our best understanding of general relativity and look for deviations away from general relativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the numerous tests of general relativity, &lt;em&gt;parametrized tests&lt;/em&gt; are one of the unique ways to test general relativity. In parametrized tests, the gravitational wave signal in general relativity is modified by adding extra phenomenological deviation parameters that attempt to capture a particular class of deviation from general relativity. The value of these deviation parameters is zero in general relativity. Precise measurement of deviation parameters reveals the nature of the gravitational wave signal. If the gravitational wave signal is consistent with general relativity, the values of these deviations should be consistent with zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The accuracy of these tests relies on the accuracy of gravitational waveforms which describe the dynamics of binary. The task of developing waveform models is a complex one that involves making approximations, assumptions, and the possibility of modeling errors due to missing physics. This means that our waveform models are not able to perfectly capture the behavior of gravitational waves. The inherent imperfections in waveform models can introduce systematic bias into estimated parameters such as black hole’s masses, spins, and deviation parameters. These systematic biases on deviation parameters if become greater than the statistical uncertainty, may appear as a false violation of general relativity. The interpretation of the measured signal may show a contradiction from general relativity leading us to believe that there is something wrong with the theory, but we have to be very careful before making such extraordinary claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent study, conducted in collaboration with Prof. Marc Favata (Montclair state university, USA) and Prof. K.  G. Arun (Chennai Mathematical Institute, India), we focused on the systematic bias due to neglect of orbital eccentricity in the waveform model and demonstrated how eccentricity-induced systematic bias can mimic a false violation of general relativity. As two black holes in an elliptic orbit revolve around each other, due to the emission of gravitational waves, the orbit of the binary tends to become circular. Gravitational wave detectors are presently capable of detecting the gravitational waves from the last few orbits of the binary before its merger. Therefore, it is expected that the binary’s orbit has likely already been circularized by the time it is detected. LIGO and Virgo currently use quasi-circular waveforms for testing general relativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ellipticity of a binary’s orbit depends on its formation history. Black hole binaries formed in the galactic fields are expected to be in quasi-circular orbits due to various mass transfer episodes between the binary’s constituent. However, for black holes that are formed inside dense star clusters, it is possible to remain in highly eccentric orbits due to dynamical interactions and exchanges with other stellar objects in the cluster. The orbit of these binaries may not be fully circularized due to the emission of gravitational waves, but still possess small amount of eccentricity when the detector observes the binary. For eccentric binaries, the neglect of eccentricity in waveform models may cause the deviation parameters to be biased and exhibit inconsistency with general relativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gravitational_waveforms_pankaj/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    (a) LIGO
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gravitational_waveforms_pankaj/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    (b) Cosmic Explorer
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 2: Systematic and statistical errors on the leading order deviation parameter as a function of orbital eccentricity e0. Systematic errors are represented by solid lines and statistical errors are denoted by dashed lines. These errors are shown for four representative binaries with different total masses. The orbital eccentricity e0 on the x-axis is defined at a gravitational wave frequency of 10 Hz.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a black hole binary with total mass 15M&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt; (solar mass) and orbital eccentricity 0.04 is observed by LIGO, the eccentricity-induced systematic bias on the leading-order deviation parameter becomes comparable to the statistical errors as illustrated in the adjacent figure (taken from Saini et al. (2022)). These biases will shift the deformation parameters away from their true value, which is zero in general relativity, indicating a false deviation from general relativity. This value of eccentricity is even lower (0.005) for the more sensitive future third-generation gravitational wave detector (Cosmic Explorer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very likely that in the near future, we detect gravitational waves from the mergers of black holes in eccentric orbits. There are already signatures of a few eccentric mergers in the detected gravitational wave signals. To avoid the risk of falsely claiming a breakdown of general relativity, controlling waveform systematics is of immediate need for the gravitational wave community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[Saini et al.(2022) Saini, Favata, and Arun] P. Saini, M. Favata, and K. G. Arun, Phys. Rev. D 106, 084031 (2022), arXiv:2203.04634[gr-qc].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/link_gateway/2022PhRvD.106h4031S/arxiv:2203.04634&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Testing general relativity using gravitational waves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Pankaj Saini&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Marc Favata, K. G. Arun&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Chennai Mathematical Institute, Chennai, 603103; India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/gravitational_waveforms_pankaj</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/gravitational_waveforms_pankaj</guid>
        
        <category>Testing general relativity using gravitational waves</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Using a pseudo-Kerr formalism to study accretion and wind flows around rotating black holes</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Hydrodynamic flows around black holes is a fascinating area of research that provides a window into the processes that power relativistic jets and energetic particle acceleration. However, this is a challenging task when studied using the full general relativistic framework. In our work, we find an exact pseudo-potential formalism that can be used to study hydrodynamics around rotating black holes very accurately. This formalism can be a useful tool in numerical simulation studies and to extract spin parameter of black hole candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accretion is one of the most fundamental physical processes in the universe that describes the inflow of matter towards a central gravitating object or the centre of mass of an extended system and is responsible for the formation and evolution of structures in the universe. However, the most spectacular observational manifestation of accretion occurs when the central objects are the most compact in the cosmos – black holes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of black holes (BHs) is a remarkable prediction of Einstein’s theory of General Relativity (GR). According to GR, gravity is a geometric phenomenon that arises from the curvature of space-time instead of being an invisible force that attracts objects towards each other. The more massive an object, the more it curves space-time. BHs are regions in space bounded by a surface called the event horizon from which nothing, not even light, can escape. In this sense, they are perfect space-time traps, and the event horizon marks the boundary of no return. This means that a BH itself is invisible. However, astronomers can still observe them indirectly through the way it affects the motion of nearby stars and pulls matter into orbit around them. As matter accretes around a BH, it heats up. It releases vast amounts of energy in the form of radiation. In this way, the accretion of matter onto BHs powers some of the most luminous sources in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to GR, a BH is characterized by just three observable properties – mass M, angular momentum J and electric charge Q. In any realistic setting, however, a BH is unlikely to have any electric charge because it will typically be rapidly neutralized by the plasma surrounding it. Therefore, astrophysically relevant BHs can be fully described by only their mass and angular momentum. It is helpful to define the dimensionless spin parameter of a BH as a=J/M, i.e., the angular momentum per unit mass of the BH, that can take any values within the range 0&amp;lt;|a|&amp;lt;1. The BH is non-rotating when a=0 and a=1 correspond to the maximum value of the angular momentum a BH can attain. To determine the mass of a BH, astronomers can observe how groups of stars and gas move around the BH, which is a relatively easy task. However, the spin is rather subtle because it requires probing the strong gravity region close to the BH, where relativistic effects are prominent. So, the measurement of BH spin requires a model that can accurately describe the relativistic effects close to the event horizon of the BH. In general, most of the astrophysical BHs are expected to be rotating. They are defined by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kerr_metric&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kerr metric&lt;/a&gt;, which is an exact solution of the Einstein field equations of GR. The geometry of the space-time described by the Kerr metric is shown in Figure 1, where all the important surfaces are marked. The outer event horizon is essentially the surface from which nothing can return. The shaded region called the ergoregion is another essential region where everything is forced to rotate with the BH and has exciting observational consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/pseudo_Kerr_formalism_rotating_bh_abhrajit/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
 Figure 1: The geometry of the space-time described by the Kerr metric (Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/0706.0622.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Matt Visser&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To study accretion flows around a BH, one must solve the relativistic hydrodynamics equations. Since this task is very challenging when studied using GR, it is often useful to use the pseudo-potential approach. The advantage of the pseudo-potential approach is that one can use the equations of Newtonian hydrodynamics but with the Newtonian potential replaced by a pseudo-potential that mimics the relativistic effects around BHs. One can use this approach to easily study complex processes around BHs as if the central object is a Newtonian object. This approach is also helpful in easily handling radiative transfer problems in time-dependent numerical simulations just by replacing a few lines in numerical codes written for a Newtonian object. However, the pseudo-potential must be accurate enough so that the errors crept in for not using GR equations are within the observational errors. For non-rotating BHs, a pseudo-potential was introduced by &lt;a href=&quot;https://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/pdf/1980A%26A....88...23P&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Paczynski &amp;amp; Wiita&lt;/a&gt; (1980, hereafter PW80) that captures the relativistic features of the non-rotating BHs quite accurately and has been extensively used to investigate the physical properties of accretion flows around non-rotating BHs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1674-4527/ac4889&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recent publication&lt;/a&gt; derives the exact form of the effective potential for hydrodynamic flows around a rotating BH from the Kerr metric. We assume that the accretion flow is confined near the equatorial plane of the BH, and we find that this potential accurately reproduces the relativistic features of particle orbits for the entire range of the spin parameter. One can treat this effective potential as a pseudo-potential used in a Newtonian set of equations to describe accretion flows around rotating BHs. We call this the pseudo-Kerr formalism because this uses a Newtonian approach to study hydrodynamics around rotating (Kerr) BHs which are relativistic objects. So, knowledge of Newtonian hydrodynamics is sufficient. One needn’t have to bother about GR when applying this potential to study accretion flows around BHs. This is because all the relativistic effects are already incorporated into the potential. Moreover, a Taylor series expansion of our potential reveals that the leading order term is the PW80 potential. So our potential includes all the higher-order corrections to the PW80 potential for non-rotating BHs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use the pseudo-potential in a Newtonian approach to study accretion and wind flows around rotating BHs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/pseudo_Kerr_formalism_rotating_bh_abhrajit/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: The variation of (a) shock location, (b) shock strength and (c) compression ratio with the specific energy of the flow for a=0.5 and different values of angular momentum l=2.8, 2.9, 3.0. The stable (and unstable) shock locations are shown by solid (and dashed) curves. The left (and right) segments of each set of curves for a particular value of angular momentum corresponds to accretion (and winds). The GR curves are shown in red color. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/pseudo_Kerr_formalism_rotating_bh_abhrajit/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: An example of shock solution in (a) accretion (a=0.5, l=3.0, E=1.003) and (b) wind (a=0.5, l=3.0, E=1.007) . The dashed vertical arrows indicate the stable shock transitions and the GR solutions are shown in red color. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wind flows are outflowing matter from the region close to a BH and is an opposite process to accretion. For simplicity, we assume that the flow has no dissipation, i.e., the fluid is chosen to be inviscid (having zero viscosity). This means that the specific angular momentum of the flow remains constant. We then solve the equations of Newtonian hydrodynamics and show that the accretion process is necessarily transonic in nature. Transonic flows in this context mean that the radial velocity of the matter is subsonic (velocity less than sound speed) far away from the BH, and it gradually increases to become supersonic (velocity greater than sound speed) and finally enters the event horizon of the BH with the speed of light. Transonic flows are essential because they provide evidence for the formation of shock waves which are abrupt and strong discontinuities in the properties (pressure, temperature and density) of the accreting matter usually associated with violent phenomena in BH environments. Shock waves play a critical role in the dynamics of accretion flows. They can have important effects on the structure and evolution of accretion flows. In studies of transonic flows, it is useful to define a quantity called Mach number M=v/a&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt;, which is the ratio of the velocity of matter v and the speed of sound a&lt;sub&gt;s&lt;/sub&gt;. Then,  M&amp;lt;1 for subsonic flow and M&amp;gt;1 for supersonic flow. Two crucial parameters useful in studying shock waves are the shock strength S=M&lt;sub&gt;-&lt;/sub&gt;/M&lt;sub&gt;+&lt;/sub&gt; and the shock compression ratio R=ρ&lt;sub&gt;+&lt;/sub&gt;/ρ&lt;sub&gt;-&lt;/sub&gt;, where M is the Mach number, and ρ is the flow density. Both the quantities are calculated at the location of the shock, and the +/- signs correspond to quantities just after/before the shock. These quantities measure the discontinuities in the Mach number (or velocity) and density of the accreting matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We investigate the shock solutions in accretion and winds in detail. Comparing our results with the GR solutions reveals that our approach reproduces the GR values accurately. In Figure 2, we show the variation of the shock location, shock strength and shock compression ratio as a function of the specific energy for different values of the angular momentum of the flow for both accretion and wind. One can observe that the values are very close to the GR values (the red curves). In Figure 3, we show an example of a shock solution (the variation of the Mach number with the radial coordinate) for both accretion and wind and compare it with the GR solution (the red curves). The shock location in both cases is shown with dashed vertical arrows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find that our approach reproduces the GR results with high accuracy, and the errors, if any, are all within observational limits. This is true even when one chooses a highly spinning BH with a~1. This formalism can be a useful tool to study various aspects of accretion processes around BHs and to carry out numerical simulations that could provide new insights into problems that are usually tedious when studied using the GR approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1674-4527/ac4889&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Transonic Accretion and Winds Around Pseudo-Kerr Black Holes And Comparison with General Relativistic Solutions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Abhrajit Bhattacharjee&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Sandip K. Chakrabarti, Dipak Debnath&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Centre for Space Physics, Kolkata , India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/pseudo_Kerr_formalism_rotating_bh_abhrajit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/pseudo_Kerr_formalism_rotating_bh_abhrajit</guid>
        
        <category>Black Hole Physics</category>
        
        <category>Accretion</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Exploring the topology of hydrogen distribution in the early universe</title>
        <description>&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We study how galaxies and other sources in the early universe change the neutral universe or InterGalactic Medium (IGM) into the ionized one. We compare different kinds of source models and how they ionize the neutral universe which mainly consists of neutral hydrogen. We trace the largest ionized region formed by these sources by using a statistic known as the Largest Cluster Statistics (LCS). We found that LCS of different source models evolve differently and hence show different natures of ionizing photons or sources. We also investigate the geometry and topology of these ionized regions and how they are different for each model.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The universe on a very large scale seems like a web which we astronomers refer to as the cosmic web. Entities like galaxies and clusters of galaxies are trapped within this giant web (see figure 1). The unknown but the most abundant matter, dark matter, plays a governing role in shaping these giants by capitalizing the full potential of the most dominant force on a cosmic scale, gravitational force. We put our efforts to understand the formation and evolution of the universe including these giants by looking at the driving physics behind these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
 Figure 1: Image of the cosmic web. Figure shows the dark matter distribution (taken from the Millennium simulation). Here, every bright point represents a galaxy cluster. Image Credit: V.Springel, Max-Planck-Institut für Astrophysics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The universe has undergone a significant transition on a regular basis since its birth. Figure 2 shows the evolution of our universe from the Big Bang on the left hand side to the current local universe which we see today  on the right hand side of the plot. One of the major recent and remarkable phase transitions is the Epoch of Reionization (EoR), when the neutral Intergalactic Medium (IGM), mainly composed of neutral hydrogen, gets transformed into an ionized one. The galaxies residing within the dark matter halos (host of galaxies) act as one of the primary sources responsible for the reionization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Pictorial representation of the evolution of our Universe according to the standard cosmological model. Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://astrobites.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;astrobites&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to understand this era, we use several techniques and approaches to recreate the environment. We use analytic models (refer to  &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1209.2215&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;  Wyithe and Loeb 2012&lt;/a&gt;), semi-analytic models (refer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1512.00562&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;  Mutch et al 2016&lt;/a&gt;), semi-numerical models (refer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stv2812&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;  Majumdar et al. 2016&lt;/a&gt; ), etc., to understand the EoR and to comply with what we observe from large surveys conducted using advanced telescopes that are increasingly more sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is evident that different sources during EoR emit different kinds of ionizing photons, and hence, ionize the IGM in a different way. In our analysis, we investigate this era by focusing on the properties of some of these possible sources which can ionize the IGM. We consider six reionization source models based on the semi-numerical method originally proposed in &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stv2812&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;  Majumdar et al. 2016&lt;/a&gt;. These source models differ from each other in two main aspects: a) how the number of ionizing photons emitted by the sources are related to their host halo mass i.e. Nphotons ∝ (Mhalo)n and b) how the rest frame energy of the ionizing photons is distributed. The different source models considered in our work are mentioned in the table below. The Uniform Ionizing Background (UIB) dominated source model emits hard X-ray photons having large mean free path and hence creates a uniform ionizing background. The Soft X-Ray (SXR) dominated source model emits soft X-ray photons having limited mean free path. Source models like Fiducial (assumes 100% contribution of UV rays coming out from the galaxies residing inside the dark-matter halos) and Power Law (PL) (n=3) differ from each other in terms of the number of ionizing photons they emit following the relation shown in point (a) above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Reionization models&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Ultraviolet photons (UV)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Uniform Ionizing Background (UIB)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Soft X-Ray photons (SXR)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Power Law (PL), (n)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Fiducial&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;100 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Clumping&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;100 % and Non Uniform Recombination&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;UIB Dominated&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;80%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;SXR Dominated&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;80%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;UV + SXR + UIB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;50%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;PL (n=3)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reionization scenario like clumping model shows an extreme reionization case considering the clumpiness of the density field and emits ultraviolet (UV) photons. On the other hand, UV + SXR + UIB source model shows a combined contribution of UV photons, hard X-ray photons and soft X-ray photons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We investigate how the ionized regions formed by these sources evolve with redshift and what geometrical or topological information we can grab from their evolution by looking at their shape and size. One can use Minkowski functionals (a set of four functionals which gives information about the geometrical and topological distribution of matter in the universe) (for example,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/sty714&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bag et al. 2018&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/astro-ph/9312028&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mecke et al. 1994&lt;/a&gt;) to define the morphology of an object. In our work, we specifically use this to define the shape and size of our object (ionized region in our case). We use an algorithm called SURFGEN2 which identifies ionized regions from the density field and informs about their shape and size in the form of three Shapefinders (namely, thickness, breadth and length).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at these ionized regions, with time, different reionization source models forming these ionized regions grow in size as well as in numbers, which then start to overlap. At some point in time, they coalesce together and form a single large connected ionized region as one can notice from the middle and right panels in the figure 3. This transition phase is known as the percolation transition (one can look at the articles &lt;a href=&quot;https://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/pdf/1993ApJ...413...48K&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Klypin and Shandarin 1993&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/pdf/1996ApJ...465....2Y&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Capp Yess and Shandarin 1996&lt;/a&gt;).  In our analysis, out of many ionized regions, we primarily focus on the largest ionized region and its evolution around the percolation. We use the Largest Cluster Statistics (LCS) which is defined as the ratio of the volume of the largest ionized region to that volume of all ionized regions in a simulation volume to trace the largest ionized region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;

LCS = Volume of Largest Ionized Region / Volume of all ionized region 

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before percolation we have a very small largest ionized region but as we reach percolation and after percolation, the ionized region increases drastically, and at the end of reionization, almost the entire simulation box is filled with the largest ionized region as evident from the figure 3 as we go from left to right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Figure shows the transition of the largest ionized region from smaller size before percolation to the size of the entire simulation box after percolation. Middle panel shows the onset of percolation. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the reionization progresses, the neutral hydrogen present in the IGM ionizes and eventually the entire IGM converts into an ionized one at the end of the reionization. The neutral fraction (x&lt;sub&gt;HI&lt;/sub&gt;) informs about the amount of neutral hydrogen present in a volume with respect to the entire hydrogen species including both neutral and ionized one at any time. In our analysis, we use this quantity to see the evolution of LCS and shapefinders which we discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;evolution-of-largest-cluster-statistics&quot;&gt;Evolution of Largest Cluster Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest ionized region evolves differently for different reionization source models. The point of percolation is also different for different models. The inside-out scenarios where the reionization starts from the denser part of the IGM and then proceeds to the less dense part, the percolation occurs at much higher neutral fraction as compared to its counterpart, the outside-in scenario, where reionization starts from less dense regions and then the high-dense region is covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 4 shows the variation of Largest Cluster Statistics (LCS) with the neutral fraction and Filling Factor (FF) for different reionization models. Here, Filling Factor is defined as the ratio of volume of all ionized regions to volume of our simulation box. One can notice from the left panel that the largest ionized region or LCS before percolation (shown by vertical lines) is significantly small for all reionization models but at the onset of percolation and after percolation, an abrupt increment in LCS can be observed. This result is quite obvious because as the reionization progresses, different ionized regions grow and interconnect with each other and hence form a single interconnected ionized region which is true for all reionization models as one can notice from the figure. Hence, before percolation, when we have a very small largest ionized region, it is indistinguishable from other ionized regions but as we reach percolation, they interconnect and become quite distinguishable. It depicts how the neutral IGM slowly transformed into an ionized one when the ionized bubbles got enough time to develop. However, percolation for different models occurs at different neutral fractions. The inside-out reionization models percolate at higher neutral fraction (shown by solid lines) whereas the outside-in reionization models percolate at lower neutral fraction. At the end of reionization, we can observe a single large ionized region occupying the entire simulation volume as is evident from the right panel of figure 4, where LCS is close to unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: The percolation transition has been compared for all six reionization models in terms of LCS. The left panel shows the LCS as a function of neutral fraction (x&lt;sub&gt;HI&lt;/sub&gt;) whereas the right panel illustrates how LCS evolves with FF for the different reionization scenarios. In both panels, the vertical lines represent the percolation transitions in the reionization models with corresponding colors. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, we can say that following the LCS along with the percolation, we can distinguish between the two broad categories of reionization models i.e, inside-out and outside-in reionization models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;shape-of-largest-ionized-region&quot;&gt;Shape of Largest Ionized Region&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ionized bubbles formed by different sources, in principle, can be of complicated shape or geometry as they grow. For ease of understanding, one can use a simple geometrical or topological approach for the same. The Shapefinder technique uses Minkowski functionals to unveil the shape and size of the ionized region. The four Minkowski functions for a closed 2-D surface are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Volume enclosed, V:&lt;/strong&gt; Informs about the enclosed volume within the surface of an object or ionized region.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surface area, S:&lt;/strong&gt;  Informs about the surface area of the object.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrated Mean Curvature (C):&lt;/strong&gt; Informs about the concavity or convexity of the surface or in other words principal curvature (or radius of curvature) of the surface.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaussian Mean Curvature (Euler Characteristics):&lt;/strong&gt; Informs about the topological properties of an object.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shapefinders are expressed as the ratio of these Minkowski functionals to assess the shape of an object. In 3-D, the three shapefinders are :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thickness: T&lt;/strong&gt;  = 3V/S&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breadth: B&lt;/strong&gt; = S/C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Length: L&lt;/strong&gt; = C/4π&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These three are the good measures of the extension of an object in 3-dimension. We can further use these shapefinders to determine the morphology of an object by means of these two dimensionless quantities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planarity: P&lt;/strong&gt; = (B-T) / (B+T)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filamentarity: F&lt;/strong&gt; = (L-B) / (L+B)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We employ these aforementioned techniques to see how the geometry or topology of the largest ionized region evolves with the redshift. An ionized region can be expressed in terms of its length, breadth and thickness, which are the three Shapefinders mentioned earlier. We show the variation of cross-section and length with the neutral fraction in figure 5. We can observe that the cross-section of the largest ionized region for all reionization scenarios in the left panel remains almost constant with the variation in neutral fraction. Whereas, in the right panel, its length increases several orders of magnitude as the reionization progresses. Hence, one can robustly confirm the fact that as the reionization progresses, the topology of the largest ionized region becomes filamentary, as one can notice in figure 6 where the filamentarity (shown by thick line curves) has a larger value than the planarity (thin line curves) for all reionization scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 5: This figure illustrates the evolution of the shape of the largest ionized region (LIR) for the five reionization scenarios (excluding the clumping model since this is the only scenario where extreme reionization is considered and hence it’s shapefinders behave differently) near the respective percolation transitions. The left and right panels show the variation of cross-section (estimated by T x B) and the length (L) of the LIR on the y-axis against the neutral fractions on the x-axis. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh/image6.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 6: Planarity and filamentarity of the largest ionized region in different models have been compared near the respective percolation transitions. The solid and dashed curves represent the reionization models following inside-out and outside-in reionizations respectively. The thick line curves (solid and dashed) represent the filamentarity and thin line curves represent the planarity of the largest ionized region in different models.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also observe that as the reionization progresses, the largest ionized regions in all the scenarios become more multi-connected as their genus (in simple words, for any surface, it represents the number of holes present in the surface and hence informs about the multi-connected regions) increases. Thus, from our findings, we can conclude that at the later stage of reionization, we observe multi-connected filamentary structures for all reionization models. We found that the reionization model, like the clumping model, which follows extreme reionization, can be distinguished or separated quite easily by the Shapefinder technique. We crudely estimate the uncertainties by dividing each original simulation volume into eight smaller sub-volumes followed by estimating the variance of various quantities from these sub-volumes. Our research group at IIT Indore is currently working on noise which we get from the observations and the impact of primary beams on LCS analysis of the 21-cm signal considering the upcoming low-frequency Square Kilometer Array (SKA1-low) observations using a realistic simulations for such observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We consider the evolution of the largest ionized region by using a statistic called LCS in order to distinguish between the different reionization models.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We found that LCS for all reionization models before percolation is quite small and hence indistinguishable, but it increases abruptly at the onset of percolation. However, different reionization models percolate at different neutral fractions. Hence, following the evolution of LCS along with the percolation can help to distinguish between different models, and especially the inside-out or out-side- in models.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We also find that the cross-section of the largest ionized region in all the scenarios (except for the clumping model) remains stable at the percolation transition when the largest ionized region abruptly grows, mostly in terms of its third Shapefinder – ‘length.’ The genus of the largest ionized region also increases as reionization progresses. Hence, multi-connected filamentary structure is observed at a later stage of EoR.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr color=&quot;black&quot; /&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1088/1475-7516/2022/11/027&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Distinguishing reionization models using the largest cluster statistics of the 21-cm maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Aadarsh Pathak&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Satadru Bag, Saswata Dasgupta, Suman Majumdar, Rajesh Mondal, Prakash Sarkar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Department of Astronomy, Astrophysics &amp;amp; Space Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Indore, Indore, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/hydrogen_distribution_early_universe_aadarsh</guid>
        
        <category>Cosmology</category>
        
        <category>Epoch of Reionization</category>
        
        <category>Largest Cluster Statistics</category>
        
        <category>Percolation</category>
        
        
        <category>Cosmology and Nongalactic Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Astrophysical autopsy of a cosmic demise</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As the saying goes, “न कंचित् शाश्वतम्” (lit. Nothing is permanent), and hence the nature of this universe. The ever-evolving twinkles in the starry night are also non-discriminate towards this concept. If a star is born, it ought to die. Supernovae  are cosmic fireworks that do not require any occasion (e.g., New Year or winning a football world cup!) to explode. This explosion is the terminal stage of stellar evolution. Therefore, we can say that supernova is the death of a star that sends a siren to the universe in the form of gravitational waves to radio emissions (one of the best candidates for multi-messenger astronomy).  We study one such demise in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    Figure 1: OpenAI’s DALL.E 2 rendering of a core-collapse supernova [Generated by author]
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supernovae (SNe) have fascinated humankind since time immemorial with recorded events millennia ago. Many essential elements that are part of us also resulted from such explosions. It is imperative to understand these events in detail and try to ascertain their origins. SNe can be broadly classified as Type I and Type II on the basis of the absence and presence of hydrogen features in their spectra, which is unrelated to their explosion mechanisms (thermonuclear SN and Fe core-collapse SN). Apart from their use as independent distance indicators (Type Ia, Type II-P), they are part of various multi/interdisciplinary studies, viz. galactic chemical evolution, origins of various heavier elements, etc. The key question in supernova studies is ascertaining the progenitor, for which, at times, archival images are available through &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.stsci.edu/missions-and-data/hst&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hubble Space Telescope&lt;/a&gt;, but this is quite rare. There are other analytical solutions based on simplified physics related to the explosion and derived relations to estimate the explosion energy, pre-SN mass, ejecta mass, initial mass of progenitor star that exploded as SN, etc. crudely. But a more sophisticated way is to generate synthetic time evolution of flux ( light curves), and velocity evolution of ejecta, then try to match them with observations. Currently, 3D modeling is challenging and resource-hungry, and we rely on 1D hydrodynamical modeling using tools viz. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.mesastar.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Modules for Experiments in Stellar Astrophysics (MESA)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ascl.net/1108.013&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stella&lt;/a&gt;, and other open-source frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such explosion, SN 2020jfo, happened in the galaxy M61 [Figure 2], a stellar graveyard that has also hosted 8 SNe in the past century. In contrast, our Galaxy is due for even one for centuries! We carried out the observations extensively in the optical regime from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/?q=telescope_iao&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Himalayan Chandra Telescope&lt;/a&gt; situated at the Indian Astronomical Observatory, Hanle, UT of Ladakh. More than 25 epochs of multi-band photometry and spectroscopy covered the evolution of SN 2020jfo for about a year [Figure 3]. The observations were supplemented with data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aries.res.in/facilities/astronomical-telescopes/360cm-telescope&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Devasthal Optical Telescope&lt;/a&gt;, Nainital (Uttarakhand), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ztf.caltech.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Zwicky Transient Facility (ZTF)&lt;/a&gt; survey, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://swift.gsfc.nasa.gov/about_swift/uvot_desc.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Swift/UVOT&lt;/a&gt; data. SN 2020jfo, although a Type II-P (plateau) SN, did not fit in the classical definition of a plateau which is a constant luminosity phase in light curve evolution and typically lasts for about a hundred days. A deviation from the plateau was seen after 65 days putting it under one of the rare short plateau Type II SN. The SN explosion synthesizes many radioactive elements, primarily Nickel-56, that solely power its light curve in the late phase, estimated to be 0.033(6) solar mass. As the SN ejecta expands with time, we see the constituent inner layers of the progenitor as evident in spectral time evolution [Figure 3].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   Figure 2: The location of SN 2020jfo in the host galaxy M61 is shown. Orange boxes marked are the available SDSS spectra for the host. [Credits: &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac610b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Teja et al. 2022&lt;/a&gt;] 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plethora of information about ejecta, elements, and the ejecta velocity evolution could be obtained using spectra. Overall evolution is typical of Type II spectra, but we find ionized helium and rare stable nickel. Having these peculiarities, it warranted detailed studies and modeling to look for the origins of this supernova. With all the observational evidence, viz. compact progenitor, presence of stable nickel produced during stellar nucleosynthesis, and strength of nebular oxygen lines pointed towards a small mass progenitor, the present theoretical and modeling works hinted otherwise. Hence to ascertain this progenitor scenario, we employed hydrodynamical modeling of this event from the inception of the star to its death. Eventually, it defied the situation presented in some models regarding the high mass progenitors. It resulted from a lower-mass red supergiant star (RSG) going SN. Still, the mass loss mechanism with which the star lost its significant hydrogen layer is uncertain (the weighing is more towards the presence of a binary counterpart). We present the alternative scenario to the current understanding of short plateau supernova origins. We also obtained the non-detection in the radio light curve. Some of the key results obtained are as follows. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh/image3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  Figure 3: Panchromatic photometric (above) and optical spectroscopic (below) observations spanning about a year for SN 2020jfo are shown here. [Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac610b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Teja et al. 2022&lt;/a&gt;] 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh/image5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  Figure 4: Model light curves obtained using the MESA+STELLA framework for various evolved progenitors are plotted along with the pseudo-bolometric light curve for SN 2020jfo. The figure in the inset shows the requirement to include CSM interaction to fit the observed light curve. [Adapted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac610b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Teja et al. 2022&lt;/a&gt;] 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SN 2020jfo peaked in the Bessell’s V photometric filter at an absolute magnitude of -17.4(4) mag; for comparison, the Sun has an absolute magnitude of +4.83 in the same filter, implying SN to be millions of times brighter than the Sun. From 1D hydrodynamical modeling, we found that the most plausible progenitor is an RSG with an initial mass about 12 times the mass of the Sun, a radius about 600 times the Sun’s radius, and a final pre-SN mass &amp;lt;6 solar mass. Using the nebular-phase (post plateau decline phase, which is majorly powered by radioactive nickel decay chain) spectrum, we estimated a progenitor of mass ∼12 solar mass in corroboration with modeled mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We concluded that It evolved in a relatively high-metallicity environment and shredded a significant amount of mass during its evolution. The presence of ionized Helium line, HV Hα feature, higher luminosity in contrast to slower velocity evolution, and the steeper decline in luminosity indicated the presence of circumstellar (CSM), which was corroborated in models [Figure 4]. A fraction of the solar mass of CSM spread across 40 AU was deduced for SN 2020jfo’s progenitor, possibly resulting from a high mass loss a few years before the collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of various night sky surveys, viz. ZTF , &lt;a href=&quot;https://atlas.fallingstar.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ATLAS (Asteroid Terrestrial-impact Last Alert System)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://asas-sn.osu.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ASAS-SN (All Sky Automated Survey for SuperNovae)&lt;/a&gt;, and upcoming &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lsst.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LSST (Legacy Survey of Space and Time)&lt;/a&gt;, there is a great boom in discovering the exotic transients, which challenge our understanding of these events. It is necessary to study these in detail using observations and modeling and, if possible, weed out any cases which are not deemed worthy as indicators of distance. With the growing sample of these events, it is possible there could be more classes to these SN than the given one, and hence these kinds of studies provide the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac610b/meta&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SN 2020jfo: A Short-plateau Type II Supernova from a Low-mass Progenitor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Rishabh Singh Teja&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Avinash Singh, D. K. Sahu, G. C. Anupama, Brajesh Kumar, and Nayana A. J.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru, 560034; India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/astrophysical_autopsy_rishabh</guid>
        
        <category>Transients</category>
        
        <category>Supernova</category>
        
        <category>Observations</category>
        
        <category>Hydrodynamic Modelling</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
