<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> Welcome to CosmicVarta.</title>
    <description> Platform for promoting Indian astronomy research to the public.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 17:58:26 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 17:58:26 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Shedding Light on the Cosmic Web with Fast Radio Bursts</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fast Radio Bursts are millisecond-duration radio transients of extragalactic origin. Their dispersion measures are sensitive to the presence of ionized matter along their lines of sight. This unique measurable makes FRBs a promising cosmological probe that can shed light on a hitherto invisible matter reservoir that constitutes the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of Fast Radio Bursts (FRBs) is one of the fastest developing fields of astronomical research.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Discovered serendipitously only in 2007 by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2007Sci...318..777L/abstract&quot;&gt;Lorimer et al&lt;/a&gt;, FRBs are bright, millisecond-duration transient radio events. According to some &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2013Sci...341...53T/abstract&quot;&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt;, thousands of FRBs occur in the sky daily. If one could see the sky in the radio frequencies, they would look like Fig.1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/frb_sunil/image1.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: An artist’s rendition of what FRBs look like in the radio wavelengths. &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/146295242&quot;&gt;Credit: NRAO outreach&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most FRBs detected have extragalactic origins with the only exception being two &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2020PASP..132c4202B/abstract&quot;&gt;recently discovered&lt;/a&gt; radio pulse emissions from a Milky Way &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnetar&quot;&gt;magnetar&lt;/a&gt;, a compact remnant of a supernova that sports extremely strong magnetic fields, SGR 1935+2154. As the FRB pulses travel through space, they are dispersed by plasma (ionized matter) that permeates the universe, just like sunlight disperses in a prism into a rainbow. This means the higher frequency components of the pulse travel faster than the lower frequency waves. Fig. 2 shows the dispersed pulse reported by Lorimer et al. The amount of dispersion is quantified by the Dispersion Measure (DM). DM is defined as the line-of-sight integral of electron density, weighted by the cosmological scale factor. In Fig. 2, the DM essentially tells you how far apart the 1.5 GHz and 1.2 GHz components are. Measuring DM therefore relies on accurately estimating the arrival delay between the high and low frequencies constituting the light and since the delay is of the order of a few seconds. Lorimer et al could not account for the burst’s large DM using estimates of matter density within our galaxy alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was very much this dispersion that led Lorimer et al to postulate they are extragalactic in origin. In fact, it was several times larger and the burst was estimated to have originated at a distance of &amp;lt;1 Gigaparsec (Gpc). The sharp FRB pulse is therefore quite a unique and powerful probe of ionized matter on cosmological scales. Previously available cosmological probes of matter like quasar absorption lines are largely “blind” to ionized matter as fully ionized hydrogen and helium (which makes up most of the universe) do not produce any line features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/frb_sunil/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: The dispersed pulse of the Lorimer Burst. The dark curve is the FRB event. The horizontal axis shows the time relative to a reference. The higher frequency components of the pulse come before the low frequency components and thus the curve goes from the top-left to bottom-right. The shape of the curve is governed by plasma physics. The inset image shows the pulse when all the frequencies are aligned (i.e. the curve is straightened) and summed over. Note how sharp the pulse is compared to the total time of the FRB event (~0.4 s).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emission or absorption line features are manifestations of the quantum nature of an atom. In the ionized state, i.e. when  atoms are stripped of their electrons, there is no quantum system to produce said features. Furthermore, continuum (i.e. non line-like) emission from electrons/ions in the intergalactic medium is extremely hard to detect due to its sparsity. FRB dispersions on the other hand provide a direct measure of the line-of-sight integrated ionized matter density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to their transient nature, it is only recently that FRBs have been localized in the sky with a precision better than an arcsecond thanks to advances in radio interferometry. The first FRB to be precisely localized was FRB 20121102 (by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017ApJ...834L...7T/abstract&quot;&gt;Tendulkar et al&lt;/a&gt; in 2017), which using the American Very Large Array (VLA), was pinpointed to a small, highly star-forming galaxy at a redshift of 0.19. This FRB was first detected by the Arecibo telescope in 2012 and then since the source burst repeatedly albeit sporadically over the years, it was finally captured with the radio interferometer that is the VLA in 2017. In 2018, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019Sci...365..565B/abstract&quot;&gt;Bannister et al&lt;/a&gt; detected and simultaneously localized the FRB 20180924 thanks to the Australian Square-Kilometer-Array Pathfinder (ASKAP) and a new technique of performing radio interferometry. ASKAP consists of several large radio antenna pointing in the same direction in the sky. The telescope essentially looks for a transient in the non-interferometric mode&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, i.e. without correlating the signal from its individual antennae, to maximize the area of the sky scanned. The moment it detects a transient, the data in its buffer gets dumped to an external storage space for post-detection correlation and subsequently localization. Since the first detection, ASKAP has localized several FRBs and will continue doing so. Precise localization is crucial in pegging the FRB’s distance as the pulse itself does not carry precise information about the redshift&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. Localization is crucial to identify the host galaxy and spectroscopic follow-up observations of the host yield the redshift or distance estimate&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/frb_sunil/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: UV image of the FRB 20190608 host galaxy showing the active starforming regions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApJ...922..173C/abstract&quot;&gt;Chittidi et al 2020&lt;/a&gt;). The red circle/white rectangle shows the radio-derived location of the FRB which is coincident with one of the starforming clumps.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the dispersion and the distance to the FRBs, one can start constraining the matter distribution in the foreground universe. One FRB sightline that we studied in detail was that of FRB 20190608 (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2020ApJ...901..134S/abstract&quot;&gt;Simha et al 2020&lt;/a&gt;). This FRB was localized to a spiral galaxy at redshift 0.3215 in the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) footprint. A UV Hubble image of the galaxy showed that the FRB originated from one of the star-forming clumps within a spiral arm (Fig. 3). Due to its fortunate location within the SDSS database, we had extensive spectroscopic information of the field galaxies. This informed us about the location of foreground galaxies relative to the sightline and thus, with some modeling, the contribution of different foreground electron reservoirs to the FRB DM. Being an integrated quantity, the DM can be split into multiple parts corresponding to the source of electrons. That is,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
DM&lt;sub&gt;FRB&lt;/sub&gt; = DM&lt;sub&gt;MW&lt;/sub&gt; + DM&lt;sub&gt;halos&lt;/sub&gt; + DM&lt;sub&gt;IGM&lt;/sub&gt; + DM&lt;sub&gt;host&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here DM&lt;sub&gt;MW&lt;/sub&gt; is the contribution from the Milky Way interstellar medium (ISM) and halo, DM&lt;sub&gt;host&lt;/sub&gt; is a similar term but for the host galaxy, DM&lt;sub&gt;halos&lt;/sub&gt; is from the gas present in intervening galactic halos and DM&lt;sub&gt;IGM&lt;/sub&gt; is from the diffuse filamentary gas that permeates the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observable_universe#Large-scale_structure&quot;&gt;cosmic web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;. In our work, we aimed to estimate each of these individual subcomponents from optical observations. For the Milky Way, we used models of the ISM electron distribution constructed using galactic pulsars (NE2001; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2003astro.ph..1598C/abstract&quot;&gt;Cordes and Lazio 2003&lt;/a&gt;). We modeled the gas distribution of the halo as a modified NFW profile (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019MNRAS.485..648P/abstract&quot;&gt;Prochaska and Zheng 2019&lt;/a&gt; for details). In total, of the 340 pc cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;of the FRB DM, we estimated roughly 80 pc cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; arising from the Milky Way. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApJ...922..173C/abstract&quot;&gt;Chittidi et al 2020&lt;/a&gt; estimated the DM&lt;sub&gt;host&lt;/sub&gt;~100 pc cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integral_field_spectrograph&quot;&gt;integral field unit&lt;/a&gt; (IFU)&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; observations with the Keck Cosmic Web Imager (KCWI) and the same halo model as the one used for the Milky Way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the SDSS and WISE photometry available for the field galaxies in tandem with the spectroscopic redshifts, we estimated the stellar masses of foreground galaxies. Then, using the stellar-to-halo-mass ratio from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2013MNRAS.428.3121M/abstract&quot;&gt;Moster et al 2013&lt;/a&gt;, we estimated their halo masses. Assuming that the halo gas typically extends up to one virial radius&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;, we determined which halos intersect the FRB sightline and then using our modified NFW halo gas model, determined their DM contributions. We estimated DM&lt;sub&gt;halos&lt;/sub&gt; ~ 20 pc cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimating DM&lt;sub&gt;IGM&lt;/sub&gt; was perhaps the most challenging as one cannot directly observe diffuse filamentary gas, its presence is generally inferred indirectly. However, since we had access to the SDSS galaxy redshifts, we could, in theory, reconstruct the cosmic web density using them as tracers. Thus, we leveraged the Monte-Carlo &lt;i&gt;Physarum Machine&lt;/i&gt; (MCPM) model introduced by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2020ApJ...891L..35B/abstract&quot;&gt;Burchett et al&lt;/a&gt; in 2020 to do exactly this. The algorithm is inspired by the motion of Physarum polycephalum or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3rWk6h0Syog&quot;&gt;slime mold&lt;/a&gt;. The mold efficiently searches for food particles and produces a filamentary network connecting them in its wake. Modeling the galaxies as “food”, one can produce a steady-state slime mold particle density with MCPM and translate this to physical matter density by calibrating against dark matter density in cosmological simulations. The result (see Fig. 4) is an estimate of gas density along the sightline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/frb_sunil/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: Cosmic web density “reconstruction” using the MCPM algorithm for the FRB 20190608 sightline. Though galaxies were cone-searched around the FRB, as it is located in one of the narrow strips of SDSS, there were more spectra available in one direction (top) than the other (side) and thus our model doesn’t appear conical.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this model, we estimated DM&lt;sub&gt;IGM&lt;/sub&gt; ~ 110 pc cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus just using optical data, we were able to estimate DMFRB and closely match the radio measurement. Our model uncertainties are fairly large (~30%) but nevertheless, this work was a proof of concept that FRB DMs can inform us about the matter distribution in the universe. Furthermore, if this analysis is performed on multiple sightlines, we can start laying statistical constraints on some of the key model parameters that were only assumed in this work e.g. the fraction of the universe’s baryons in the filamentary gas and the fraction of halo gas present in the hot (&amp;gt;10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; K) ionized phase. In fact, our future work on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021arXiv210900386L/abstract&quot;&gt;FLIMFLAM&lt;/a&gt; (FRB Line-of-sight Ionization Measurement with Lightcone AAOmega Mapping) survey intends to achieve ~ 10% constraints on these parameters using ~25 sightlines. We are currently collecting spectroscopic redshifts of field galaxies along multiple sightlines and hope to start producing preliminary results within the next year. FRB-aided cosmology promises exciting research in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] See &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019A%26ARv..27....4P/abstract&quot;&gt;Petroff et al&lt;/a&gt; 2019 for an excellent review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://astronomy.curtin.edu.au/research/craft/&quot;&gt;CRAFT webpage&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41550-018-0597-7&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; for more details on the survey and the telescope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Though the dispersion is correlated to the distance, there are many sources of uncertainty in the DM-redshift relation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] Astronomers use redshift as a proxy for distance when it comes to cosmological scales. This is thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubble%27s_law&quot;&gt;Hubble relation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] This is the large-scale structure of matter in the universe. As dark matter (and regular matter) condensed gravitationally after the Big Bang, it created halos and filamentary structures connecting halos, giving it a web-like appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6] IFUs are specialized instruments that can take images as well as spectra of the field-of-view simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7] A virial radius of a halo is the radius from its center within which the halo dark matter density is roughly 200 times larger than the background value. Think of it as the radial extent of the halo matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApJ...921..134S/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Estimating the Contribution of Foreground Halos to the FRB 180924 Dispersion Measure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Sunil Simha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Nicolas Tejos, J. Xavier Prochaska, Khee-Gan Lee, Stuart D. Ryder, Sebastiano Cantalupo, Keith W. Bannister, Shivani Bhandari and Ryan M. Shannon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; University of California, Santa Cruz, CA 95064, United States&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/shedding-light-cosmic-web-sunil</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shedding-light-cosmic-web-sunil</guid>
        
        <category>Cosmology</category>
        
        <category>Fast Radio Bursts</category>
        
        <category>Galaxy dark matter halos</category>
        
        <category>Radio transient sources</category>
        
        <category>Quasar absorption line spectroscopy</category>
        
        
        <category>Cosmology and Nongalactic Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Identifying emission-line stars from a large spectroscopic database</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We present a catalog of 3339 hot emission-line stars (ELS) identified from 451,695 O, B, and A type spectra, provided by the LAMOST DR5 release. We developed an automated python routine that identified 5437 spectra having a peak between 6561 and 6568~Å. False detections and bad spectra were removed, leaving 4138 good emission-line spectra of 3339 unique ELS. We re-estimated the spectral type of 3307 spectra as the LAMOST Stellar Parameter Pipeline (LASP) did not provide accurate spectral types for these emission-line spectra. As Herbig Ae/Be stars show higher excess in near-infrared and mid-infrared wavelengths than Classical Ae/Be stars, we used 2MASS and WISE photometry to distinguish them. Finally, we report 1089 Classical Be, 233 Classical Ae, and 56 Herbig Ae/Be stars identified from the LAMOST DR5. In addition, 928 B[em]/A[em] stars and 240 CAe/CBe potential candidates are identified. From our sample of 3339 hot emission-line stars, 2716 ELS identified in this work do not have any record in the SIMBAD database and they can be considered as new detections. Identification of such a large homogeneous set of emission-line spectra will help the community to study the emission phenomenon in detail without worrying about the inherent biases when compiling from various sources.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand what emission line stars (ELS) are, one needs to know about the spectrum of a star. Each star has its own unique spectrum, analogous to the fingerprint of humans. A spectrum can be used to identify the properties of the star such as its temperature, chemical composition and (indirect) physical constraints. So clearly, spectroscopy of cosmic objects can reveal lots of information about the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let us ask a more basic question. What is a spectrum? To understand this, imagine a rainbow on a rainy day. A rainbow is formed when the sunlight passes through the water molecules suspended in the air after the rain. As the sunlight moves through a spherical water droplet, it gets dispersed into various colours ranging from Violet to Red. This is a real-life example of spectroscopy. The light from a stellar object, when passed through a slit or a prism (the optical equivalent of the spherical water droplet), gets split into various colours. If the light from the star is as ideal as white light is, which is made up of all the colors with equal intensity, we would get a beautiful color gradient with all colors shining equally. However, the universe is not that simple. The spectrum of a star will have bright and dark lines, similar to the way we have ridges and valleys in our fingerprint (Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1:  A representative high-resolution spectrum showing the visible light of alpha Boo. The black lines in this spectrum are caused due to various metallic elements present in the photosphere of the cool giant alpha Boo.
Image source:&lt;a hrefsridharan1_emission_stars_database=&quot;https://noirlab.edu/public/images/noao-arct/&quot;&gt;N.A.Sharp, NOIRLab/NSF/AURA)
 &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bright and dark lines (or emission and absorption lines) are the most crucial information of the spectrum. They tell us about the atomic and molecular processes going on in the top most layer of the star which is known as the photosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An absorption line is formed in the spectrum when light of a certain wavelength is absorbed by an atom or a molecule. Similarly, an emission line is formed when light of a certain wavelength is emitted (or radiated) by an atom or a molecule. To put it simply, when an atom ‘absorbs’ light, it goes into a higher energy level and when it ‘emits’ light, it comes down to a lower energy level as shown in Figure 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 2: The above plots show the absorption and emission process as caused by the excitation and de-excitation of electrons around the nucleus.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webassign.net/labsgraceperiod/ucscgencheml1/lab_6/manual.html&quot;&gt;webassign &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spectrum of a star is the information that gives us the intensity at each wavelength of light. An observed stellar spectrum consists of the blackbody continuum, absorption lines and in some cases, emission lines. The blackbody continuum in the visible and infrared region is due to the thermal emission of the star and the absorption lines are seen because the ‘cooler’ photosphere absorbs light at certain wavelengths. These two components are seen in the spectrum of all the stars because it arises due to the basic structure of stars. Now let us come to the topic of this article, ELS. Emission lines arise from a hot, gaseous region around the star that is formed due to some special nature of the star. The type of stars that show emission lines in their spectrum are called Emission line stars (ELS). You can call them the rebellious group of star families, who want to be unique by showing emission lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various types of ELS known to us today (and its analogues)
Pre-main sequence (PMS) stars - young, naughty teenagers creating chaos
Classical Be stars - people with midlife crisis
Wolf-Rayet stars - old, wise people
Even though ELS comprises stars in various evolutionary phases, in most cases the emission arises from the equatorial circumstellar disc which is made of gas and dust. The formation mechanism of circumstellar disc varies between different classes. For example, in PMS stars the circumstellar disc is the accretion disc through which material is added to the star from its surroundings. In Classical Be stars, the disc is formed due to rapid spinning of the star which pushes away material from the star to its surroundings. So it should be noted that even though we put stars with emission lines into a single category of ELS, they are very different from each other. Hence, we need to classify them based on their photometric properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aim&quot;&gt;Aim:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As large-scale spectroscopic surveys collect a large number of spectra every night, we need to identify special classes of stars such as ELS and classify them into different categories for the research community to study various emission mechanisms. This is the motivation for the work titled “Discovery of 2716 hot emission-line stars from LAMOST DR5’’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data&quot;&gt;Data:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAMOST) is a multi-object telescope that can observe around 4000 stars in one night. By its 5th data release (DR5), it had accumulated around 9 million spectra from 2011-2017 which are available to the community. We made use of this huge database to increase the number of ELS stars known to us. One interesting fact about LAMOST is that the majority of  observed stars are in the Galactic anticenter direction. This is particularly important because the earlier studies which have identified ELS have not looked into this direction of the sky. So this opened up an opportunity to study ELS in previously less explored parts of the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;analysis&quot;&gt;Analysis:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this work, we took O, B and A type stars (Teff ranging from 30000 K to 10000 K) from the LAMOST DR5 database (for an explanation of different spectral types, look into Anusha R’s CAe article). We restricted ourselves to these spectral types because the main aim of this was to identify new Classical Be/Ae and Herbig Be/Ae stars. Once we removed bad quality (Signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) &amp;lt; 10)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; spectra from our list, we used an open-source python package called ‘scipy.signal’ to identify emission peaks. The entire definition of ELS rests on the presence of one of the most commonly found emission line, Hα at 6563 Å. We searched and picked out spectra with the Hα line anywhere between 6561 Å and 6568 Å. This range was selected to take into effect the instrumental calibration defect (if any) and the doppler shift that may be seen in a few stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identified 4138 spectra that belong to 3339 unique ELS stars from our analysis. To classify stars into different categories such as CBeAe or HBeAe, we need an accurate spectral type for each spectrum. The LAMOST automated pipeline does provide a spectral type for each spectrum which did not turn out to be accurate due to the presence of emission lines. This introduced the necessity for us to re-estimate spectral type for each spectrum. We followed a technique called template matching. We made use of the MILES stellar spectral library for this purpose. For each spectrum, we matched the templates from MILES library to our target spectrum and identified the best fit. Then the spectral type of the best fit template was assigned to the target spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to differentiate between Classical Be/Ae and Herbig Be/Ae stars, we made use of the inherent difference between them known as Infrared (IR) excess. Herbig Be/Ae stars, being young stars, have lots of gas and dust around them in addition to a circumstellar disc. This extra gas and dust reprocesses the energy from the star and emits them in infrared wavelengths. Due to this, the HAeBe stars are brighter in IR wavelengths than CBe stars. Hence we use the photometric data&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; available to us to differentiate them based on colors and spectral indices. The breakup of various classes identified in this work is given in the table below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;  Table 1: Statistical break-up of various classes identified in this work.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.08025&quot;&gt;Table 1 of the review paper) &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We visually examined the Hα line features belonging to each class and reported their statistics. Finally, a representative spectrum of major classes is presented in Figure 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 3: This plot shows a representative spectrum belonging to each of Oe*, CBe, CAe, HBe, HAe, B[em], and A[em] classes. Red dotted lines denote [NII] lines at 6548 and 6584 ̊A and green solid lines denote [SII] lines at 6717 and 6731 ̊A. The spectra are normalized using laspec open source python package.

Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.08025&quot;&gt; Figure 7 of the review paper &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-scope&quot;&gt;Future Scope:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research work identifies new ELS stars from a large database and classifies them into various categories based on their photometric properties. As the data collection capabilities increase day-to-day, the need for such works increases. We have multiple follow-up works in the fray which uses the LAMOST database effectively in identifying and study the properties of CBeAe and HAeBe stars in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021arXiv210808025B/abstract&quot;&gt; Discovery of 2716 hot emission-line stars from LAMOST DR5 &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Shridharan Baskaran&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Blesson Mathew, Nidhi S, Anusha R, Arun R, Sreeja S. Kartha, Yerra Bharat Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; CHRIST (Deemed to be University), Bangalore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Signal-to-noise ratio or SNR is a quantity which defines the quality of a spectrum. More the SNR, the better the spectrum. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Photometry (in astronomical context) means measurement of brightness of a star. The brightness of a star observed through filters of different wavelengths can be used to decode information about the star. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photometry_(astronomy)&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/sridharan_emission_stars_database</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/sridharan_emission_stars_database</guid>
        
        <category>Emission-line stars</category>
        
        <category>Catalog</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bar Buckling and Boxy/Peanut Bulges as the Tracer of Dark Matter Halo Shape</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Galaxies reside in the deep potential of invisible matter called dark matter. Their dynamics is significantly affected by the distribution of dark matter around them. Distribution of dark matter around galaxies is usually known as dark matter halo. Most of the previous studies of galaxies assumed spherical dark matter halos. But, cosmological simulations of structure formation suggest that the dark matter halo can vary in shape. It can also have non-spherical shape (e.g. oblate and prolate) which can significantly influence the evolution of the galaxy. In this study, Astronomer from IIA, Bangalore and SJTU, China have studied the effect of non-spherical dark matter halos on the buckling of the bars and formation of boxy/peanut shape bulges. They perfomed a set of numerical simulation for varying dark matter halo shape and traced the formation of bars and boxy/peanut shape bulges.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at the clear night sky, you may find a white bright band stretching from north to south in the sky. It is nothing but our home galaxy, the Milky Way. There are trillions of galaxies in our observable Universe. Galaxies are gravitationally bound systems of stars, gas, dust, and invisible matter called dark matter. Galaxies come in different shapes and sizes ranging from spherical - like a ball to disk - like a round plate. Since most of the disk galaxies have spiral arms, they are also called spiral galaxies. Depending on the presence of a bar, a spiral galaxy could be a barred spiral or unbarred spiral. Disk galaxies usually possess a dense collection of stars in their centres which is termed as the bulge. Bulges can range from nearly spherical to as flat as the disk of galaxies. Our Milky way has a boxy/peanut shape flat bulge which is supposed to have formed from the thickening of the bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ankit1_bar_buckling_dark_matter/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1: Example of unbarred and barred galaxies.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://ned.ipac.caltech.edu/&quot;&gt;NED
 &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The matter we can see in a galaxy is far less than its actual matter content. More than 80% of the total galaxy mass is invisible to us. Only the motion of the stars or gas in the galaxy shows the presence of dark matter. This invisible matter is commonly referred to as dark matter. Due to the presence of an enormous amount of dark matter in the galaxy, the dynamics of the stars is remarkably affected by the distribution of the dark matter. In the past, there have been several detailed studies of the galaxies assuming the spherical distribution of dark matter in the galaxies. There are very limited works that consider the non-spherical distribution of dark matter for the study of galaxies. In the present paper, Ankit Kumar and the team have investigated the effect of non-spherical dark matter distribution on the bar buckling and the formation of boxy/peanut flat bulge like that seen in our Galaxy. Bar buckling is a bar thickening mechanism where the bar suddenly bends out of the disk of the galaxy. Bar buckling can be simply understood using a practical example of a beam or pillar. Say, there is a vertically standing beam and you start increasing the load on it. Then at some point, it will suddenly bend somewhere in the middle (or may collapse). This sudden change is called the buckling of the beam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ankit1_bar_buckling_dark_matter/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 2: Examples of oblate, spherical, and prolate dark matter halos in a disk galaxy.

Image source: Author.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authors have used the supercomputing facility to generate mock realistic disk galaxies and to evolve them in time. The distribution of dark matter in the galaxies ranges from oblate to prolate including spherical one. Oblate distribution (or oblate halo) looks like the shape formed on squeezing a sphere from its top and bottom whereas prolate distribution (or prolate halo) is similar to the shape formed on stretching a sphere from its top and bottom. To trace the formation and evolution of the bar and buckling events, they used Fourier analysis and found that the galaxies in prolate halos form bar earlier than the galaxies in oblate halos. Also, the bar in prolate halos buckles before the bar in the oblate halos. Fourier analysis is the method to decompose any general function or structure into simple trigonometric functions or structures with definite frequencies (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourier_series&quot;&gt; this article  &lt;/a&gt; for Fourier series).
Buckling events are very rarely observed. To date, there are only 8 confirmed galaxies that are currently going through the buckling events. In this study, Ankit Kumar and the team found three distinct buckling events for the bar in the prolate halo. It is the first time where more than two buckling events in a bar have been detected in any study. The total duration of buckling is longer for the bar in the prolate halo. The rarity of buckling in observations and longer duration buckling in the prolate halos lead authors to conclude that most of the dark matter halos could be oblate and spherical in shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ankit1_bar_buckling_dark_matter/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; A clear buckling of the iso-density contour can be seen in the outer bar of the prolate halo during the 3rd buckling event. It also shows the formation and growth of peanut shape bulge after bar buckling.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/509/1/1262/6406514&quot;&gt; Kumar et. al. 2021. &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each buckling event makes the bar thick in size. First buckling thickens the innermost region of the bar while the succeeding bucklings thicken the outer regions of the bar. As a result of these thickening boxy/peanut shape flat bulge forms. Since the bar in the prolate halo shows more buckling events as compared to the oblate halo, the bar in prolate halo thickens the most and forms the most thicker boxy/peanut shape bulge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article-abstract/509/1/1262/6406514?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt; The effect of dark matter halo shape on bar buckling and boxy/peanut bulges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Ankit Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Mousumi Das, and Sandeep Kumar Kataria&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt;
Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India – 560034; Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India – 560012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/bar-buckling-dark-matter-ankit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/bar-buckling-dark-matter-ankit/</guid>
        
        <category>Galaxies</category>
        
        <category>Bar Buckling</category>
        
        <category>Boxy/Peanut shape bulges</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Measuring the age of the Universe: An overview</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A popular article exploring how the age of the Universe was calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://cosmicvarta.in/measuring-the-age-sun-moon-gourav&quot;&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; has already provided a flavour of how scientists use mathematics combined with knowledge obtained from physics to reveal numerous hidden secrets of nature such as the age of the Earth, the Moon and even the Solar System. But the story does not end here. It literally cannot. This is because the curiosity of human beings is unquenchable. Naturally, any curious mind will ask the next question, what is the age of the universe? Fortunately, the power of human intellect combined with the supreme efficiency of mathematics and physics have provided an answer to this almost impossible to solve question also. We now know with reasonable confidence that our universe is around 13.8 billion (i.e. 1380 crore since 1 billion = 100 crore) years old. But, how do we measure the age of the universe? To know the answer, one has to study ‘cosmology’. This might be one of the most thrilling detective stories of all time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cosmology is the study of the size, structure and evolution of the universe — in other words, the &lt;em&gt;geography&lt;/em&gt; of the universe as a single system. In cosmology, our subject is the whole universe, defined as all matter and energy in existence anywhere, observable or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;birth-of-cosmology&quot;&gt;Birth of cosmology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most fundamental questions of humanity is the question of origins:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Where did we come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question runs deeper than the origins of any one person and delves into questions of where did life, our planet, and the entire universe come from. Many cultures have avoided the notion of an origin to the universe by placing their creation stories in a cycle. Buddhist and Hindu origins stories measure the birth, death, and rebirth of the universe in units of 4 trillion years, which is a day in the life of Brahma. At night, all matter is absorbed into the spirit of the sleeping Brahma. At dawn, when Brahma awakes, matter reappears and the cycle continues. The Greek Stoics saw the universe as being created from fire, only to be destroyed by fire, and so on. Cosmological cycles are also found in the cultures of the Maya and the Aztec.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of modern cosmology began with Albert Einstein and Edwin Hubble. From Einstein’s theories, the shape of space is described as being warped by gravity. From the observations of Hubble, we learned the universe is expanding. Together these two men described the evolving shape of space and they opened up a new field of science called cosmology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-big-bang-model&quot;&gt;The Big Bang model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern theory of the origin of the universe starts with the idea of expanding space. Georges Lemaître was a priest and a mathematician, an unassuming man who had beaten the giants of physics to the punch in deducing that the universe could be expanding. In 1929, Lemaître was the first to hypothesize a revolutionary idea: at one time, the universe might have been as small as an atomic nucleus. He proposed that the universe derived from a cosmic singularity, &lt;em&gt;a day without a yesterday&lt;/em&gt; when the universe was infinitely small and infinitely curved, and all matter and energy were concentrated in a single point. Many astrophysicists found the idea bizarre and distasteful and English theorist Fred Hoyle disparaged the idea with the name &lt;em&gt;big bang&lt;/em&gt;. The label stuck, and scientists continue to call the description of the creation of the universe the Big Bang model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gourav_measuring_age_universe/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1: According to the Big Bang model, the universe expanded from an extremely dense and hot state and continues to expand today
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_Big_Bang_theory&quot;&gt;Wikipedia &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big Bang model forces us to consider the idea of cosmic evolution. The universal recession of galaxies implies that the universe is evolving, and it has not always been in the same state. Our observations of nearby galaxies represent a single frame in a movie that has been playing for billions of years. We can wind the tape backwards, seeing snapshots of a progressively older universe, by observing sets of galaxies at progressively larger distances, and thus at progressively larger look back times. (Since light takes time to travel, we see objects far away as they looked when the light was released rather than as they are now.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we look back into the early universe, we can see the galaxies move closer together. Observationally, we can’t see all the way back to the first moments, but we can see times when galaxies were just forming, and the large scale structures — the cosmic walls and voids — were just starting to form. If we could look further back, we’d see that as the universe gets smaller; its volume contracts until all the mass are smashed together in a tiny universe. The mass that formed galaxies and stars breaks down into a seething hot gas, as the universe tends toward a state of infinite temperature and density. Thinking of the Big Bang as an explosion is tempting, but it is also misleading. In an explosion on Earth, debris flies through space. In the Big Bang, the initial singularity contains all space and matter. Time itself begins with the big bang. The evolution of the universe is the unfolding of time and space from a condition of incredible heat and density to cold and enormous state billions of years later. This bang had no center, it had no past and it simply was the sudden beginning of everything in an expanding geometry that may or may not be finite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific story of creation says that everything — you and the Earth and the Sun and the Milky Way and all the billions of galaxies — emerged from a tiny dense dot of energy and matter that unfolded into the universe we see now. It sounds as fantastic as any of the creation myths of older cultures. How do we know that the big bang actually occurred? There are three primary pieces of evidence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Galaxies are taking part in a universal expansion as indicated by the linear relation between distance and redshift (the Hubble relation).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The abundance of the lightest elements can be explained by fusion in the universe when it was young and dense and hot (cosmic nucleosynthesis).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Space is filled with the radiation from the early hot phase, now diluted and reduced in energy to the level of microwaves (the cosmic microwave background).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Describing each of these concepts is beyond the scope of this article. But the Hubble relation mentioned in the first point bears huge importance in measuring the age of the universe. Hence, I shall take the opportunity to discuss in brief the Hubble relation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hubble-relation-or-hubbles-law&quot;&gt;Hubble relation or Hubble’s law&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hubble relation, popularly known as the Hubble’s law or Hubble–Lemaître law is considered the first observational basis for the expansion of the universe and today serves as one of the pieces of evidence most often cited in support of the Big Bang model. Although widely attributed to Edwin Hubble, the notion of the universe expanding at a calculable rate was first derived from the general relativity equations in 1922 by Alexander Friedmann. Friedmann published a set of equations, now known as the Friedmann equations, showing that the universe might expand, and presenting the expansion speed if this was the case. Then Georges Lemaître, in a 1927 article, independently derived that the universe might be expanding, observed the proportionality between the recessional velocity of and distance to distant bodies and suggested an estimated value of the proportionality constant, which when corrected by Hubble became known as the Hubble constant. Then in 1929, Edwin Hubble confirmed the existence of cosmic expansion and determined a more accurate value for the constant that now bears his name. Hubble inferred the recession velocity of the objects from their redshifts, many of which were earlier measured and related to velocity by Vesto Slipher in 1917.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gourav_measuring_age_universe/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 2: Georges Lemaître
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georges_Lema%C3%AEtre&quot;&gt;Wikipedia &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gourav_measuring_age_universe/image3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 3: Edwin Hubble
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/biography/Edwin-Hubble&quot;&gt;Britannica &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gourav_measuring_age_universe/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 4: Fred Hoyle
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2010/oct/03/fred-hoyle-nobel-prize&quot;&gt;The Guardian &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The law is often expressed by the equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;v = H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;D   (1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where, v is the recessional velocity, typically expressed in km/s.
H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; is Hubble’s constant and corresponds to the value of H (often termed the Hubble parameter which is a value that is time-dependent and which can be expressed in terms of the scale factor) in the Friedmann equations taken at the time of observation denoted by the subscript 0. This value is the same throughout the universe for a given comoving time.
D is the proper distance (which can change over time, unlike the comoving distance, which is constant) from the galaxy to the observer, measured in megaparsecs (Mpc), in the 3-space defined by given cosmological time.
The reciprocal of H0 is the Hubble time. This constant term H0 help us to estimate the age of the universe. Let me now discuss in brief how it does so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;age-of-the-universe&quot;&gt;Age of the Universe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Einstein, Lemaitre, and others solved the equations of general relativity, they were able to describe how the size of the universe has changed with time. Astronomers use the symbol R to represent the scale or size of the universe at any time. You can think of R as the size of the universe, but more accurately it represents the distance between any two well-separated places. The cosmological principle says that any two points are moving apart at the same rate. Thus, the entire history of the universe is described by the way that R varies with time. Since the universe is expanding, R has been continuously increasing for billions of years. Remember that R describes the expansion of space that carries galaxies apart — the galaxies themselves are not expanding. Galaxies are just markers of expanding space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big Bang model even provides a prediction for the age of the universe. If we imagine the evolving universe as a movie, the birth of the universe is the time in the distant past when all matter and radiation was crushed in a state of infinite temperature and density. The scale factor, R, was zero. Space had not yet begun to unfold. There are three ways to constrain the age of the universe. But in many ways, looking at the expansion rate of the universe is one of the easiest ways to figure out the universe’s age. This technique looks at the current expansion rate and then running it backwards to determine when today’s universe must have been compressed down to a single point. Mathematically, the age of the universe is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;t&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 / H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;f (Ωr Ωm Ωλ;…)    (2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where t&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; is the current age, H0 is the current expansion rate, and f is a correction that takes into consideration the mass, energy, and other characteristics of the universe. For this method to work, you need to not only know the current expansion rate but also how this rate has changed over time due to the effects of gravity and the effect of dark energy (Ωλ;), which is pushing the universe apart. The best published value for the expansion rate is H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;=70.6 ± 3.1 (km/sec) / Mpc. This means that every Megaparsec of space expands roughly 70.6 km each second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on stellar evolution models, we estimate the oldest globular star clusters are between 11 and 13 billion years old. Apart from these two techniques, the most trusted means of determining the age of the universe comes from very precise measurements of the cosmic microwave background (CMB) radiation. The CMB is a diffuse, uniform background of microwave radiation that comes from all directions in the sky. This CMB is the electromagnetic radiation which is the remnant from an early stage of the universe, also known as &lt;em&gt;relic radiation&lt;/em&gt;. First observed accidentally by the radio engineers Arno Penzias and Robert Wilson in 1965, CMB is a crucial piece of evidence that supports the big bang model for the origin of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three space missions, in particular, have been instrumental in measuring this radiation in finer and finer detail and with better and better precision. NASA’s Cosmic Background Explorer (COBE) took data from 1989 to 1996 and it was the first to detect tiny variations in the intensity of the radiation. Next came the Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe (WMAP), launched by NASA in 2001. WMAP took data for a decade and its very accurate measurements put constraints on a set of parameters of the big bang model. The current state-of-the-art experiment is ESA’s Planck mission, launched in 2009. The level of accuracy of Planck data is tens of thousands of times greater than the discovery measurements of Penzias and Wilson. Based on the WMAP measurements and theoretical models, the universe is estimated to be 13.82 ± 0.12 billion years old. This is the most quoted age used by astronomers and is consistent with both other measurements within their errors. Remarkably, you can see that this value is very close to what has been estimated using the Hubble constant in equation 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very early in the history of mankind, ignorance of nature and fear of the unknown naturally made men religious. So God played a central role in primitive societies. They tried to answer every question with the help of God. As time passed, with experience and intellect men could understand more and more of the natural phenomenon. I have mentioned in my previous article that if one looks at the long march of human understanding, one will find that science begins with the idea that we can understand our role in the universe using logic and observation. Today humans have come a long way. And mathematics has truly acted as the most essential weapon in almost every known field, including astronomy. By now any reader will understand that in these two articles, I’ve discussed in brief how mathematics in simple form also has helped in the development of astronomy and human knowledge as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Birth of Time: How We Measured The Age Of The Universe; John Gribbin; Weidenfeld &amp;amp; Nicolson; 1999. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.in/books/about/The_Birth_of_Time.html?id=aWG3QgAACAAJ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&quot;&gt;Reference 1 &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Astronomy: The Solar System and Beyond; Michael A. Seeds, Dana E Backmann; Wadsworth Publishing Co Inc; 6th Ed: 2009. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6765882-astronomy&quot;&gt;Reference 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Planetary Science; Michael M. Woolfson, George H.A. Cole; CRC Press; 2013. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.in/books/about/Planetary_Science.html?id=B17OBQAAQBAJ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&quot;&gt;Reference 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;History of Astronomy: A Very Short Introduction; Michael Hoskin; Oxford University Press; 2008. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/589339?journalCode=isis&quot;&gt;Reference 4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Astrophysical Techniques; C R Kitchin; CRC Press; 2013. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/266150873_Astrophysical_Techniques_Sixth_Edition_by_CRKitchin&quot;&gt;Reference 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/measurig_age_uiverse_gourav</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/measurig_age_uiverse_gourav</guid>
        
        <category>popular</category>
        
        <category>age_of_universe</category>
        
        <category>big_bang</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Futuristic gravitational wave observations to resolve dichotomy of compact objects</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Gravitational waves are invisible ripples in space travel at the speed of light. It is generated in different scenarios, such as when two celestial bodies orbit around each other, an isolated body with tri-axial symmetry spins, inhomogeneity in matter distribution in the early universe, etc. Gravitational-wave astronomy aims to study these waves to improve the understanding of objects such as white dwarfs, neutron stars, and black holes, events such as supernovae, and processes including those of the early universe shortly after the Big Bang. The article describes how futuristic gravitational wave observatories can be used to resolve the dichotomy of compact objects.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, astronomy primarily relies on electromagnetic radiation. Over the past hundred years, various interesting astronomical objects have been discovered with gamma-ray detectors to radio telescopes. In recent years, gravitational wave astronomy has opened a new window to probe various exciting objects, and we can now look into the universe from a very different perspective. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LIGO&quot;&gt;LIGO&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virgo_interferometer&quot;&gt;Virgo&lt;/a&gt; gravitational wave detectors have so far made tens of detections from the merger of various compact objects. These are ground-based detectors operating at frequencies more than 1  Hz. As time progresses, these detectors have been upgraded continuously to increase their sensitivities so that we can look objects residing at further distances. Moreover, around 2035, a space-based gravitational wave mission, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elisascience.org&quot;&gt;LISA&lt;/a&gt; is planned to launch, which would operate at less than 1 Hz frequency. Many interesting objects such as galactic binaries, massive binaries, extreme mass ratio inspirals, etc., emit gravitational radiation at less than 1 Hz frequencies. Hence the current ground-based detectors cannot detect these objects, and LISA is planned to probe them. It is important to note that none of these objects are isolated in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, a group of researchers have claimed that LISA might detect some isolated compact objects too. The term compact objects primarily represent white dwarfs, neutron stars, and black holes. White dwarfs are the end state of stars with mass less than &lt;math&gt; (10
&amp;#177;2) M&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt;, where M&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt; ~2 x 10&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt; kg is the mass of the sun, in which the hydrogen fusion has stopped. One such object is the super-Chandrasekhar white dwarf. Over the past couple of decades, various researchers have detected more than a dozen over-luminous &lt;a href=&quot;http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/Astro/snovcn.html&quot;&gt;type Ia supernovae&lt;/a&gt;. Based on these observations, they have inferred that these supernovae have to be originated from massive white dwarfs, which violate the standard Chandrasekhar mass limit of 1.4 M&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt;. As a result, these objects are often termed as super-Chandrasekhar white dwarfs. It has been shown that if a white dwarf possesses strong magnetic fields at the center, such white dwarfs can indeed hold mass more than 1.4  M&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt;. Moreover, if such a white dwarf rotates in such a way that there is a misalignment between its magnetic and rotation axes, it can emit continuous gravitational waves. These researchers have explicitly shown that if a white dwarf has a strong central field but a weaker field at its surface, LISA can detect it within 1 year of detection period. On the other hand, if the white dwarf possesses a strong surface field or a weak central field, LISA will not be able to detect it. However, such white dwarfs can be detected by some other futuristic detectors, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20100526050722/http://trs-new.jpl.nasa.gov/dspace/bitstream/2014/37836/1/05-2157.pdf&quot;&gt;BBO&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://tamago.mtk.nao.ac.jp/spacetime/decigo_e.html&quot;&gt;DECIGO&lt;/a&gt;, etc. In this way, LISA can directly confirm the existence of super-Chandrasekhar white dwarfs (Fig. 1). Note that signal-to-noise ratio (S/N) is proportional to the square root of observation time (T) such that S/N increases with the observation time and the signal is more likely to be detected (see Section 1.4 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019Univ....5..217S/abstract&quot;&gt;Sieniawska &amp;amp; Bejger, 2019, Universe 5, 217&lt;/a&gt;). This likeliness of detection is due to the increase in observation period and not due to the increase in sensitivity of the detectors. If S/N &amp;GreaterEqual; 5, such a signal can be detected by a gravitational wave detector (see Section~2.1 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/415/2/1849/1044522?login=true&quot;&gt;Pitkin, 2011, MNRAS, 415, 1849&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_to_resolve_dichotomy_of_compact_objects_surajit_images/image_1a.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(a) Poloidally dominated white dwarf.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_to_resolve_dichotomy_of_compact_objects_surajit_images/image_1b.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(b) Toroidally dominated white dwarf&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1: Gravitational wave S/N as a function of integration time for a white dwarf with central density= 2 × 10&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; g cm&lt;sup&gt;−3&lt;/sup&gt;. The thick orange line corresponds to &amp;lt;S/N&amp;gt; ≈ 5.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gravitational wave astronomy is also helpful to resolve the dichotomy of some other objects too. There are some isolated compact objects, named &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.physics.mcgill.ca/~pulsar/magnetar/main.html&quot;&gt;soft gamma repeater~(SGR) and anomalous X-ray pulsar~(AXP)&lt;/a&gt;, which are mostly believed to be neutron stars as they are found to be associated with supernova remnants. However, some of them do not have a supernova remnant association, and their magnetic field is also unknown. Hence, some researchers have also shown that some of their features can be explained assuming they are white dwarfs. To resolve this controversy, the researchers have shown that gravitational wave astronomy is also a helpful tool. It was shown that if they are neutron stars, no proposed gravitational wave detector can detect them. On the other hand, if they are white dwarfs, they can be detected by BBO and DECIGO detectors within 1 year of detection period. The exact time needed for the detection is dependent on the magnetic field configuration and its strength (Fig. 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_to_resolve_dichotomy_of_compact_objects_surajit_images/image_2a.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(a) Poloidally dominated white dwarf.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_to_resolve_dichotomy_of_compact_objects_surajit_images/image_2b.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(b) Toroidally dominated white dwarf&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_to_resolve_dichotomy_of_compact_objects_surajit_images/image_2c.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(c)  Neutron star with radius 14 km.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 2:  Gravitational wave S/N as a function of integration time for 1RXS J170849.0−400910. In the parentheses of parts (a) and (b), the radius of the white dwarf in the units of km is mentioned. For part (c), in the parentheses, the dominant magnetic field configuration in neutron star is mentioned.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, gravitational wave astronomy will be a useful tool to resolve dichotomy related to various compact objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/508/1/842/6371126&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Resolving dichotomy in compact objects through continuous gravitational waves observation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Surajit Kalita&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tushar Mondal, Christopher A. Tout, Tomasz Bulik, Banibrata Mukhopadhyay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://iisc.ac.in/&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_compact_objects_surajit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_compact_objects_surajit</guid>
        
        <category>Gravitational waves</category>
        
        <category>Neutron Stars</category>
        
        <category>White dwarfs</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Magnetic Field Measurements of the Solar Corona by Aditya L1</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the science goals of the Aditya L1 is to map the coronal magnetic field topology. The infrared channel of the VELC payload of the Aditya L1 is equipped with a spectropolarimeter to perform full stokes spectropolarimetric observations in the Fe XIII 1074.7 nm line to measure the vector magnetic field. This article discusses the design and the working of the spectropolarimeter of the VELC. This article also discusses the challenges associated with the spectropolarimeter of the VELC, which are to optimize the data volume to be sent to the ground as no onboard data processing is planned, and the other is to account for the change in polarimeter characteristic due to mismatch in retarder rotation frequency and the length of signal detection time.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.isro.gov.in/aditya-l1-first-indian-mission-to-study-sun&quot;&gt;Aditya L1&lt;/a&gt; is the first Indian space-based Solar observatory that will continuously observe the Sun to study coronal heating, solar wind acceleration, coronal magnetometry, origin, and monitoring of near-UV solar radiation. It is equipped with seven payloads. One of the payloads is Visible Emission Line Coronagraph (VELC), developed by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA)&lt;/a&gt; to study the diagnostic parameters of solar corona and dynamics and origin of Coronal Mass Ejections and magnetic field measurement of the solar corona.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A coronagraph is a telescopic instrument that blocks the light of a star so that the nearby objects which would otherwise be hidden in the star’s glare be resolved. A solar coronagraph occults the bright solar disc to resolve the corona. The VELC is equipped with a spectrograph as a backend instrument. A spectrograph disperses the polychromatic light and records the intensities over a range of wavelengths called the spectrum. We study the properties of the spectrum to estimate the plasma parameters like velocity, electron density, temperature, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/coronal_magnetic_field_measurement_velc_aditya_l1_harsh_images/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1: A &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_Angle_and_Spectrometric_Coronagraph&quot;&gt;LASCO&lt;/a&gt; C2 Coronagraph. LASCO consists of three coronagraphs (C1/C2/C3) onboard NASA’s Solar and Heliospheric Observatory satellite.&lt;br /&gt;
Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swpc.noaa.gov/products/lasco-coronagraph&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VELC is designed to record spectra simultaneously in three spectral lines at 530.3 nm due to Fe XIV (green channel), 789.2 nm due to Fe XI (red channel), and 1074.7 nm due to Fe XIII (IR channel). It is a multi-slit spectrograph (4 equispaced slits) covering the FOV up to 1.5R⊙, where R⊙ is the radius of the Sun. The IR channel is equipped with a polarimeter to carry out full Stokes polarimetric observations of the Fe XIII line. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polarization_(waves)&quot;&gt;polarisation&lt;/a&gt; of electromagnetic waves refers to the path or the locus of the electric field vector. If the electric field oscillates in a single direction, it is called linear polarisation. If the electric field rotates in a circular plane as the light travels forward, it is called circular polarisation. The plasma’s magnetic field information is encoded in the polarisation of the spectral lines via the Zeeman effect and the Hanle effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/quantum/zeeman.html&quot;&gt;Zeeman effect&lt;/a&gt; is the splitting of the spectral line in the presence of an external magnetic field. The Zeeman splitting of the spectral line gives rise to three spectral components, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sun.stanford.edu/~sasha/PHYS780/SOLAR_PHYSICS/L5/Lecture_05_PHYS780.pdf&quot;&gt;𝞼+, 𝞼-, and 𝜋 components&lt;/a&gt;, which are right circularly polarised, left circularly polarised, and linearly polarised, respectively. If the magnetic field is along the line of sight, in that case, only the 𝞼+, 𝞼- components are observed. If the magnetic field is perpendicular to the line of sight (LOS), all three components are observed as linearly polarised. Also, the separation between these components, an observable quantity, is directly related to the magnitude of the magnetic field. Hence by measuring the polarisation in spectral lines, we can estimate both the magnitude and the direction of the magnetic field in the solar atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/coronal_magnetic_field_measurement_velc_aditya_l1_harsh_images/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 2: Subfigure (a) shows the break in the degeneracy between magnetic sublevels in the presence of an external magnetic field, and this break or split of the levels produces three spectral components (𝞼+, 𝞼-, and 𝜋). In subfigure (b), we see if the magnetic field is perpendicular to LOS, then 𝞼+, 𝞼-, and 𝜋 components are observed as linearly polarized. In the subfigure (c), the magnetic field direction is into the plane of the screen (i.e., along the line of sight), therefore only 𝞼+, 𝞼- components are observed as right and left circularly polarized respectively.&lt;br /&gt;
Image courtesy: Author
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hanle effect is observed when the splitting or separation between energy levels of a spectral line, in the presence of an external magnetic field, is less than or equal to the natural width of that line. The anisotropic radiation coming from the underlying photosphere or chromosphere gets scattered by the atoms in the upper layers like the transition region and corona (TR-corona). This scattering process leads to linear polarization of the emitted spectral lines. This is valid even when there is no external magnetic field. Now, in the weak magnetic field regions such as TR-corona (where expected field strength is 1 to 300 Gauss), there will be a modification of the scattering or linear polarization as well as rotation of the plane of linear polarization of the emitted lines. This effect of modification in the line polarization is called the Hanle effect. By measuring this change in the polarization of the lines, the weak magnetic field can be estimated in the TR-corona of the sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As described above, we can estimate the magnetic field in the solar atmosphere by measuring the polarization in spectral lines. A polarimeter is an instrument used to measure polarization. A polarimeter consists of a polarization modulator and a linear polarizer/analyzer. First, the unpolarized light from the Sun enters the polarization modulator which changes the state of input polarization. Then the polarized light from the modulator enters the linear polarizer which cuts the intensity of light perpendicular to its orientation. Hence, we measure at the detector the intensity allowed by the linear polarizer, which in turn depends on the output from the polarization modulator, which in turn depends on the polarization state of the input light of the Sun. By measuring at the detector the output intensity of the incident light of the Sun through the polarimeter and knowing the characteristics of the polarimeter, we can estimate the input polarization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/coronal_magnetic_field_measurement_velc_aditya_l1_harsh_images/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 3: Figure showing a Retarder acting as a Polarization Modulator and Linear polarizer acting as an analyzer.&lt;br /&gt;
Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/introduction-to-spectropolarimetry/78F63E2346A17DA2D401DF3A7D180F49&quot;&gt;Introduction to Spectropolarimetry&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VELC polarimeter consists of a continuously rotating wave plate (RWP) followed by a polarizing beam displacer (PBD) as the polarization analyzer. The PBD produces two beams that are orthogonally polarized, which are simultaneously recorded by the detector. This setup is commonly known as a dual-beam polarimeter. The main advantage of dual-beam setup is to reduce the spurious polarisation, i.e., cross-talk from Stokes I to Q, U, and V. The light enters the polarimeter setup (RWP + PBD), and a frame is recorded on the detector. Then RWP is rotated by an angle, and another frame is recorded. To measure the four Stokes parameters (I, Q, U, and V), a minimum of 4 such measurements, called samples, are required at different orientations of RWP. This is called modulation of the polarization state of light. One modulation cycle constitutes 4 samples per half rotation of the wave plate, so one complete rotation of the RWP provides 2 modulation cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the limited number of photons in the solar corona, large integration times are required to build the required signal-to-noise ratio. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signal-to-noise_ratio&quot;&gt;Signal to noise ratio&lt;/a&gt; (SNR) is the ratio of the desired signal strength to the background noise level. When SNR is low, we need to add the signal for many time intervals (integration time), which adds up the signal and reduces or cancels the noise as the noise is assumed random. It poses several challenges concerning the polarimeter of the VELC. One of them is the increased data volume to be sent to the ground station as no on-board data processing is planned. The second is the change in the polarimeter characteristic. In typical polarimeters, first RWP rotates, then the detector frame is recorded, However, in the case of VELC, the RWP rotates, and the detector records independently of each other. There is a mismatch between the retarder’s rotation frequency and the length of the signal detection time, which causes a change in the characteristic of the polarimeter after one cycle of measurements. Nagaraju and the team discuss the above problems and suggest a potential solution to optimize the data volume and account for the change in polarimeter characteristics in successive modulation cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To optimize the data volume, Nagaraju and the team discuss the optimal efficiencies of measuring Stokes parameters as a function of the number of samples per half rotation (n) of the wave plate (RWP) and provide efficiencies when the retarder’s rotation frequency does not match the signal detection time. They find that efficiency slowly increases with an increase in the number of samples per half rotation of the wave plate. They find that the increase in efficiency of measuring Stokes I and Stokes U is close to 10% for the case of n=5 to n=95, for Stokes Q, it is about 8%, and for Stokes V, it is about 4%. However, as the number of samples per half rotation will increase from n=5 to n=95, the data size will proportionally increase, and this will offset any gains in efficiency. They estimate the data size of 3.14 Mb per second for n=4 to 74.19 Mb per second for n=95. Hence they suggest that the number of modulation steps or the samples per half rotation be chosen by considering the data volume and other measurement aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/coronal_magnetic_field_measurement_velc_aditya_l1_harsh_images/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApOpt..60.8145N/abstract&quot;&gt;Original article&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nagaraju and the team discuss the change in the elements of polarimeter characteristics with time to understand the effect of the mismatch between retarder rotation frequency and signal detection time. They model this change for the different number of samples per half rotation of the wave plate. They find a cyclical/periodic variation in the elements with time. They find that the larger the time difference between the retarder rotation frequency and signal detection time, the faster is the variation in the elements of polarimeter characteristics with time. Despite the significant variation in individual elements, the efficiency of measuring Stokes parameters does not change significantly throughout integration time. They suggest this change in the elements of the polarimeter characteristics can be taken into account through calibration. They notice that the elements corresponding to measuring Stokes Q and Stokes U vary two times faster than elements corresponding to measuring Stokes V. Hence, recording the calibration data to cover one entire cycle within which elements of polarimeter characteristics corresponding to measuring Stokes V complete one period of variation may suffice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/coronal_magnetic_field_measurement_velc_aditya_l1_harsh_images/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApOpt..60.8145N/abstract&quot;&gt;Original article&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, they find that the data volume can be optimized by choosing an appropriate number of samples per half rotation of the wave plate (RWP) without significantly affecting the efficiency of the Stokes parameters. The variation of elements of polarimeter characteristic with time is also addressed due to a mismatch between the retarder rotation frequency and signal detection time, and a potential solution is suggested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgment&quot;&gt;Acknowledgment:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank Raveena Khan, JRF, IIA, for helping simplify the explanation of the Hanle effect and doing the the editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApOpt..60.8145N/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Spectropolarimeter on board the Aditya-L1: polarization modulation and demodulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; K. Nagaraju&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; B. Raghavendra Prasad, Bhavana S. Hegde, Suresh Venkata Narra, D. Utkarsha, Amit Kumar, and Varun Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/coronal_magnetic_field_measurement_velc_aditya_l1_harsh/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/coronal_magnetic_field_measurement_velc_aditya_l1_harsh/</guid>
        
        <category>Spectropolarimeter</category>
        
        <category>Aditya-L1</category>
        
        <category>VELC</category>
        
        
        <category>Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Deciphering The Mysteries of The Quiet Sun Explosions</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;XSM onboard Chandrayaan 2 observed the Sun during its minimum activity period in 2019-2020. Using this data, the researchers have for the first time detected a very large number of small scale explosions, called microflares, happening on the Sun. The physical parameters of the microflares have been calculated and their spatial location is also detected using various satellites. The study also gives evidence that such small scale heating events occur everywhere on the Sun and they contribute to coronal heating.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outer atmosphere (the corona) of the Sun poses a long standing mystery regarding its temperature. The solar corona is composed of plasma (ionised gas) that emits strongly in X-rays and ultraviolet radiation. Its temperature exceeds a million degree kelvin, while the visible surface (the photosphere) is at 6000K. One of the theories to understand the so-called ‘coronal heating problem’ proposes the occurrence of a large number of small scale explosions (known as microflares and nanoflares) on the Sun. It is known that these flares are a manifestation of the magnetic field of the Sun that is generated in its interior. But the Sun’s magnetic field is not constant, it varies with an average period of 11 years, which is known as the solar cycle. Approximately every 11 years, the Sun’s magnetic field reverses. In other words, the north pole becomes the south pole, and vice versa. The flip of the poles is an end product of the slow evolution of Sun’s magnetic field over time. As the cycle progresses, all of the Sun’s activities related to its magnetic field (such as sunspots, flares, coronal mass ejections) builds to a maximum (when the magnetic field reverses). Then the Sun settles back down to a minimum, before the whole cycle starts again. The Sun was in a very low state of activity during the minima of solar cycle 24 covering the year 2019. It was in fact the quietest the Sun has been in the last 100 years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this quiet period of the Sun, at the mid of the year 2019, Chandrayaan 2 was launched with the several instruments/payloads to observed our moon and the Sun. Among them CLASS is an instrument to understand the abundance of elements present on the moon. But this requires knowledge of the X-rays emitted from the Sun. Thus, the orbiter also carried an instrument called Solar X-ray  Monitor (XSM). XSM observed the Sun during its deepest minima of solar cycle 24, covering the year 2019-2020 with a good temporal and energy resolution. Using observations during this time, Santosh Vadawale and his team has uncovered some fascinating information about the quiescent Sun. They have shown that during this period small scale transients, so-called microflares (smaller counterpart of the conventional solar flares) are occurring everywhere on the solar disk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solar flares are eruptions of electromagnetic radiation of all wavelengths from the Sun. They last from a few minutes to a few hours. Flares are classified depending on the energy they release during its peak in the soft X rays. Though the number of large flares increase with the progress of the solar cycle, this study suggested that small flares, called microflares, keep exploding on the Sun at all times. Though the definition of microflares has varied though the years due to the sensitivity of the instrument, in this study flares having a peak flux below 10&lt;sup&gt;-8&lt;/sup&gt; W/m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; are considered as microflares. During this period of extremely quiet solar corona when no active regions were present on the disk, Santosh Vadawale and team identified a total of 98 microflares from 76 days. The microflares are marked in the lightcurve (Figure 1). Most of the microflares were seen to behave similar to larger flares having a fast rise and a slow decay. Some microflares did not follow this behaviour possibly due to blending of multiple microflares or they intrinsically have a different origin. The temperature and emission measure of these microflares are determined. Temperature tells how hot the plasma gets during the explosion while the emission measure gives an idea about the density of plasma emitted at that particular temperature. The temperature is found to be between 3-6 MK and the emission measure is in the order of 10&lt;sup&gt;46&lt;/sup&gt; cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/mysteries_quiet_sun_explosions_lakshitha/image1_lakshitha.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: XSM lightcurve during the period of deepest solar minima of the past century. Red vertical lines indicate the detected microflares outside the conventional active regions.
Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16644.pdf&quot;&gt;S.Vadawale et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The XSM microflare locations are identified in the extreme ultraviolet images obtained from NASA’s ‘Solar Dynamics Observatory’ and from the X-ray images obtained by the Japanese HINODE X-ray Telescope. Most microflares were seen to be associated with X-ray Bright Points. ‘Solar Dynamics Observatory’ HMI magnetograms were used to analyse the corresponding photospheric magnetic field. They observed the microflares to be associated with magnetic bipolar regions having  weaker field strengths, which indicates magnetic reconnection happening at smaller scales (Figure 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/mysteries_quiet_sun_explosions_lakshitha/image2_lakshitha.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: Identification of the location of one of the XSM microflares with the 1–5 keV light curve shown in panel (a). Flare location is marked on the SDO AIA 94 &amp;Aring; full disk image in (b) and a 5’ × 5’ cutout is shown in panel (c). Panel (d) shows AIA 94 &amp;Aring; light curve for the flaring pixels as shown in panel f. FeXVIII image of the flare location is shown in panel (e) and the map of pixels of the flaring plasma based on FeXVIII emission is given in panel (f). Available synoptic HMI magnetograms and XRT Be-thin images nearest to the flare peak time are shown in panels g-j.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16644.pdf&quot;&gt;S.Vadawale et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also the first statistical survey of X-ray microflares outside active regions. By plotting the frequency distribution of microflares, the team has given evidence for the hypothesis that small scale heating events occur everywhere on the Sun and they contribute to coronal heating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/abf0b0&quot;&gt; Observations Of The Quiet Sun During The Deepest Solar Minimum Of The PastCentury With Chandrayaan-2 XSM – Sub-A Class Microflares Outside Active Regions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Santosh Vadawale&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; N. P. S. Mithun, Biswajit Mondal, Aveek Sarkar, P.Janardhan, Bhuwan Joshi, Anil Bhardwaj, M. Shanmugam, Arpit R. Patel, Hitesh Kumar L. Adalja, Shiv Kumar Goyal, Tinkal Ladiya, Neeraj Kumar Tiwari, Nishant Singh and Sushil Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad, Gujarat-380 009, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/lakshitha_solar_article_corona</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lakshitha_solar_article_corona</guid>
        
        <category>sun</category>
        
        <category>corona</category>
        
        <category>flares</category>
        
        <category>x-ray</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The First Theoretical Model of the Near-Surface Shear Layer of the Sun</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is well known that the Sun rotates differentially, i.e. its equator rotates faster than the pole. Not only at the surface, but the solar rotation profile also varies with the radius, which was discovered in helioseismic observation. This observation reveals an exciting feature close to the visible solar surface that the rotation profile of the Sun changes very sharply, which is named as Near-Surface Shear Layer (NSSL). In this work astronomers from ARIES and IISc have given the theoretical explanation for the existence of NSSL very the first time. They have used the thermal wind balance equation to explain the existence of NSSL.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun, our life-giving star, has always been a star of many interests. Its importance for the living beings made many astronomers turn their telescope towards the Sun just after the advent of the telescope by Galileo Galilei. The early and regular observations of the Sun revealed the presence of dark spots, now known as sunspots, and 11 years of periodic variation in their number of appearances, popularly known as the solar cycle. The systematic observations of sunspots also show that the solar surface rotates &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Differential_rotation&quot;&gt;differentially&lt;/a&gt;, which means the equator of the Sun spins faster than its pole. However, the internal rotation of the Sun has only been revealed after the &lt;a href=&quot;http://soi.stanford.edu/results/heliowhat.html&quot;&gt;helioseismology&lt;/a&gt; (technique of using sound waves to peek inside the Sun) era. Helioseismology has answered the many puzzling questions about the Sun while raising many questions about our nearest star at the same time. One of the crucial observations that helioseismology has made was the existence of the near-surface shear layer (NSSL).  The NSSL is the region very close to the visible solar surface, where there is a sharp change in the rotation profile of the Sun. The understanding of NSSL is crucial for the Sun, but it will also help us understand the other stars. Many researchers had indicated the presence of such a layer in the past based on solar surface observations but the real inference has been provided only after helioseismic measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in this work, researchers from ARIES, Nainital and IISc Bangalore have given the theoretical explanation for the existence of NSSL, for the very first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their study used the thermal wind balance equation, which tells about how the slight difference in temperature between solar poles and equator, which is called thermal wind term, is balanced by the centrifugal force appearing due to solar differential rotation. Now, the question is, why are they expecting the solar pole to have a slightly higher temperature? To understand this, we have to think about the motion of plasma blobs or convective blobs in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://solarscience.msfc.nasa.gov/interior.shtml&quot;&gt;solar convection zone&lt;/a&gt; in which heat is transported by convection in the same way as it is transported in boiling water. Unlike boiling water, the Sun is rotating, and hence the upward moving blobs will experience &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coriolis_force&quot;&gt;Coriolis force&lt;/a&gt;. The effect of Coriolis force is zero on blobs moving along the axis of rotation (as in the case of a pole) and will be maximum when they are moving perpendicular to it (as in the case of the equator). Therefore, the heat transfer will be more efficient along the axis of rotation, leading to a higher temperature near the pole which drives the plasma from pole to equator. Another term is called centrifugal, which arises due to solar differential rotation driving the plasma in the opposite direction that is equator to pole. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://solarscience.msfc.nasa.gov/interior.shtml&quot;&gt;temperature profile of the Sun&lt;/a&gt; shows a sharp decrease near the visible surface and authors have shown that the pole-equator temperature difference also decreases as we approach the surface. To balance these effects Solar rotation profile (centrifugal term) has to change sharply, giving rise to NSSL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most scientists believe that this condition is valid only in the interior of the Sun, and it does not hold near the solar surface. In their work, the authors have shown that this belief actually holds near the surface as well. They have noted that if this condition is true near the solar surface it can explain the existence of NSSL which is inferred in helioseismology based observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/solar_theoretical_model_bibhuti/bibhuti_final.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig.: The solar rotation profile calculated based on the theoretical model given by &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stab1717&quot;&gt; Jha et al. (2021)&lt;/a&gt;. The solid black and dashed red contours are the contours of constant angular rotation based on the model and observation, respectively.


&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stab1717&quot;&gt; The First Theoretical Model of the Near-Surface Shear Layer of the Sun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Bibhuti Kumar Jha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Arnab Rai Choudhuri&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bangalore 560034, Karnataka, India;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences, Nainital 263001, Uttarakhand, India;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pondicherry University, Chinna Kalapet, Kalapet, Puducherry 605014, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/theoretical-model-shear-layer-bibhuti</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/theoretical-model-shear-layer-bibhuti</guid>
        
        <category>Sun; Differential Rotation; NSSL; Theory</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Classical Ae stars: What are they? Why study them?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Starting from the history of star classification in the millinniums, this interesting note will take you through some of the very basic concepts on emission-line stars. You will be able to understand what they are and why these type of stars are my special children. The article will pose a number of very fundamental yet unresolved questions on these groups waiting to be unraveled from the nature. PS: You will not regret opening this link!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ae_stars_anusha/image1_anusha.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: The most comprehensive Hubble deep field image of the evolving universe.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hubblesite.org&quot;&gt;Hubblesite &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Author’s note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I can stare all day at the image above showing details of a large number of Galaxies and stars which are the building blocks of the visible universe we know. The expanding universe, the infrared afterglow, litter from the most distant parts of our universe, remind me of the nearer still, the largely unaffected bounty of the space in my presence. Even being an ignorant survival,  these depths and darkness leading one to their origin are intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to understand a system is to observe and question their behavior leading to logical  reasons. In this manner, for ages, many incredible minds have corroborated the nature of stars,  observed them over years, mapped their positions to good accuracy, and questioned their fundamentals, for many which even today we do not know answers to. As a first step towards this process, we explore the different types of stars and their nature using the stellar spectral classification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stellar-classification&quot;&gt;Stellar classification:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oldest ever known catalogue of stars in the sky dates back to the 2nd millennium BC (1531- 1155 BC), which upgraded in number over years. But, the catalogued stars were classified into different categories based on their observable properties only by the late 19th century. Through observations, we understand that stars differ in colour and temperature. To understand these observable differences, we categorized stars based on their temperature into different ‘stellar spectral types’, assigning one alphabet for each class. The sequence of stars presently adopted,  begins with the hottest stars, class O, and proceeds from hot to cool in the order: O, B, A, F, G,  K, and M. Most of the stars in the visible universe can be classified into one of these groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ae_stars_anusha/image3_anusha.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: The HR-diagram of stellar classifications. The X-axis shows different spectral types from hot massive O stars to cooler M stars.
Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.astronomytrek.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/Star-Classification-Chart.jpg&quot;&gt; Astronomytrek &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hot massive stars usually include stars in the spectral type range O to A. It is interesting though that the physical properties, internal structure, chemical nature, and the observables of hotter stars are very different from that of their cooler counterparts. A special category of these hot stars is the emission-line stars which show prominent emission features in their spectrum. A  closer look into this category reveals that not all hot massive stars show emission-line signatures. To date, we have insufficient details to explain why this nature is not universal. Many interesting studies have been conducted to date in examining the observational properties and statistical nature of these emission-line stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-do-we-know-about-emission-line-stars&quot;&gt;What do we know about emission-line stars?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, the term &lt;em&gt;emission-line stars&lt;/em&gt; (ELS) denote stellar objects that show emission features in their spectrum. In general, hot ELS include Classical Ae/Be type stars,  Herbig Ae/Be type stars, Wolf-Rayet stars, supergiants, etc. The mechanism of the emission-line formation differs between each of these classes.
Taking into consideration Classical Ae/Be stars, a group of ELS enclosing hot massive Oe, Be,  and Ae stars (where ‘e’ stands for emission). The emission lines in this group of stars are known to originate from a cooler disk-shaped envelope surrounding the star. The disk is composed of ionized gas and surrounds the star equatorially. The mechanism of such a gaseous equatorial  disk formation is termed the Be phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ae_stars_anusha/image2_anusha.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: An artistic impression of a Classical Be star. Note the presence of a circumstellar envelope in the shape of a disk surrounding the star.
Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Be_star&quot;&gt;Wikimedia commons  &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;classical-be-and-classical-ae-stars&quot;&gt;Classical Be and Classical Ae stars&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, I consider Classical Be (CBe hereafter) and Classical Ae (CAe hereafter)  stars as one of the very interesting classes of objects. After 150+ years of their first detection, these stars still pose a great challenge in understanding them completely. The most fundamental (yet unresolved) question about these stars is that, &lt;em&gt;Why do these stars form a circumstellar disk?&lt;/em&gt; It has to be noted that not all B-type stars are CBe stars, not all A-type stars CAe stars. Why do we see a selection for this emission mechanism in nature?. The better we study these stars in detail,  the better we get to understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research article titled &lt;em&gt;Identification of new Classical Ae stars in the Galaxy using LAMOST DR5&lt;/em&gt; intends at compiling the very first homogeneous catalogue of the CAe stars from our  Galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;identification-of-classical-ae-stars&quot;&gt;Identification of Classical Ae stars.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article makes use of one of the largest spectroscopic databases of the Galaxy – Large sky  Area Multi-Object fibre Spectroscopic Telescope (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lamost.org/public/?locale=en&quot;&gt;LAMOST&lt;/a&gt;), undertaken by the Chinese academy of sciences, situated at Xinglong Station, China. They identified about 4,789 A-type  emission-line stars (Hα shows emission profile) from the LAMOST database. As quoted  previously, many types of objects can show this emission feature. To identify the CAe stars, they made use of the infra-red photometric properties. The idea behind this selection is that the circumstellar disk of CBe/CAe stars will give rise to additional flux excess in the infrared region of the electromagnetic spectrum. By filtering out stars showing this additional flux, the team  identified 159 new CAe stars from the Galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cbe-stars-versus-cae-stars&quot;&gt;CBe stars versus CAe stars&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Figure. 2 we understand that A-type stars are comparatively cooler than B-type stars.  Hence, the CAe stars are considered cooler counterparts of CBe stars. Though these systems show a similar presence of circumstellar disk, it is important to understand how their disk properties change concerning their temperature.
This study provides a dedicated section on comparing the observed spectroscopic features of  CBe stars and the CAe stars. They were able to predict that the CAe stars could host smaller disks compared to CBe stars. Apart from hydrogen, this study identified the presence of ionized metallic lines of FeII, Ca II, OI, etc in the spectra of the CAe stars and that these features are similar to that of CBe stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article provided new insights on the nature of the CAe stars and motivates the research community to study further study and compare them to CBe stars for a better understanding of the Be phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021MNRAS.501.5927A/abstract&quot;&gt; Identification of new classical Ae stars in the Galaxy using LAMOST DR5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Anusha.R&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Blesson Mathew, B.Shridharan.; R.Arun, S.Nidhi, Gourav Banerjee, Sreeja S Kartha, K.T.Paul, Suman Bhattacharyya&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt;  Department of Physics and Electronics, CHRIST (Deemed to be University), Bangalore 560029, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/classical-ae-stars-anusha</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/classical-ae-stars-anusha</guid>
        
        <category>emission-line</category>
        
        <category>stars</category>
        
        <category>circumstellar matter</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Twinkle twinkle little stars, should I wonder what you are? A brief account of variable stars</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Curiosity is what has driven mankind to observations of new phenomena. Every twinkling star in the night sky is definitely not due to the atmospheric refraction of earth. Rather, one might be looking at a variable star, each with a different origin story to tell. A study of variable stars enhances our understanding of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-introduction&quot;&gt;1.	Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first nursery rhymes I might have been introduced to was the popular rhyme, “Twinkle twinkle little star”. Over the years, the verse took a different form once we were introduced to the astronomically correct idea of a star. Now the rhyme reads somewhat like below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Twinkle twinkle little star&lt;br /&gt;
You look small cause you are far&lt;br /&gt;
Lightyears out from here to there&lt;br /&gt;
Your light is distorted by the air&lt;br /&gt;
So you twinkle twinkle little star&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elementary physics lectures have introduced us to the idea of atmospheric refraction, due to which observed starlight seems to vary in intensity. This phenomenon of twinkling is attributed to the varying densities of the atmosphere. However, not all twinkling stars attribute their twinkle to atmospheric refraction. Some twinkle due to their inherent properties. Such stars are called variable stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time scales associated with stellar evolution are generally so large that the Universe has been traditionally viewed as a static phenomenon. However, we have long known short human time scale events, such as Solar System events and stellar explosions. With the advent of robotically controlled telescopes and high cadence near all-sky monitoring in the last decade of the 1990s, the study of astronomical events on ever shorter time scales has exploded. With access to this new stream of data, our understanding of many phenomena has increased significantly. However, the number of unanswered questions have increased multiple times. One such question addressed the dilemma of why many celestial bodies varied in their brightness. This led to the study in the field of Time-Domain Astronomy and variable stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-time-domain-astronomy&quot;&gt;2.	Time Domain Astronomy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time domain astrophysics is a field of observational astronomy that studies the universe on all timescales from less than milliseconds to more than decades and at all wavelengths. This became possible due to the availability of great detectors and computing advances over the past decades. The idea of observations and analysis have now moved beyond the one-off photographic surveys in the past. Beginning from the 1990s, the MACHO(massive astrophysical compact halo object), OGLE(Optical Gravitational Lensing Experiment), and SuperWASP projects used large field of view, highly sensitive cameras on manual or robotic optical or near-infrared telescopes and obtained deep digital images of large swathes of the sky. These scans were repeated to build up vast databases of time-resolved images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were to describe the elementary ideas of time-domain astronomy, we could explain it in the following manner. Observe a particular section of the sky. Note the physical limits visible in that section. After some time t, observe the area under consideration. If any of the physical quantities have changed from earlier, we tag the particular body in the database for future study. The time it takes for the instrument to re-observe the same patch of sky is referred to as the “cadence.” The old strategy of looking deep and far into the Universe is used, and sources of a given brightness methodically mapped out in a three dimensional volume. In time-domain astronomy, sources that vary by some brightness with a rate equal to the inverse of the instrument cadence can be steadily mapped out. In a way, the time-domain adds another dimension, given by the frequency equal to the inverse cadence, to the properties of observed phenomena. The study of variable stars is an essential section of time-domain astronomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-variable-stars&quot;&gt;3.	Variable Stars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Omicron Ceti was the first variable star to be identified in 1596 by David Fabricius. Johannes Holwards observed Omicron Ceti pulsating in a regular 11-month cycle in 1638. This discovery debunked the theory that the stars were eternal and invariable as ancient philosophers such as Aristotle had believed.
Variable stars change in brightness over time. These changes can vary from as small as a few parts in a million or by a considerable factor. The changes observed can also range from a few milliseconds to a few years or decades, for that matter. Since many astronomical bodies can qualify as a “variable star”, an array of techniques are devised to discover and analyse the possibility of a variable star. The next obvious question is on the importance of studying variable stars. The study is of importance as the variations provide unique insights about nature, the origins, evolution and often the future trajectory of the star under observance. This information helps us deduce more fundamental knowledge about our universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variations may be due to the rotational motion executed by a spotted star, or due to a star being eclipsed by its companion star, or even by an unseen planet. The variations may also be due to the vibrations of a star. If these vibrations are complex, we might be able to get a rough picture of the internal structure and composition of this star. The variations may be due to eruptions on a star (flares), or an accretion disc (dwarf novae) or major explosions on a star (novae), or to the total disruption of a star in a supernova. Supernovae are one of the most violent incidents in the known universe. However, the existence of life is an indirect result of supernovae. They help to recycle the atoms created in stars into space. Some of these atoms became part of the Sun, others into planets, and for that matter, even the biosphere. It is deduced that the elements heavier than iron were mostly created in the supernova explosion. Supernovae may be dramatic and extreme, but they represent only one of the many roles that variable stars play in modern astrophysics and in our understanding of the universe and the processes which govern it. The organised study and recording of observations led to the establishment of the Variable Star Section of the British Astronomical Association (BAAVSS) in 1890, followed soon after by the establishment of variable star studies at Harvard College Observatory, which eventually led to the founding of the American Association of Variable Star Observers (AAVSO) in 1911.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-classification-of-variable-stars&quot;&gt;4.	Classification of Variable Stars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The General Catalogue of Variable Stars (GCVS) recommends an official classification system of variable stars based on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Light Curve&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Temperature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Luminosity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Population type&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this system, a family tree of variable stars can be constructed. Such a tree is called a Variability Tree. A simplified version of the variability tree is given below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/twinkle_twinkle_little_star_robin_thomas_images/Image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1: Variability tree, denoting the various classes of variable stars. The image can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://starlifecycleastro.weebly.com/variable-stars.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The variable stars are classified into two groups based on the reason of variability in the observed intensities, Intrinsic and Extrinsic variable stars. They are further categorised into sub-classes, which are discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-intrinsic-variable-stars&quot;&gt;5.	Intrinsic Variable Stars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intrinsic variable stars vary their light output, hence their brightness, due to the physical variation in the star or stellar system. This type of star provides a large amount of information about the internal structure of the star that helps astronomers to model the stellar evolution. Pulsating stars and eruptive or cataclysmic variable stars belong to this category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;51-pulsating-variable-stars&quot;&gt;5.1.	Pulsating Variable Stars&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pulsating variables are the stars that show periodic expansion and contraction of their surface layers. The change in brightness occurs due to the change in size or shape. Most of the pulsating stars simply expand and contract repeatedly in a continuing cycle of size changes and this is known as the fundamental mode of pulsation. Some of the changes not only in their size but also in their internal arrangement of material. Some others vibrate in more than one way at the same time and this makes the system complex. Like most vibrating systems, pulsating variables repeat their changes and they tend to be periodic. Depending on the period, on the mass and evolutionary status of the star, pulsating variables are classified into many categories. We shall discuss each sub-category briefly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;cepheid-variable-stars&quot;&gt;Cepheid variable stars&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cepheid variables form an important class of pulsating variables. These are large yellow stars pulsating with periods from 1 to 70 days, with an amplitude of light variation from 0.1 to 2 magnitudes. They are very bright objects and have periodic oscillations. Cepheid light curves are distinctive and show a rapid rise in brightness followed by a more gradual decline that is shaped like a shark fin. The spectral class of Cepheid actually changes as it pulsates, being about an F type at maximum luminosity and down to G or K at minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cepheids follow a period-luminosity relation. Period luminosity relationship states that ‘more luminous cepheids pulsated more slowly’. This concept was put forward by Henrietta Leavitt in 1912.
The period of cepheid can be calculated from its light curve which can be used to estimate the Cepheid’s luminosity. Knowing its magnitude and luminosity we can calculate the distance using the relation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;
m - M = 5 log(d/10)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; is the apparent magnitude, &lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; the absolute magnitude and &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; the distance to the star in parsecs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/twinkle_twinkle_little_star_robin_thomas_images/Image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2: Light curve of cepheid Delta Cephei. The image can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eso.org/public/outreach/eduoff/aol/market/collaboration/varstar/pg2.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;long-period-variables&quot;&gt;Long-period variables&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the largest population of pulsating variables are the long-period variables (LPVS). They are pulsating red giants or supergiants with periods ranging from 30 to 1000 days. Long-period variables are further subdivided into two major subclasses, the Mira type and the semiregular variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-mira-variable&quot;&gt;a.	Mira variable&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are periodic red giant variables that vary with periods of 80 to 1000 days in magnitudes as high as 2.5 in the visible bands. Mira type variables are red giant stars, often of enormous size. Their high luminosity means that they can be detected at large distances. Many of them are slowly ejecting a steady stream of matter into the surrounding space and this mass loss has dramatic consequences on their future evolution. They have weak outer layers in their atmosphere which gets heated from regular pulsations. These are interesting due to their similar size as the Sun and that they are undergoing a late stage of the same evolutionary path that all one-solar mass stars, including the Sun, will experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;b-semi-regular-variable&quot;&gt;b.	Semi-regular variable&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Semiregular variables are giants or supergiants which show appreciable periodicity accompanied by semiregular or irregular light variation. Their periods range from 30 to 1000 days, generally with amplitude variations of fewer than 2.5 magnitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;rr-lyrae&quot;&gt;RR Lyrae&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RR Lyrae stars are of short period (.05 to 1.2 days), pulsating white giant stars, usually of spectral class A. They are older and less massive than Cepheids. The amplitude of variation of RR Lyrae is generally from .3 to 2 magnitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;rv-tauri-star&quot;&gt;RV Tauri Star&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RV Tauri stars are yellow supergiants having a characteristic light variation with deep and shallow minima. Their periods, defined as the interval between two deep minima range from 30 to 150 days. They show brightness variations of up to 3 magnitudes. Some of these stars show long term cyclic variations from hundreds of thousands of days. Generally, their spectral class ranges from G to K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/twinkle_twinkle_little_star_robin_thomas_images/Image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 3: Light curve of RV Tauri star R Scuti. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R_Scuti&quot;&gt; Wikimedia commons &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;52-cataclysmic-variable-stars&quot;&gt;5.2.	Cataclysmic variable stars&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eruptive variables are stars varying in brightness because of violent outbursts caused by thermonuclear processes in their surface layers. They exhibit significant and rapid changes in their luminosity which is usually accompanied by mass outflow in the form of stellar winds of variable intensity. These are a system of two stars (binary system) orbiting very close to each other. One of them is a normal sunlike or giant star, while the other is a white dwarf. Some of the outermost material from the larger star is pulled away by the white dwarf’s gravity, but this material does not fall directly onto the white dwarf. Instead, it builds up in a disk called an accretion disk, which orbits the white dwarf. Thus, the eruptive variable star is a combination of normal or giant stars, white dwarf and accretion disk as shown in the following figure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/twinkle_twinkle_little_star_robin_thomas_images/Image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 4: A cataclysmic variable star. The image can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://astrosurf.com/vdesnoux/catvar/catvar.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combination of main-sequence or giant stars, white dwarf and accretion disk lead to celestial fireworks. So, instead of varying like pulsating variables, eruptive variables exhibit outbursts of activity. Some events may result in the destruction of the star while others can reoccur one or more times. These are called recurrent novae. The changes in their light curves are usually very unpredictable and tend to be sudden and dramatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;53-supernovae&quot;&gt;5.3.	Supernovae&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supernovae are examples of such cataclysmic variable stars. These occur either during the last evolutionary stages of a massive star or when a white dwarf is triggered into runaway nuclear fusion. The original object(progenitor) either collapses to a neutron star or black hole or gets destroyed. We will now look briefly into the types of supernovae.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;type-i-supernovae&quot;&gt;Type I supernovae&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These do not exhibit any hydrogen lines in spectra. Type Ia supernovae are understood to arise from white dwarf stars in a close binary system. As gas from the companion star accumulates on the white dwarf, the white dwarf is continuously undergoing compression. At the Chandrasekhar Limit, the white dwarf has accumulated too much mass to resist the force of gravity, thus setting off a runaway nuclear reaction inside. This leads to a cataclysmic supernova outburst. Type Ia supernovas are employed as “standard candles” to measure cosmic distances because they are believed to blaze with equal brightness at their peaks. Hence, they can be used as standard candles to determine the distance to a galaxy once the stretch factor is accounted for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;type-ii-supernovae&quot;&gt;Type II supernovae&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pre-requisite for a star to explode as a Type II supernova is that the star must be several times more massive than the sun (around 8 to 10 Msolar). Once the core of this star runs out of hydrogen and then helium at its core, it moves ahead with the nucleosynthesis process to create heavier metals. As a result, heavier elements accumulate at the centre, similar to a layered onion. Lighter elements are found in the outer regions of the star. Once the star’s core becomes heavier than the Chandrasekhar limit, the star begins to implode. This is why these supernovae are called core-collapse supernovae. Eventually, the core starts to heat up and becomes denser. The implosion bounces back off the core and expels the stellar material into space, forming the supernova. Type II supernovae show hydrogen lines in their early spectra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6-extrinsic-variable-stars&quot;&gt;6.	Extrinsic Variable Stars&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extrinsic variable stars are those in which the light output changes due to some process external to the star itself. The two main classes of extrinsic stars are the eclipsing binaries and rotating variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;61-eclipsing-binaries&quot;&gt;6.1.	Eclipsing binaries&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eclipsing binaries are binary star systems whose members eclipse each other, blocking one another’s light. As a result, the system looks occasionally fainter to observers on earth. The light curve of an eclipsing binary depends on the sizes and brightness of the stars, their separation from each other and the geometry of view from the earth. The process of eclipsing and the corresponding light curve of an eclipsing system is shown in the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/twinkle_twinkle_little_star_robin_thomas_images/Image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 5: Eclipsing binary star. The image can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifa.hawaii.edu/users/kud/teaching_15/6_DEB.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;62-rotating-star&quot;&gt;6.2.	Rotating star&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rotating variables are rapidly rotating stars, often in binary systems, that undergo small amplitude changes in light due to dark or bright spots on the star’s surface which is much similar to sunspots on the sun. Stars with sizeable sunspots show significant variations in brightness as they rotate. Stars that have ellipsoidal shapes also exhibit variation in brightness when they present varying areas of the surface to the observer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;7-conclusion&quot;&gt;7.	Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curiosity is what has driven mankind to observations of new phenomena. Every twinkling star in the night sky is definitely not due to the atmospheric refraction of earth. Rather, one might be looking at a variable star, each with a different origin story to tell. A study of variable stars enhances our understanding of the universe. Cepheid variables help in determining distances to galaxies and determining the age of the Universe. Mira variables help us in making an understanding of the future evolution of the Sun. Accretion disks in cataclysmic variables help us to understand the activity inside active galaxies with supermassive black holes. Type Ia supernovae have helped us conclude on the accelerated expansion of the Universe by acting as a standardisable candle. Transiting extrasolar planets provide clues into the processes of planetary formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This article is part of the author’s Masters dissertation)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/brief-account-variable-stars-robin</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/brief-account-variable-stars-robin</guid>
        
        <category>Variable stars</category>
        
        <category>transient events</category>
        
        <category>Light Curve</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
