<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> Welcome to CosmicVarta.</title>
    <description> Platform for promoting Indian astronomy research to the public.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 12:36:03 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 12:36:03 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bending of Cosmic fountains, giving birth to a peculiar X-shaped galaxy</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;When observed with a radio telescope, a giant peculiar X-shaped morphology is seen in some galaxies. It is difficult to understand what gives rise to such peculiar morphology; And, to date, this is a topic of debate among astronomers themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the supermassive black holes (SMBHs) that are billion times more massive than the sun reside at the centre of giant galaxies become active. During this active phase, the SMBH begins to rapidly accrete matter (hot ionized gas/plasma), some of which is violently thrown away along the SMBH’s spin axis by a complex process triggered by a strong magnetic disturbance. Hence, these active SMBHs usually throw jets of hot material out to large distances (out to a few billion light-years) with a velocity nearly the speed of light. These ejected jets resemble a structure that can very well be labelled as cosmic fountains. These jets typically consist of relativistic magnetised hot plasma (as the plasma is thrown, it also takes some of the magnetic field with it), which produce an outburst of radio emission via the synchrotron process. What’s surprising is that jet ejecta, which is expected to follow a particular path (a straight line; determined by the spin axis of the SMBH), sometimes bend from it and form a peculiar morphology that looks like the English letter ‘X’. So, when someone observes these galaxies with a radio telescope, they will find a giant X-like structure floating in the vast cosmos. It is difficult to understand what gives rise to such peculiar morphology; And, to date, this is a topic of debate among astronomers themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/x-galaxy-gourabg-images/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
&lt;p align = &quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: Radio map (at 23 cm) of a galaxy named PKS 2014-55 obtained from MeerKAT telescope, showing a peculiar X-structure. Here one pair of lobes is called the active lobe and the other pair is called the wing. The extent of the formed structure is ~ 3 million light-years, traced by the straight black line. The elliptical curve here mimics the elliptical galaxy that hosts the structure. &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/495/1/1271/5831730&quot;&gt;Cotton et al. 2020&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent study led by our team of astrophysicists including Indian and Italian scientists, have addressed this issue by re-investigating the formation mechanism of such structures computationally. We identified a possible origin hidden within the host galaxy shape itself. This is quite similar to the Bengali saying, &lt;em&gt;The ghost is already hiding in plain sight&lt;/em&gt;. Using computer simulations performed using the Max Planck supercomputing cluster in Germany, we demonstrated the complex relationship between the X-morphology formation and the shape of the host elliptical galaxy, which plays a key role in deflecting the material hurled out by the supermassive black hole. To be specific, the already existing interstellar gas distribution of the galaxy itself is found responsible for deflecting the ejected hot plasma by the black hole sideways, giving the cosmic fountain (the ejected jet) an X-shape. In scientific terms, we demonstrated that as the jet propagates through the denser interstellar gas distribution of the galaxy, the jet head becomes unstable. As a result, it creates lots of back-flowing plasma material that traverse back again towards the centre of the galaxy. While doing so, the host galaxy specifies a path for its motion by providing a path with a maximum pressure gradient (the pressure gradient generates a force), which lies along the minor axis of the galaxy (i.e., along the shorter dimension of an ellipse). This generated force causes a deflection in the back-flowing plasma, creating the wing structure. Observational studies often find such alignments of these back-flowing materials along the minor axis of the host galaxy, which further supports our findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/x-galaxy-gourabg-images/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
&lt;p align = &quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Here, we present our simulated X structure formed by the deflected, back-flowing plasma, generated from the jet head. The elliptical-shaped galaxy is visible in the top image. It is a 2D slice of our 3D simulation that is shown in the bottom image. The bottom image is a 3D velocity distribution plot seen from an angle to the y-axis. The blue and red colors here represent the velocity values that are +ve or -ve, representing forward or backward moving materials (to the y-axis).
&lt;/p&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our novel simulation has also shed light on a decade-old problem of these radio galaxies, which led our work towards a publication in a very prestigious European journal named Astronomy &amp;amp; Astrophysics by ESO (European Southern Observatory). The problem is noted below: Based on the properties of wing structure (which is less intense and rather diffuse than the active lobe), it was believed that the wing is a passively evolving feature (i.e., simply evolves under normal adiabatic expansion) compared to the active lobe, where the jet is currently in an active stage (by continuously filling itself with fresh and young plasma material from the SMBH). A similar characteristic has also been observed in our simulation showing the active lobe possessing freshly injected particles from the active galactic core, whereas the wing accumulates the older particles that back-flow from the jet head. Based on this, it can be stated that the active lobe should possess spectral index values flatter than the wing (flatter spectra mean younger particles; characteristics of synchrotron radiation). However, in observational studies, no systematic difference in the radio emission (hence in the spectral index) has been found in the four different arms of the X-shape. This further highlights that from a theoretical standpoint, there is a clear lag in the understanding of these galaxies’ emission processes, seriously contradicting the existing formation models. It has also led scientists to address these objects as peculiar sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work led by Gourab Giri and the team has offered a resolution to this issue with a critical analysis of these radio galaxies. They highlight that shock acceleration processes of ultra-fast electrons (travelling nearly at the speed of light!) cause such peculiar emission characteristics. A shock wave is a wave that is generated by a moving object when its speed of movement exceeds the speed of sound in that medium. In our work, we explicitly showed the origin of these shock waves in the four arms of X-shaped structure and hence their influence on the radio emission of such peculiar morphologies. The conclusion which came out from our work is that the shock acceleration significantly re-energizes the plasma by speeding them up (hence altering their spectra), keeping the particles alive which instead would have lost all their energy under several dominant cooling processes (radiative and adiabatic cooling). Most importantly, the wing, which was thought of as a passively growing structure of X-shaped galaxies, is actually very active as it produces shock acceleration sites in it. The shocks are generated due to the diverted back-flowing material, as also shown by the black arrow in Fig. 2, making the wing actively evolving. This can single-handedly explain the peculiar emission characteristics observed in X-shaped radio galaxies including the signature where no systematic difference in the emission of lobe and wing is found. Our work has already been appreciated by a greater scientific community. Additionally, the prestigious journal Astronomy &amp;amp; Astrophysics has also decided to feature our work on the cover page of their upcoming volume. This work is already available on the arXiv preprint server, handled by Cornell University, the USA for open-source science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2022arXiv220301347G/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Modelling X-shaped Radio Galaxies: Dynamical and Emission Signatures from the Back-flow model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Gourab Giri&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Bhargav Vaidya, Paola Rossi, Gianluigi Bodo, Dipanjan Mukherjee, Andrea Mignone&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Technology (IIT), Indore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/x-galaxy-gourabg</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/x-galaxy-gourabg</guid>
        
        <category>Galaxies</category>
        
        <category>Radio jets</category>
        
        <category>Magnetohydrodynamics</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How much Metal does the Quiet Sun Corona contain?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;XSM onboard Chandrayaan-2 observed the Sun during the deepest solar minimum of the past century from in 2019-2020. By studying the XSM spectra for the days when the Sun was very quiet, researchers have found that the abundances of all Mg, Al, Si is around two times higher than its abundances in the photosphere! They also calculated the temperature of the quiet Sun corona to be around 2 MK. This article explains how these measurements were made.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The visible orange-yellow surface of the Sun that we can see even with the naked eye is called the Photosphere. It extends up to a height of 400 km. The temperature here decreases from 6000K, at the bottom of the layer, to 4500K at the top of the layer. This is expected because as we move away from a source of energy and heat, the temperature drops. The next layer is the Chromosphere, that is in between a height of about 400 - 2100 km. The temperature in the Chromosphere varies between about 4000 K at the bottom and 8000 K at the top. As the numbers show, in the Chromosphere, as we move upwards it gets hotter and not cooler as common sense suggests!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More mystifyingly, things get extremely hot (literally) as we move into the next layer, the transition region, which is just a 100 km in height but the temperature drastically increases from a few thousand kelvin to a few million kelvin! Temperature stays at a million degree kelvin in the Corona (which extends throughout the solar system) as well, which is the uppermost atmospheric layer of the Sun. The reason for this temperature increase in the solar atmosphere is one of the long standing problems of solar physics referred to as the &lt;em&gt;Coronal Heating Problem&lt;/em&gt;. You can read more about this in the article: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cosmicvarta.in/vishal_machine_learning_corona_article&quot;&gt;Using machine learning to infer Solar Coronal heating&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/lakshitha_quiet_corona_metal/image1_lakshitha2.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: The Sun and its layers.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hinode.nao.ac.jp/en/news/results/formation-mechanisms-of-the-solar-chromosphere-revealed-by-hinode-and-iris/&quot;&gt;Hinode&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Corona is mainly visible in UV and X rays. This is because the hotter a material is, the light coming from it will be of higher energy. You can see this in daily life in the flames of a stove. The innermost regions of the fire will be bluish compared to the outer parts, which will be red, orange and yellow. As we have seen, since the Corona is at a million degree kelvin temperature, it emits mainly in the high energy part of the spectrum, that is, in UV and X-rays, while the Photosphere emits mainly in optical wavelengths that we can perceive with our naked eyes. This means that telescopes on the Earth are enough to observe and study the Photosphere. But since the ozone layer blocks UV and X rays (thankfully, otherwise we would not exist as we do now!), Coronal studies began only with advent of the space age and satellites in the 1960s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another phenomenon that is related and similarly astonishing to the ‘Coronal Heating Problem’ that occurs in the transition region and the Corona is called as the First Ionization Potential (FIP) Effect. This effect deals with the abundances of elements in the Corona.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after the launch of the first satellites with instruments to study the Sun in UV and X rays, &lt;a href=&quot;http://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/pdf/1963ApJ...137..945P&quot;&gt;Stuart R. Pottasch&lt;/a&gt; in 1963 found something very weird concerning the elements present in the Corona. Using spectroscopy, that is, by studying light from the Corona, he discovered that the absolute abundances (i.e., the abundances with respect hydrogen) of certain elements &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ionization_energy&quot;&gt;the low FIP elements&lt;/a&gt; like magnesium (Mg), silicon (Si) and iron (Fe) were mode abundant (3-4 times higher!) in the Corona than in the Photosphere. Now you might ask why is this surprising? After all, Corona is a different layer with a very different temperature. So, why can’t it have different abundances of elements than the Photosphere, right? This is because all the material that is present in the Corona comes from the lower atmospheric layers through flares and Coronal mass ejections (CMEs). &lt;a href=&quot;https://spaceplace.nasa.gov/solar-activity/en/&quot;&gt;Flares&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swpc.noaa.gov/phenomena/Coronal-mass-ejections&quot;&gt;CMEs&lt;/a&gt; are huge explosions that supply material and energy from the Photosphere to the Corona. So it was expected that the elemental abundances in the Corona will reflect that of the Photosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theories that are trying to explain the FIP effect predict that the FIP effect and the Coronal Heating Problem are intimately connected with each other. Thus studying one problem might give insights about the other and vice versa!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, many studies of the FIP effect have shown that the amount of FIP effect, which basically tells by how much the (low FIP) elements in the Corona are more compared to the Photosphere, is different in different structures of the Corona. Sun’s activity changes with an approximate period of 11 years called as the solar cycle. At the start of a cycle, large flares and CMEs on the sun are usually non-existent. With the progress of the cycle, activity increases, reaches a maximum and starts coming down again before the start of the next cycle. Studies have also shown that the elemental abundance in the Corona changes in accordance with the solar cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is relatively easier to study the Corona when explosions (flares and CMEs) happen. This is because the Sun is very active and outputs a large amount of UV and X rays which the instruments can receive. But studying the Sun when it is quiet requires extremely sensitive instruments to be present and observing the Sun. Here comes in Chandrayaan-2 live a saviour! The Chandrayaan-2 mission was launched in July 2019 and the orbiter carried an instrument called Solar X-ray Monitor (XSM), which is till date the most sensitive instrument to measure the sun’s spectra (light). For more information on XSM, refer to the article:&lt;a href=&quot;https://cosmicvarta.in/lakshitha_solar_article_corona&quot;&gt;Deciphering The Mysteries of The Quiet Sun Explosions&lt;/a&gt;. 2019 also marked the end of solar cycle 24 during which the sun was extremely quiet. This was the quietest the sun has been in the past 100 years! Thus with the Sun in its deep minimum and the XSM observing its inactivity, Santosh Vadawale and team have managed to decode the abundances of three (low FIP) elements - Mg, Al and Si  - in the quiescent Corona using spectroscopy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spectroscopy is the study of light of different energies that is emitted by a source. The instrument that is used for spectroscopy is called as a spectroscope/spectrometer. And the output of a spectroscope is a spectrum (plural - spectra). A spectrum is basically a graph of intensity (or count rate which gives the number of photons) versus the wavelength (or energy) of light. It is possible to derive the temperature and other physical parameters by studying the shape of the spectrum (known as the continuum), and by studying the bumps (called as ‘emission lines or emission complexes’), it is possible to derive the abundances of various elements present in the source (see figure 2). Each emission line is a ‘signature’ of a different element. By modelling (i.e., comparing the strength of the observed line and shape of the continuum with that predicted by theory) the spectra, we can find the abundances and other physical parameters. For more in-depth information about spectroscopy, please refer to: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cosmicvarta.in/solar-chromosphere-spectral-lines-vishal&quot;&gt;Understanding the solar chromosphere through spectral lines.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/lakshitha_quiet_corona_metal/image2_lakshitha2.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Soft X-ray spectra measured by the XSM for two representative days of quiet Sun observations are shown. Solid lines represent the best fit isothermal model and the residuals are shown in the bottom panel. Gray points correspond to non-solar background spectrum.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16643.pdf&quot;&gt;S.Vadawale et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By studying the XSM spectra for 73 days when the Sun was very quiet, they found that the abundances of all three elements (Mg, Al, Si) were around two times higher than the corresponding photospheric abundances. They also calculated the temperature of the quiet Sun to be around 2 MK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/lakshitha_quiet_corona_metal/image3_lakshitha2.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Light curve for the duration of the XSM observations used in this study. Orange shaded regions are duration when active regions were present on the Sun, pink shaded regions are duration when the Sun showed enhanced X-ray activity, and blue shaded regions are duration of quiet Sun observations.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2103.16643.pdf&quot;&gt;S.Vadawale et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As no activity was happening on the Sun, XSM was even able to measure the absolute lowest X-ray energy emitted by the Sun, which is about 6 x 10&lt;sup&gt;-10&lt;/sup&gt; Wm&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;. For comparison, the highest soft X-ray energy emitted by the Sun is of the order of 10&lt;sup&gt;-4&lt;/sup&gt;   Wm&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;, which is 6 orders of magnitude higher!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/abf35d&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Observations Of The Quiet Sun During The Deepest Solar Minimum Of The PastCentury With Chandrayaan-2 XSM: Elemental Abundances in the Quiescent Corona&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Santosh Vadawale&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Biswajit Mondal, N. P. S. Mithun, Aveek Sarkar, P. Janardhan, Bhuwan Joshi, Anil Bhardwaj, M. Shanmugam, Arpit R. Patel, Hitesh Kumar L. Adalja&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad, Gujarat-380 009, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/lakshitha_solar_article_quiet_sun</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lakshitha_solar_article_quiet_sun</guid>
        
        <category>Sun</category>
        
        <category>Corona</category>
        
        <category>Chandrayaan-2</category>
        
        <category>Elemental abundances</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>EARTH-SIZED TELESCOPES FOR ASTRONOMICAL OBSERVATIONS IN THE LOW RADIO FREQUENCIES</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The study of the cosmos is only complete when we can receive and analyse data from the entire electromagnetic spectrum, ranging from picometer-sized gamma rays to several meters long radio waves. This realization is what led to the advent of multiwavelength astronomy. But even in today’s era when technology has paved the way for us to observe the sky in a very wide range of wavelengths, it still remains poorly explored at wavelengths greater than a few tens of meters. This is mainly because the Earth’s ionosphere blocks most of these wavelengths. Even if we could observe them, it would require us to build a telescope several kilometres wide to properly resolve the sources, which is physically impossible. This article is a review of a journal paper that tackles these issues by proposing to simulate an Earth-sized radio telescope. The paper dwells into some technical details on how we can achieve a radio telescope larger than the size of the Earth and discusses the advantages such a system would offer. This article tries to simplify the concepts involved, and introduce the readers to an exciting new domain in radio astronomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is for sure physically impossible to build a telescope larger than even a few hundreds of meters, you might be wondering how the paper suggests we build a telescope not just a few kilometres wide, but larger than the entire diameter of the Earth, which is just shy of 13,000km! To achieve such a feat, it is proposed we build several small observing elements and send them to space, to revolve around the Earth in different orbits. Then we employ some analysis techniques which can cumulatively be known as Very Long Baseline Interferometry (VLBI, or more specifically, orbiting VLBI in our case, as our observing elements are all in orbit) to “stitch” the multiple images taken by each of these elements and produce a high-resolution image of the entire sky. Before we dive further into the how, what and why of the paper, let us first understand in some detail, these concepts involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radio astronomy is a subfield of astronomy that studies the universe in the radio spectrum (ranging from 1mm to 100km wavelengths). To fulfil this purpose, radio astronomy takes multidisciplinary contributions from physics, electronics and computer sciences alike. Radio waves are so large that we cannot practically use the typical lens and mirror arrangements that we use to observe in most other electromagnetic (EM) spectra. Lucky for us, the larger wavelengths mean smaller frequencies, small enough that we can “see” the crests and troughs of the wave using an antenna – yes, the same antenna that is in our smartphones and TV dishes! In fact, we can actually use our smartphones and TV dishes to observe the radio sky, albeit with a few modifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/earth_size_telescope_jaini/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: The electromagnetic spectrum and the atmospheric opacity for different wavelengths. While the Earth’s atmosphere is almost completely transparent to short-wavelength radio waves, it is completely opaque to wavelengths longer than 15m. (Source: http://gisgeography.com/electromagnetic-radiation/)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few advantages of observing in the radio frequencies include the fact that most of the high frequency radio waves completely pass through the Earth’s atmosphere. So, we are able to perform ground-based observations, which are cheaper and less complicated. It is also possible to observe astronomical objects or phenomena that are nearly impossible to detect in other wavelengths. But where there are advantages, there are disadvantages as well. Radio waves having wavelengths greater than 15m are blocked completely by the ionosphere, as can be seen from Figure 1, rendering it impossible to make any observations of the radio sky at those wavelengths using ground-based telescopes. Radio waves also tend to be plagued by man-made radio frequency interference (RFI). These can be any signals generated by us, such as the FM and TV frequencies, mobile communication signals, signals from any and all electronic equipment we use, all of which corrupt the astronomical radio signals, making it difficult to study them from the ground.
Being able to see the sky at wavelengths greater than 15m is important, because it is expected to be extremely bright with never-before-seen astronomical phenomena. At the risk of using a few technical jargons, the sky at these frequencies will be dominated by non-thermal emissions, such as synchrotron emission, as well as free-free absorption from the thermal plasma that outer space has an abundance of. Interested readers can learn more about these phenomena by referring to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cv.nrao.edu/~sransom/web/Ch4.html&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;. Therefore, in order to grab this unprecedented opportunity to observe these new astronomical processes and to avoid the drawbacks of ground-based radio telescopes, we must go to space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vlbi-visibility-and-the-image-plane&quot;&gt;VLBI, Visibility and the Image Plane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interferometry is a measurement technique that relies on the phenomenon of interference of light waves to produce a fringe (interference) pattern. Young’s double slit experiment and Michelson’s interferometer are two common experiments that most of you might have performed in your physics labs in your high school days.
VLBI is nothing but an extension of this technique for microwaves and radio waves. In VLBI, a signal from an astronomical source is collected using multiple radio telescopes (called as an array) placed some distance apart. Next, the distance between the radio telescopes is calculated using the difference between the time of arrival of the radio signals at different telescopes. This time difference is usually very small and is caused as the telescopes are located some finite distance apart. This allows observations of an object that are made simultaneously by many radio telescopes to be combined, thus creating a telescope with a size equal to the maximum separation between the telescopes, which is known as the maximum baseline. Since a radio telescope is nothing but an antenna, the signals received by each telescope are converted into voltages. These voltage signals are then amplified, filtered, digitized and then sent to the correlator, a digital device that cross-correlates the signals received from all the telescopes to produce the final image. In simple terms, the correlator “multiplies” each signal with every other signal and computes how well they are related.
VLBI is a very popular technique in radio astronomy because it enables the distance between telescopes to be much greater than that possible with conventional interferometry, which requires antennas to be physically connected by coaxial cables or other types of transmission lines. This, in turn, allows for the resultant images to be of much higher resolution. This can be inferred using the Rayleigh’s criterion, which specifies the minimum separation between two astronomical sources that may be resolved into distinct objects. This angular resolution (expressed in arcseconds) for any telescope is given by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://latex.codecogs.com/svg.image?\theta_{arcsec}&amp;space;\approx&amp;space;0.6&amp;space;\frac{&amp;space;\lambda_m&amp;space;/30m}{D_{km}/10000&amp;space;km}&amp;space;&quot; title=&quot;https://latex.codecogs.com/svg.image?\theta_{arcsec} \approx 0.6 \frac{ \lambda_m /30m}{D_{km}/10000 km} &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where, λm is the wavelength (in meters) and D_km is the size of the effective aperture of the telescope (in kms). In case of any interferometric technique, the size of the effective aperture will be equivalent to the maximum baseline of the radio telescope array. So, to sum it up, we can infer from Rayleigh’s criterion that the angular resolution is directly proportional to the wavelength and inversely to the effective aperture. Therefore, to obtain resolutions comparable to that in visible astronomy, radio astronomers must build telescopes a billion times the size, which is impractical. Instead, they employ VLBI, which gives them the option to use multiple smaller aperture telescopes to synthesize a larger aperture, at the expense of collecting area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ow that we understand the basics of VLBI, let us move on to the next important concept, which is visibility (also known as complex visibility or interferometric visibility by non-radio astronomers). In radio astronomy, visibility is defined as the response of the interferometer, which is the 2-dimensional Fourier transform of the sky brightness distribution. Fourier transform is a mathematical function that decomposes a time signal (which in our case, is the signal that a radio telescope receives) into the frequencies that make it up. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=spUNpyF58BY&amp;amp;ab_channel=3Blue1Brown&quot;&gt;This video&lt;/a&gt; beautifully explains the concept of Fourier transform, and is a must watch for anyone interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sky brightness distribution is given by T(l,m), which is the intensity of radio waves coming from a particular location (l,m) in the sky, where l and m are angles and measured in radians. Finally, visibility is given by V(u,v), which is a complex function of signals correlated from all the radio telescopes in the array. This visibility is measured at a position (u,v) on any user-defined plane (called the image plane or the uv-plane) which usually is the ground for ground-based arrays. The u and v axes are measured in wavelengths (or km, in our case). The image plane can be considered as a simulated aperture of a telescope, and each telescope pair in the array would give two V(u,v) samples (for simplicity, we’ll hereon refer to it as just uv-sample) on the plane at a given time. So, an interferometer array with N telescopes will have N(N - 1)/2 baselines and give twice that number of samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/earth_size_telescope_jaini/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: The first picture shows three different configurations of the Submillimeter Array represented in blue, red and black colours. They are observing a source at a Dec of +22˚ at a frequency of 345 GHz. The second image shows the total uv-plane coverage when observing for 8 hours, as the telescopes move due to the Earth’s rotation, forming new baselines, and thus, new uv-samples. The black samples are due to the array configuration shown in black and so on. (Source: http://anita.edu.au/lectures)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To better understand the concept of image plane, imagine the screen on your phone or computer is the image plane. Now, let’s say every second a pair of telescopes in the interferometer array generates two samples, which correspond to two pixels on your screen. The more the telescopes you have in your array, the more samples are produced every second and the more pixels on your screen light up. Also, the longer you observe a source, the more unique baselines are formed, and again the more pixels on your screen light up. Ideally, we would want all the pixels on the screen to be lit up so that the source being observed is 100% imaged. But that is not possible because the telescopes in our array are separated from each other, and no matter how long you observe, there will always be dark spots on your screen, i.e., gaps on the image plane. What we can infer from this is that for better imaging, we would need better coverage of the uv-plane, which can be done by observing a specific source over a longer period of time. Refer to Figure 2 for a better visual explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a better grasp on the concepts of VLBI, visibility, the image plane and radio interferometry in general, interested readers can refer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.radio2space.com/introduction-to-radio-interferometry/&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; for a basic discussion and &lt;a href=&quot;http://spiff.rit.edu/classes/ast613/lectures/radio_iii/radio_iii.html&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; for a slightly more advanced coverage of the topics. If you aren’t much of a reader, then &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0TwnZhiEc3A&amp;amp;ab_channel=AnitaChapter&quot;&gt;this 2-video series&lt;/a&gt; also does a fantastic job at simplifying these concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system proposed by the paper extends all these concepts into space, with the radio telescopes now aboard satellites revolving around the Earth. Orbiting VLBI is not a new concept in radio astronomy and the proof of concept was shown as early as 1986, by the Tracking and Data Relay Satellite System (TDRSS) launched by NASA. Following that came the Space VLBI Satellite: MUSES-B under the Japanese VLBI Space Observatory Program (VSOP) and RadioAstron (Spektr-R) operated by the Russian Astro Space Center. An extensive study of the past, present and future of space VLBI can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.01230&quot;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all of these multi-element space-based radio interferometers have only been used in conjunction with ground-based telescopes, therefore, rendering them unusable for observations in the lower frequency window that we’re interested in. The increasing interest in the low frequency radio sky, though, has resulted in several fully space-based interferometric missions being proposed such as the Low-Cost Space-based Ultra-long wavelength Radio Observatory (SURO-LC) and Orbiting Low Frequency Antennas for Radio Astronomy (OLFAR), to name a few. These proposed swarms of small satellites would be orbiting close to the Earth or at other special locations within our solar system, such as the Lagrange L2 point or the lunar orbit and would have a large number of observing elements working together in aperture synthesis mode, but with baseline lengths limited to only about a 100 km or so.
The novelty of the model proposed by this paper lies in the fact that by performing sensitive imaging observations with very high angular resolutions at low frequencies, we can reveal astronomical objects and phenomena that have never been seen before. These are the prospects that led to the simulation of a suitable space interferometer system so as to enable such high-resolution imaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-model&quot;&gt;The Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model was simulated keeping in consideration to have a minimal number of observing elements to view the entire sky. Intuitively, we can see that having just two telescopes in space is not going to be sufficient, so the model begins by assuming three observing elements mounted on satellites in mutually orthogonal and near-circular Low Earth Orbits (LEO), which is an orbit ranging from 300km to 2000km above the Earth’s surface, as shown in Figure 3. Each of the observing elements is assumed to have a uniform field of view (FoV) of 2π steradians (in other words, the telescope can see the entire hemisphere in front of it). Such a configuration would allow us to have baselines of over 15000km, which is larger than the diameter of the Earth, thus enabling angular resolution as fine as 1 arcsec (from Rayleigh’s criterion) even at 4 MHz (or wavelength of 75m).
The three satellites have different orbital heights, making their orbital periods distinct from each other. These orbital heights are deliberately chosen such that the orbits are mutually asynchronous. This ensures that the apparent baselines are distinctly different during each orbital cycle, thus giving a significantly better coverage of the uv-plane in a relatively short time span. The orbital speeds and time periods of the satellites can be calculated from the Newton’s law of gravitation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://latex.codecogs.com/svg.image?Orbital~velocity,&amp;space;~s=\sqrt{\frac{GM_e}{R&amp;plus;h}}&amp;space;&quot; title=&quot;https://latex.codecogs.com/svg.image?Orbital~velocity, ~s=\sqrt{\frac{GM_e}{R+h}} &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://latex.codecogs.com/svg.image?Time&amp;space;~Period,&amp;space;~T&amp;space;\approx&amp;space;\frac{2\pi&amp;space;(R&amp;plus;h)}{s}&amp;space;&quot; title=&quot;https://latex.codecogs.com/svg.image?Time ~Period, ~T \approx \frac{2\pi (R+h)}{s} &quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where, G (= 6.67&lt;em&gt;10-11 Nm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;/kg&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) is the universal gravitational constant, Me (= 5.982&lt;/em&gt;1024 kg), R (= 6371km) is the radius of Earth, and h is the orbital height of the satellite above the Earth’s surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/earth_size_telescope_jaini/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: An illustration of the model configuration: The near circular orbits (not to scale, and appearing in projection as ellipses) for the three satellites are shown. The first satellite has an equatorial orbit (red), and the other two (Satellites 2 and 3) have polar orbits (blue and green, respectively). The black circle in the centre denotes the Earth. (Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.03113&quot;&gt; Figure 2 of the paper.&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The various parameter values defined for each satellite are given in Table 1. These values were obtained by extensively testing the sensitivity of the uv-plane coverage to these parameters. The orbital height of satellite 1 is chosen to be greater than 700 km so as to be able to avoid the effects of atmospheric drag which are substantial at heights below 400 km as well as to avoid attenuation of the radio waves due to the ionospheric plasma which is significant at orbital heights below 700 km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Index&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Orbital Height (h)&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Orbital Speed (s)&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Time period (T)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;

    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Satellite 1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;770 km&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;7.48 km/s&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;100.01 min&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;

    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Satellite 2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1085 km&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;7.32 km/s&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;106.70 min&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;

    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Satellite 3&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;1400 km&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;7.17 km/s&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;113.53 min&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;


&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the model is different from the usual Earth-based and Earth-and-space-based interferometer systems, the typical definition of the uv-plane as the ground plane would not suffice. So, the uv-plane was explicitly defined in a different manner, with its origin at the centre of the Earth and the plane perpendicular to the direction of the source being observed. After extensive testing, an observing period of 16 days was found to be optimal. In order to obtain the maximum and minimum possible uv-plane coverages during this observation period as well as to find out the extent of the coverages, three exclusive source directions are chosen representing the extreme cases (as shown in Figure 3). These directions, namely A, B, and C, are defined as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Direction A: RA = 03:00:00 Dec = +45 deg, inclined equally to all three satellite orbit axes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Direction B: RA = 03:00:00 Dec = 0.0 deg, representing a set of specific directions that are perpendicular to one of the satellite orbit axes (or in the plane of that orbit) and inclined equally with the other two.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Direction C: RA = 00:00:00 Dec = 0.0 deg, perpendicular to any two of the satellite orbit axes and parallel to the third axis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be easily visualized that any source in the sky would fall within the bounds of these three directions relative to them. The corresponding uv-plane coverages are shown in Figure 4 and the evolution of the coverages over these 16 days can be viewed at &lt;a href=&quot;https://bit.ly/SpaceInterferometer&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/earth_size_telescope_jaini/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;

Figure 4: The uv-coverages over the duration of 16 days, for the three source directions A, B and C from left to right. The red, blue, and green tracks represent the baseline corresponding to the satellite pairs 1–2, 2–3, and 3–1, respectively. The u and v axes are indicated in km. (Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.03113&quot;&gt; Figure 3 of the paper. &lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring this coverage quantitatively, it is found that the percentage coverage lies between a maximum of 64% and a minimum of 55.5% for any source for an observation period of 16 days, which is significantly greater than what we usually obtain with ground-based interferometer setups (which is typically around 15% for the same observing duration). So, the model not only has much greater baselines, but is also capable of giving significantly better coverage for any source, which would ultimately result in very fine angular resolutions and better imaging capabilities at low radio frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper then proceeds to discuss the sensitivity of this coverage to the satellite orbits so as to be able to determine the best relative positions of the satellites with respect to each other. Next, it discusses the quality of the final image based on the simulations. Finally, it compares our minimal 3-satellite model with another 4-satellite model, to examine how much of an advantage adding a fourth satellite would be, how that would be reflected in terms of the improvement in uv-coverage and the time taken to obtain the desired coverage. The results indicate that even with a system of four satellites (and six baselines) the total percentage coverage is essentially similar to that obtained with three satellites when observed for the same time duration of 16 days. Although it is noted that when observed for shorter durations, the percentage coverage by the 4-satellite system is noticeably more than that of the 3-satellite one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, we discuss the importance of a fully space-based interferometer to observe the low frequency sky with very high angular resolutions and uv-plane coverages and that a minimal configuration with just three elements is optimum for the purpose scientifically, technologically and economically. Easier said than done though, because going to space entails its own challenges. While an elaborate study of them is beyond the scope of this paper, it does acknowledge some of the major ones and discusses possible solutions, showing that there are ways to not only overcome these challenges, but also use them to our advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/publications-of-the-astronomical-society-of-australia/article/minimal-space-interferometer-configuration-for-imaging-at-low-radio-frequencies/837BA18A935418FB608A245913322AF9&quot;&gt;  A minimal space interferometer configuration for imaging at low radio frequencies &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Akhil Jaini&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Avinash A. Deshpande, Sainath Bitragunta&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt;
Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India – 560034;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; (Where the research was conducted): Raman Research Institute, Bangalore, India; Birla Institute of Technology and Science – Pilani, Pilani, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/earth-size-telescope-akhil</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/earth-size-telescope-akhil</guid>
        
        <category>radio astronomy</category>
        
        <category>radio interferometers</category>
        
        <category>space telescopes</category>
        
        <category>very long baseline interferometry</category>
        
        <category>artificial satellites</category>
        
        <category>space observatories</category>
        
        <category>low frequency radio</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Identifying emission-line stars from a large spectroscopic database</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We present a catalog of 3339 hot emission-line stars (ELS) identified from 451,695 O, B, and A type spectra, provided by the LAMOST DR5 release. We developed an automated python routine that identified 5437 spectra having a peak between 6561 and 6568~Å. False detections and bad spectra were removed, leaving 4138 good emission-line spectra of 3339 unique ELS. We re-estimated the spectral type of 3307 spectra as the LAMOST Stellar Parameter Pipeline (LASP) did not provide accurate spectral types for these emission-line spectra. As Herbig Ae/Be stars show higher excess in near-infrared and mid-infrared wavelengths than Classical Ae/Be stars, we used 2MASS and WISE photometry to distinguish them. Finally, we report 1089 Classical Be, 233 Classical Ae, and 56 Herbig Ae/Be stars identified from the LAMOST DR5. In addition, 928 B[em]/A[em] stars and 240 CAe/CBe potential candidates are identified. From our sample of 3339 hot emission-line stars, 2716 ELS identified in this work do not have any record in the SIMBAD database and they can be considered as new detections. Identification of such a large homogeneous set of emission-line spectra will help the community to study the emission phenomenon in detail without worrying about the inherent biases when compiling from various sources.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand what emission line stars (ELS) are, one needs to know about the spectrum of a star. Each star has its own unique spectrum, analogous to the fingerprint of humans. A spectrum can be used to identify the properties of the star such as its temperature, chemical composition and (indirect) physical constraints. So clearly, spectroscopy of cosmic objects can reveal lots of information about the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let us ask a more basic question. What is a spectrum? To understand this, imagine a rainbow on a rainy day. A rainbow is formed when the sunlight passes through the water molecules suspended in the air after the rain. As the sunlight moves through a spherical water droplet, it gets dispersed into various colours ranging from Violet to Red. This is a real-life example of spectroscopy. The light from a stellar object, when passed through a slit or a prism (the optical equivalent of the spherical water droplet), gets split into various colours. If the light from the star is as ideal as white light is, which is made up of all the colors with equal intensity, we would get a beautiful color gradient with all colors shining equally. However, the universe is not that simple. The spectrum of a star will have bright and dark lines, similar to the way we have ridges and valleys in our fingerprint (Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1:  A representative high-resolution spectrum showing the visible light of alpha Boo. The black lines in this spectrum are caused due to various metallic elements present in the photosphere of the cool giant alpha Boo.
Image source:&lt;a hrefsridharan1_emission_stars_database=&quot;https://noirlab.edu/public/images/noao-arct/&quot;&gt;N.A.Sharp, NOIRLab/NSF/AURA)
 &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bright and dark lines (or emission and absorption lines) are the most crucial information of the spectrum. They tell us about the atomic and molecular processes going on in the top most layer of the star which is known as the photosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An absorption line is formed in the spectrum when light of a certain wavelength is absorbed by an atom or a molecule. Similarly, an emission line is formed when light of a certain wavelength is emitted (or radiated) by an atom or a molecule. To put it simply, when an atom ‘absorbs’ light, it goes into a higher energy level and when it ‘emits’ light, it comes down to a lower energy level as shown in Figure 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 2: The above plots show the absorption and emission process as caused by the excitation and de-excitation of electrons around the nucleus.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webassign.net/labsgraceperiod/ucscgencheml1/lab_6/manual.html&quot;&gt;webassign &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spectrum of a star is the information that gives us the intensity at each wavelength of light. An observed stellar spectrum consists of the blackbody continuum, absorption lines and in some cases, emission lines. The blackbody continuum in the visible and infrared region is due to the thermal emission of the star and the absorption lines are seen because the ‘cooler’ photosphere absorbs light at certain wavelengths. These two components are seen in the spectrum of all the stars because it arises due to the basic structure of stars. Now let us come to the topic of this article, ELS. Emission lines arise from a hot, gaseous region around the star that is formed due to some special nature of the star. The type of stars that show emission lines in their spectrum are called Emission line stars (ELS). You can call them the rebellious group of star families, who want to be unique by showing emission lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various types of ELS known to us today (and its analogues)
Pre-main sequence (PMS) stars - young, naughty teenagers creating chaos
Classical Be stars - people with midlife crisis
Wolf-Rayet stars - old, wise people
Even though ELS comprises stars in various evolutionary phases, in most cases the emission arises from the equatorial circumstellar disc which is made of gas and dust. The formation mechanism of circumstellar disc varies between different classes. For example, in PMS stars the circumstellar disc is the accretion disc through which material is added to the star from its surroundings. In Classical Be stars, the disc is formed due to rapid spinning of the star which pushes away material from the star to its surroundings. So it should be noted that even though we put stars with emission lines into a single category of ELS, they are very different from each other. Hence, we need to classify them based on their photometric properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aim&quot;&gt;Aim:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As large-scale spectroscopic surveys collect a large number of spectra every night, we need to identify special classes of stars such as ELS and classify them into different categories for the research community to study various emission mechanisms. This is the motivation for the work titled “Discovery of 2716 hot emission-line stars from LAMOST DR5’’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data&quot;&gt;Data:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAMOST) is a multi-object telescope that can observe around 4000 stars in one night. By its 5th data release (DR5), it had accumulated around 9 million spectra from 2011-2017 which are available to the community. We made use of this huge database to increase the number of ELS stars known to us. One interesting fact about LAMOST is that the majority of  observed stars are in the Galactic anticenter direction. This is particularly important because the earlier studies which have identified ELS have not looked into this direction of the sky. So this opened up an opportunity to study ELS in previously less explored parts of the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;analysis&quot;&gt;Analysis:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this work, we took O, B and A type stars (Teff ranging from 30000 K to 10000 K) from the LAMOST DR5 database (for an explanation of different spectral types, look into Anusha R’s CAe article). We restricted ourselves to these spectral types because the main aim of this was to identify new Classical Be/Ae and Herbig Be/Ae stars. Once we removed bad quality (Signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) &amp;lt; 10)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; spectra from our list, we used an open-source python package called ‘scipy.signal’ to identify emission peaks. The entire definition of ELS rests on the presence of one of the most commonly found emission line, Hα at 6563 Å. We searched and picked out spectra with the Hα line anywhere between 6561 Å and 6568 Å. This range was selected to take into effect the instrumental calibration defect (if any) and the doppler shift that may be seen in a few stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identified 4138 spectra that belong to 3339 unique ELS stars from our analysis. To classify stars into different categories such as CBeAe or HBeAe, we need an accurate spectral type for each spectrum. The LAMOST automated pipeline does provide a spectral type for each spectrum which did not turn out to be accurate due to the presence of emission lines. This introduced the necessity for us to re-estimate spectral type for each spectrum. We followed a technique called template matching. We made use of the MILES stellar spectral library for this purpose. For each spectrum, we matched the templates from MILES library to our target spectrum and identified the best fit. Then the spectral type of the best fit template was assigned to the target spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to differentiate between Classical Be/Ae and Herbig Be/Ae stars, we made use of the inherent difference between them known as Infrared (IR) excess. Herbig Be/Ae stars, being young stars, have lots of gas and dust around them in addition to a circumstellar disc. This extra gas and dust reprocesses the energy from the star and emits them in infrared wavelengths. Due to this, the HAeBe stars are brighter in IR wavelengths than CBe stars. Hence we use the photometric data&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; available to us to differentiate them based on colors and spectral indices. The breakup of various classes identified in this work is given in the table below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;  Table 1: Statistical break-up of various classes identified in this work.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.08025&quot;&gt;Table 1 of the review paper) &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We visually examined the Hα line features belonging to each class and reported their statistics. Finally, a representative spectrum of major classes is presented in Figure 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 3: This plot shows a representative spectrum belonging to each of Oe*, CBe, CAe, HBe, HAe, B[em], and A[em] classes. Red dotted lines denote [NII] lines at 6548 and 6584 ̊A and green solid lines denote [SII] lines at 6717 and 6731 ̊A. The spectra are normalized using laspec open source python package.

Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.08025&quot;&gt; Figure 7 of the review paper &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-scope&quot;&gt;Future Scope:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research work identifies new ELS stars from a large database and classifies them into various categories based on their photometric properties. As the data collection capabilities increase day-to-day, the need for such works increases. We have multiple follow-up works in the fray which uses the LAMOST database effectively in identifying and study the properties of CBeAe and HAeBe stars in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021arXiv210808025B/abstract&quot;&gt; Discovery of 2716 hot emission-line stars from LAMOST DR5 &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Shridharan Baskaran&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Blesson Mathew, Nidhi S, Anusha R, Arun R, Sreeja S. Kartha, Yerra Bharat Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; CHRIST (Deemed to be University), Bangalore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Signal-to-noise ratio or SNR is a quantity which defines the quality of a spectrum. More the SNR, the better the spectrum. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Photometry (in astronomical context) means measurement of brightness of a star. The brightness of a star observed through filters of different wavelengths can be used to decode information about the star. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photometry_(astronomy)&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/sridharan_emission_stars_database</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/sridharan_emission_stars_database</guid>
        
        <category>Emission-line stars</category>
        
        <category>Catalog</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bengaluru: The Astronomy City</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As part of the National Science day celebrations, the Indian Institute of Astrophysics organised a panel discussion titled- Bengaluru The Astronomy City. The focus of the meeting was to educate the young students regarding various opportunities in astronomy and astrophysics at all educational levels.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total of 10 institutions located in Bengaluru took part in the event namely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icts.res.in/&quot;&gt;International Centre for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rri.res.in/&quot;&gt;Raman Research Institute (RRI)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.isro.gov.in/&quot;&gt;Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iisc.ac.in/&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Science (IISc)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://christuniversity.in/&quot;&gt;CHRIST (Deemed to by University)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sjc.ac.in/&quot;&gt;St. Joseph’s College&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bas.org.in/&quot;&gt;Bangalore Astronomical Society (BAS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://abaaonline.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Association of Bangalore Amateur Astronomers (ABAA)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.taralaya.org/&quot;&gt;JawaharLal Nehru Planetarium (JNP)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These institutes include core research institutes (1-4), Universities (5-7), amateur organizations (8-9) and a planetarium (10) involved in astronomy research and outreach. The panel consisted of a diverse group of individuals which included Ph.D. students, postdoctoral fellows, senior faculty members as well as amateur astronomers.
The representatives introduced themselves, about their career paths and how they reached their current positions. Niruj Mohan Ramanujam from IIA started the event with an introduction to the panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/blr.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; The participants of the discussion panel. Image courtesy: author.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the introductions were over, Sonali Sachdeva from RRI gave a presentation covering opportunities for students as well as interested minds at almost all educational levels. The initial slides focussed on the opportunities in astronomy for school students. For instance, the following opportunities were presented for school students:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public talks especially for school students which are regularly organized by all participant organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schools can invite a scientist to interact with the students (ICTS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Science workshops for students and teachers (JNP)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Science Education in Early Development (SEED) Summer Program for students (JNP)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Science Over Weekends (SOW) for high school students (JNP)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Maths Circle (ICTS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outreach programs for govt schools in North Bengaluru (ICTS)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Young Scientist Program (ISRO)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the opportunities available to school students, the subsequent slides presented opportunities for students at the college level. The opportunities at the BSc and MSc levels were presented in detail. All the participating institutes provided information regarding short or long term research projects under the guidance of their faculty members. The complete information is available in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bB13TdvmkRU&quot;&gt;the video.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next part of the discussion focused on the opportunities for prospective Ph.D. students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bengaluru probably has the highest number of astronomy Ph.D. students in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the participant research institutes and universities offer Ph.D. programs for students from both science and engineering backgrounds. Students are admitted through national eligibility tests such as GATE/JEST/NET and/or through their own entrance exams, followed by an interview. These researchers can also carry out their research in collaboration with multiple universities/institutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information about the opportunities for amateur astronomers was provided by representatives from ABAA and BAS, organizations which have been educating Bengalurians about astronomy and astronomical events for a long time. JNP offers a variety of programs and workshops for people from all backgrounds and expertise. These programs have been attracting thousands of students every year for more than three decades. So far, over 135 students who have benefitted from these programs have taken up astronomy research as their career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presentation was followed by a discussion session which was quite lively and people asked a wide variety of questions such as the opportunities for primary school children, visits of students to the research laboratories, teacher training opportunities, and support for astronomy clubs in schools. For a lot of questions, the panelists provided their perspectives which provided comprehensive answers to these questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, information regarding new opportunities was provided by the institutions such as ISRO which has launched the ‘Young Scientist Program’. Representatives from IIA provided detailed information about Engineering or astronomy-based projects for the upcoming 30m telescope. Students were provided detailed information about how to apply for research projects at these research institutes. Information about summer programs and internships for MSc/engineering students in all the institutes were also discussed. The links provided at the end of the article provide comprehensive information about these opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the vibrant discussion, it is evident that Bengalurians are a curious lot when it comes to research happening in Astronomy. It was noticeably observed that parents are particularly interested in exposing their kids to astronomy and science in general from a very young age. The panelists were also excited to share more of their work. This discussion indeed seems like the first step towards the combined efforts of all these institutions coming together to take astronomy to the Bengaluru people. We hope for many more such efforts to follow in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video of the meeting is available below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bB13TdvmkRU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-links-to-various-internship-opportunities-for-students-at-various-education-levels&quot;&gt;The links to various internship opportunities for students at various education levels:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iiap.res.in/?q=degree&quot;&gt;IIA internship opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rri.res.in/careers/visiting-students&quot;&gt;RRI internship opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iisc.ac.in/positions-open/&quot;&gt;IISc open positions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icts.res.in/opportunities/graduate-studies/summer&quot;&gt;ICTS internship opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.isro.gov.in/research-and-academia-interface/internships-projects-training&quot;&gt;ISRO internship opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.isro.gov.in/capacity-building/yuvika-yuva-vigyani-karyakram-young-scientist-programme&quot;&gt;ISRO YUVIKA - YUva VIgyani KAryakram (Young Scientist Programme)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kvpy.iisc.ernet.in/main/index.htm&quot;&gt;KVPY scheme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://webjapps.ias.ac.in/fellowship2022/index.html&quot;&gt;IAS fellowship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information regarding the career opportunities, please also visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cosmicvarta.in/career_help&quot;&gt;career help&lt;/a&gt; section in our website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/bangalore-astronomy-city</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/bangalore-astronomy-city</guid>
        
        <category>popular</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understanding the evolution of the binary star system ‘Cen X-3’: New measurements of the spin and orbital parameters of the system </title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Researchers from Inter-University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics (IUCAA), Pune, present the new measurements of the spin and orbital parameters of the binary star system ‘Cen X-3’. This work is a step forward in understanding the complex dynamics of the binary star systems and their evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘Cen X-3’&lt;/strong&gt; is a binary star system observed in the constellation &lt;em&gt;‘Centaurus’&lt;/em&gt;. It is one of the most luminous X-ray sources in our galaxy and the first-ever X-ray pulsar to be discovered.
Scientists from the Inter-University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics (IUCAA), Pune present the &lt;strong&gt;new measurements of spin and orbital parameters of ‘Cen X-3’&lt;/strong&gt;. The results are crucial in &lt;strong&gt;understanding the life-cycle and evolution of X-ray binary systems&lt;/strong&gt;. The work is published in the &lt;em&gt;‘Journal of Astrophysics and Astronomy on AstroSat: Five Years in Orbit’&lt;/em&gt;. Researchers used the data from the &lt;strong&gt;Large Area X-ray Proportional Counters (LAXPCs)&lt;/strong&gt; onboard &lt;strong&gt;Astrosat&lt;/strong&gt;, for the analysis. &lt;strong&gt;Astrosat&lt;/strong&gt; is India’s first dedicated multi-wavelength space telescope launched by the &lt;em&gt;Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)&lt;/em&gt; in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cen X-3&lt;/strong&gt; is a two-star system consisting of a &lt;strong&gt;pulsar&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;em&gt;highly magnetized neutron star beaming X-rays&lt;/em&gt;, and a companion star. The neutron star is an extremely compact object; &lt;em&gt;as massive as our sun but only a few kilometers across in size!&lt;/em&gt; The neutron star in Cen X-3 gravitationally accretes matter from its companion star. The kinetic energy of the infalling matter is converted to other forms of energy including electromagnetic radiation. The neutron star’s magnetic field dictates the accretion flow inside the magnetosphere. The accreting matter is channeled along the magnetic field lines and onto the magnetic poles forming an accretion column. The neutron star’s rotational axis is not necessarily aligned with its magnetic axis. Such &lt;em&gt;misalignment&lt;/em&gt; gives rise to &lt;em&gt;highly periodic pulsations&lt;/em&gt; hence the name &lt;strong&gt;‘pulsars’&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Understanding-the-evolution-of-the-binary-star-system-Cen-X-3-ketan-images/image1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1: Illustration of an accretion-powered pulsar. The magnetic axis sweeps earth in every rotation of the neutron star due to misalignment between the rotational axis and the magnetic axis giving rise to highly periodic pulsations.&lt;br /&gt;
The image used here is available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nrao.edu/images/pulsar_web.jpg&quot;&gt; this &lt;/a&gt; URL.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both stars are gravitationally bound and revolve around each other. The binary orbit can evolve due to matter exchange between the stars, mass loss from the binary system, and due to tidal interaction between the two stars. Studying the evolution of the orbit of such systems is important in understanding stellar structure and evolution. The results of these studies can be a &lt;strong&gt;direct test for stellar structure models and evolution theories&lt;/strong&gt;. The &lt;strong&gt;first step in doing such a study is to determine the binary orbit&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Understanding-the-evolution-of-the-binary-star-system-Cen-X-3-ketan-images/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Determination of a binary orbit from the doppler shift &lt;br /&gt;(NS: Neutron Star), Image courtesy: Author
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In systems like Cen X-3, the companion star is almost 10-15 times heavier than the neutron star. Thus the center of mass of the binary system is much closer to the center of the companion star than the neutron star. In such cases, one can visualize the binary orbit, as illustrated in figure 2 where the neutron star is orbiting around the companion star.  Due to its motion in the binary orbit, the neutron star moves back and forth along the line of sight. The observed frequency of the pulses from the neutron star is shifted due to this motion owing to the phenomenon called the &lt;strong&gt;‘Doppler effect’&lt;/strong&gt;. Due to this effect, &lt;em&gt;when the neutron star is moving towards the observer, the pulses arrive faster and when the neutron star is moving away from the observer, the pulses are delayed&lt;/em&gt; as shown in figure 2.
This results in a periodic variation with time in the observed pulse frequency. The rate of this variation corresponds to the orbital period of the system. For a perfectly circular orbit, the pulse frequency variation is sinusoidal. The deviation from the sinusoidal behavior is indicative of the eccentricity in the orbit. Eccentricity is a measure of how elongated the orbit is. The eccentricity of a perfectly circular orbit is zero. The higher the eccentricity, the more elongated the orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The binary orbit can be &lt;strong&gt;determined completely&lt;/strong&gt; from this. For a system with a nearly circular orbit like Cen X-3, &lt;strong&gt;parameters that can describe the system dynamics&lt;/strong&gt; completely are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neutron star spin period and its rate of change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Period of the binary orbit and its rate of change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Orbital velocity and radius&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eccentricity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evolution of the orbit can be understood by comparing the orbital parameters at various instances of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parisee Shirke (IUCAA, Pune) and the team&lt;/strong&gt; found that the &lt;strong&gt;spin period&lt;/strong&gt; of the neutron star has reduced to &lt;strong&gt;4.80s&lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;4.81s&lt;/strong&gt;. This means that the neutron star is &lt;strong&gt;spinning up&lt;/strong&gt; which is as per its known behavior. However, the rate at which the neutron star is spinning up has halved. This can be due to &lt;strong&gt;variation in the rate of matter accretion from the companion star&lt;/strong&gt;. The &lt;strong&gt;orbital period&lt;/strong&gt; was found to be around &lt;strong&gt;2.03 days&lt;/strong&gt;. The rate of change of the orbital period was observed to be &lt;strong&gt;substantially large compared to the previously reported values&lt;/strong&gt;. The authors state that this &lt;strong&gt;could be due to short time-scale variations&lt;/strong&gt; in the orbital period. The &lt;strong&gt;orbital velocity&lt;/strong&gt; is measured to be around &lt;strong&gt;410 Km/s&lt;/strong&gt; which agrees with the previous measurements. The &lt;strong&gt;projected radius&lt;/strong&gt; of the orbit has decreased from &lt;strong&gt;39.66 lt-s&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;38.23 lt-s&lt;/strong&gt;. This change is &lt;strong&gt;in accordance with the observed orbital decay&lt;/strong&gt; in Cen X-3. The binary orbit is observed to be &lt;strong&gt;nearly circular&lt;/strong&gt; with a very small eccentricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is a step forward in understanding the &lt;strong&gt;complex dynamics of the binary star systems and their evolution&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021JApA...42...58S/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; A New Measurement of the Spin and Orbital Parameters of the High Mass X-ray Binary Centaurus X-3 using AstroSat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Parisee Shirke&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Suman Bala, Jayashree Roy, Dipankar Bhattacharya&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Inter-University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics, Pune&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/evolution-binary-star-system-cenx3-ketan</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/evolution-binary-star-system-cenx3-ketan</guid>
        
        <category>Neutron Stars</category>
        
        <category>Pulsars</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sir C. V. Raman: Raman effect and beyond</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We Indians celebrate &lt;strong&gt;National Science Day&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;strong&gt;28th February&lt;/strong&gt; each year to mark the &lt;strong&gt;discovery of the Raman effect&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Sir C. V. Raman&lt;/strong&gt;. Some of Raman’s discoveries like the &lt;strong&gt;Raman effect (for which he was awarded the Nobel prize), Raman-Nath theory, his studies on Brillouin scattering, the soft mode process&lt;/strong&gt;, etc. are so well known and outstanding, that they tend to overshadow many of his other elegant and significant contributions to the science. We attempt to highlight a few of Raman’s discoveries such that they &lt;strong&gt;portray a more complete picture of Sir C. V. Raman and his contributions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/cvraman.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Sir Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman&lt;br /&gt;(7 November 1888 - 21 November 1970)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sir C. V. Raman&lt;/strong&gt; occupies a very special place in the &lt;strong&gt;scientific landscape of India&lt;/strong&gt;. His contributions to science were monumental both in &lt;strong&gt;scale and scope&lt;/strong&gt;. He also played a pivotal role in &lt;strong&gt;shaping Indian science institutions and redefined the way in which science was done in India&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Max Born&lt;/strong&gt;, a nobel prize winning german scientist who was instrumental in the development of the quantum mechanics, had this to say about Raman,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;
“There is no Indian physicist of the rank of Raman. No man can compare with him in vigor or intensity.”
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-curious-case-of-a-relentless-experimentalist&quot;&gt;The curious case of a relentless experimentalist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the year 1921. You could find a turbaned Indian man on a ship returning from Europe to India, running all around, with his nicol prisms and cardboard tubes, collecting sea water from the depths of the ocean. The visual beauty of the Mediterranean ocean had bewitched him.
Not so long ago, Lord Rayleigh had shown that the blue color of the sky is due to scattering of light by air molecules. However, according to Lord Rayleigh, the blue color of the deep ocean was due to reflection of the sky in the water.
Raman showed, by a simple experiment he performed on board the ship, that the blue color of the ocean is due to molecular scattering and not just due to the reflection of the sky. He quenched the sky’s reflection with a nicol prism at the Brewster angle and found that the blue color &lt;i&gt;“far from being impoverished by suppression of the sky reflection was wonderfully improved thereby”&lt;/i&gt;.
In 1922, he wrote the celebrated monograph &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/110505a0&quot;&gt;“Molecular Diffraction of Light”&lt;/a&gt; and so began the saga of a single-minded man pursuing his vision with a stamina and persistence never seen before, which eventually lead to the discovery of the Raman effect and many other outstanding contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weak-fluorescence&quot;&gt;Weak Fluorescence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 1923, KR Ramanathan, one of Raman’s students, studied the scattering of light in water. Sunlight was focussed on the liquid and the scattered light was observed through a system of complementary filters, each filter completely cutting off the light transmitted by the other. Nothing should have been observed if there had been no change of color during the scattering process. However, a track of scattered light could be observed showing there was indeed a change in the color of light during scattering. This was attributed to a “weak fluorescence” due to impurities which were believed to be present. Raman was not convinced with this explanation though.
This “weak fluorescence” was not completely depolarised (as true fluorescence should have been) and the amount of depolarisation changed with wavelength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-raman-effect&quot;&gt;THE RAMAN EFFECT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/raman_spectra.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Sir C. V. Raman with the spectrograph (Top) and the first Raman spectra photographed (Bottom)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/raman_spectra_news.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Newspaper announcements of the discovery of the Raman effect
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 1927, the so-called polarised “weak fluorescence” was observed again by S Venkateswaran in pure glycerine with greater intensity. Due to limited availability of S Venkateswaran, Raman persuaded KS Krishnan, one of his brightest students, to set up experiments to find “weak fluorescence” in various materials. Raman and Krishnan worked together continuously and detected the polarized “weak fluorescence” in all the liquids, gasses and solids they examined.
According to Krishan, Raman personally verified all the liquids exhibited this phenomenon. Raman was so excited about the discovery that he rushed to Krishan’s home at night to inform him that their observations were related to the Kramers-Heisenberg process they were looking for all these years.
A note was sent to &lt;strong&gt;the Nature journal&lt;/strong&gt; about the discovery. However, Raman continued his experiments, mostly by himself since the observed phenomenon was not yet fully understood.
On &lt;strong&gt;February 28th 1928&lt;/strong&gt;, Raman examined the scattered light with a direct vision spectroscope and found that the classical and modified scattering appear in the spectrum as separate regions with a distinct dark region between them, a clear demonstration of a change of wavelength in scattering.
The &lt;strong&gt;Nobel Prize in Physics 1930&lt;/strong&gt; was awarded to Raman &lt;strong&gt;“for his work on the scattering of light and for the discovery of the effect named after him.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/nobel_prize.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Raman’s Nobel medal and citation
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;indian-musical-instruments-and-acoustics&quot;&gt;Indian musical instruments and acoustics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before Raman started working on the scattering of Light, he was fascinated by waves… sound waves! Raman’s father, R Chandrasekhara Iyer was a teacher of Physics and Mathematics and a proficient violinist. That must have influenced him to take interest in the physics of sound waves. Raman himself played violin. At the age of 16, when he was a student of the Presidency college, Madras, Raman commenced his acoustic research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/veena.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Illustration of a Veena
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He investigated whether his intuition that the veena produces the most exquisite musical sound is due to sentiment or has a sound physical basis. The bridge of the veena is so cunningly constructed that the Helmholtz law, which states that the position at which the string is plucked cannot be a node, is violated. Thus this instrument produces innumerable harmonics making its sound closest in harmonic content to the human voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/tabla.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;The mridangam and tabla produce a succession of musically harmonic overtones in the same way as any stringed instrument
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sharp ear with a keen interest in music can detect musical overtones in the sound of the mridangam and the tabla. Raman discovered that the heterogeneous loading of their membranes can produce harmonics - so that in the hands of the masters, the Indian drum is similar to a stringed instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diffraction-of-light-by-ultrasonic-waves---raman-nath-theory&quot;&gt;Diffraction of light by ultrasonic waves - Raman-Nath Theory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light is a form of electromagnetic radiation. Young’s double slit experiment conclusively showed that the interference pattern can be obtained from interaction of light with matter. How about the interaction of light with matter waves!
Raman-Nath theory explained a remarkable optical phenomenon that occurs when a parallel beam of light is diffracted by ultrasonic waves. In modern electro-optic instrumentation, the phenomenon of diffraction of light by ultrasonic waves is utilized in acousto-optic spectrometers, which analyze the electrical signal to obtain its power spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;colors-in-nature&quot;&gt;Colors in Nature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raman always had a huge fascination for colors. In the institute that he had built for himself after retirement (now Raman Research Institute), he started building his collection of colorful minerals gathered from all across the world. The collection includes limestones, marbles, alabaster, gypsums, tourmalines, agates, quartzites, jades, amethysts, fluorites, micas, serpentines, iolites, malachites, lapis lazuli and feldspars. Raman studied several of the exquisite optical phenomena displayed by these minerals. Due to lack of basic facilities during the initial days of his new institute, he had to mostly rely on the beam of sunlight to explore the optics of these substances. Even with such simple setups, it is remarkable that he could extract a substantial amount of information about these minerals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/mineral_01.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/mineral_02.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Raman’s collection of minerals
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birds are a delight to watch! Raman was very curious about the optical characteristic and the color distribution in birds, since it was so different in different parts of the same bird, in different specimens and in different species that no single explanation would suffice. He would invoke every known optics concept to try to explain these phenomena. He published only one paper on this topic; however talked about it a lot. The interest was not just limited to birds though. “Birds, Beetles and Butterflies” was his favorite title for the talk. He gave dozens of lectures on this subject, each one unique!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diamond&quot;&gt;Diamond&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after the discovery of the Raman effect, C Ramaswamy, Raman’s younger brother, asked him to suggest a research problem which he could pursue. Seeing the diamond ring of the newly wed Ramaswamy sported on his finger, Raman suggested the study of scattering in diamond. The famous 1332 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; Raman line of diamond was discovered in the spectrum. Using a 140-carat diamond that was borrowed from the Maharaja of Darbhanga, Bhagavantam, one of Raman’s pupils confirmed this result and also recorded the complex luminescence spectrum around 4152 &lt;span&gt;Å&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raman says this about diamonds,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;
“With their perfect geometric forms and their smooth lustrous beauty they look absolutely fresh from nature’s crucible, although actually taken from sedimentary formations a thousand million years old. The strongly marked curvature of the crystal faces and the smoothly rounded edges are a surprising feature of these crystals”
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/raman_diamond.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Sir C. V. Raman with beloved diamond
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In continuation with his work on diamonds, he also carried out pioneering studies of the thermo-optic behavior of other solids, their photo-elastic and magneto-optic properties, fluorescence, second order Raman effect, infrared spectroscopy, etc.
&lt;strong&gt;It is perhaps not well known that X-ray topography was discovered in this laboratory while studying the imperfections in diamond.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also worked on lattice dynamics, visual perception and many more topics and made contributions in those areas. It is almost impossible to give a complete description of his diverse research interests and achievements in a single article. More elaborate descriptions about the scientific works of Raman can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://ia803102.us.archive.org/6/items/cvramanpictorial00bang/cvramanpictorial00bang.pdf&quot;&gt;“C.V. Raman : A pictorial biography”&lt;/a&gt; a compilation by S Ramaseshan and C Ramachandra Rao.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pioneer-of-scientific-research-in-india&quot;&gt;Pioneer of scientific research in India&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout his career, Raman played an integral role in the development of the Institutes that he was part of. During the early 1900s, most of the Indian universities were teaching universities. There was a general belief that new science can not grow in the country and all the young bright minds were sent abroad for ‘training’. Raman, setting his own example, &lt;strong&gt;cultivated the culture of scientific research in India.&lt;/strong&gt;
He made an active effort to bring the best minds in the world, like Max Born, Schrodinger, Ewald, Peierls, Kuhn and many more to India. He thought, bringing such great minds could start a scientific movement in the country. Unfortunately, only Max Born could accept his invitation.
Raman founded &lt;strong&gt;the Indian Academy of sciences&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;1934&lt;/strong&gt; with the main objective of &lt;strong&gt;promoting progress and upholding the cause of science&lt;/strong&gt;. Central to this mission was to publish scientific monographs and journals through which research discoveries could be disseminated worldwide. The proceedings of the Indian Academy of sciences was considered as one of the top journals up until the 1950s. The annual meetings of the academy, so called &lt;strong&gt;‘traveling circus’&lt;/strong&gt;, were the main source of science encouragement in the country, with Raman usually being the &lt;strong&gt;star performer&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the academy publishes &lt;strong&gt;twelve journals&lt;/strong&gt; in different areas of science and science education, in addition to &lt;strong&gt;more than fifty books&lt;/strong&gt; that have been published over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: All the images in the article are taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ia803102.us.archive.org/6/items/cvramanpictorial00bang/cvramanpictorial00bang.pdf&quot;&gt;“C.V. Raman : A pictorial biography”&lt;/a&gt; a compilation by S Ramaseshan and C Ramachandra Rao.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgments&quot;&gt;Acknowledgments:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thank Saurabh Singh (Scientist, RRI Bangalore) for his timely inputs, K. Manjunath (Library, RRI Bangalore) and V. S. Naresh (Administration, RRI Bangalore) for allowing access to the RRI archives, without which this article would not have been possible. We also thank the RRI trust for their support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ia803102.us.archive.org/6/items/cvramanpictorial00bang/cvramanpictorial00bang.pdf&quot;&gt;“C.V. Raman : A pictorial biography”&lt;/a&gt; - A compilation by S Ramaseshan and C Ramachandra Rao, published by Indian Academy of Sciences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/110505a0&quot;&gt;“Molecular Diffraction of Light”&lt;/a&gt; - Published in the Nature journal in 1922&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dspace.rri.res.in/bitstream/2289/2193/1/1922%20Asutosh%20Mookerjee%20Silver%20Jubilee%20V2%20p179-185.pdf&quot;&gt;“The acoustical knowledge of the ancient Hindus”&lt;/a&gt; - Published in Asutosh Mookerjee Silver Jubilee Volume in 1922&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/science-day-raman-ketan</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/science-day-raman-ketan</guid>
        
        <category>Featured</category>
        
        <category>General</category>
        
        <category>Indian National Science Day</category>
        
        
        <category>Featured</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understanding the solar chromosphere through spectral lines</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This article takes the reader through a journey of inferring the cosmos - specifically our dear neighbour Sun - through various properties of light. The journey meanders through our work on understanding solar chromospheric properties through spectral lines, and seems to cluminate in the sea of questions raised by our work!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light is one of the most fundamental, complex and inherently mind blowing things to exist in this world. Every culture across the globe attributes (or attributed) great significance to light, while adding multiple layers of symbolism and meaning. Light has its influence right from the chloroplasts in plants converting water &amp;amp; nutrients to sugar and Oxygen, to the largest of solar panels to generate electricity for entire cities. Light is, in some sense, our window to this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is true for astronomers. Imagine an astronomer working  - I am pretty sure your immediate thought is a person looking through a telescope in the night sky. Well, you are pretty correct - in that most information about the universe comes to us through light! But light is not just what we &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt;: the radio frequency on which mobile phones operate is light, and so are the X-rays which are used to check for bone fractures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What kind of light exists depends on how it is generated in the first place. The simplest way to make light is to get objects hot. A hot iron rod glows red, while an arc welding plasma glows blue. Heat, and temperature are primary drivers of what kind of light comes out. This &lt;em&gt;colour&lt;/em&gt; of light is given by the wavelength (or the frequency) of light. The larger this frequency of light, smaller the wavelength is, and more the energy in light. X rays have a very short wavelength (and so high energy), while Radio waves have a very long wavelength (and low energy). Similarly, red light has a larger wavelength than blue (or violet) light. So, in general, hotter objects have more energy, and hence emit more in short wavelengths, while cooler objects have lesser energy, and emit more in longer wavelengths. This is the reason why X-rays are generally much more harmful than Radio waves&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun we see every day is obviously a hot object. So logically, we also expect it to give light corresponding to how hot it is. And this is quite true – the solar &lt;em&gt;surface&lt;/em&gt; or the solar disc we see in the sky is at 5500 Kelvin. Hence, it emits most of its energy near greenish-yellow light&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But all parts of the Sun do not preferentially emit this greenish-yellow light – rather, depending on the temperature, different parts of the Sun emit in different colours. In Fig. 1 below, I have displayed the same region of the Sun as seen in different wavelengths. The hottest plasma is seen in the 94 Å image, while the coolest is seen in the 2796 Å image - with temperature (approximately) reducing with increasing wavelength. Each structure contains material at different temperatures - this is because different structures form at different heights! A general rule of thumb in the solar atmosphere is “hotter stuff forms at greater height than cooler stuff”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, so the S shaped loop in the 94 Å image forms much higher than the structure in the 2796 Å image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vishal_chromosphere/image1_vishal_line.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 1: A solar flare as seen in different wavelengths (listed on top of each panel). Shorter wavelengths mean more energy. From 94 &amp;Aring; to 2796 &amp;Aring;, as temperature reduces, different structures in the solar atmosphere are clearly seen, from S shaped loops to longer loops to finally a dark sunspot-like patch from 1600 &amp;Aring; onwards! Images assembled from &lt;a href=&quot;https://sdo.gsfc.nasa.gov/&quot;&gt; AIA &lt;/a&gt; data (corona) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/iris/index.html&quot;&gt; Slit-Jaw Imager &lt;/a&gt;(chromosphere). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just one aspect of the light that comes to us. The other aspect is that the material which emits this light, also leaves an imprint on “how bright” the light is at different wavelengths. This is slightly different from the Thermal radiation, which depends &lt;b&gt;only&lt;/b&gt; on the temperature. The typical brightness at every wavelength for light coming due to an object being hot, looks somewhat like the top row in Fig. 2. Here, notice that the brightness shows some variation with wavelength (which, I remind you, is given by the colour of light) - but the essential point is that every wavelength has some amount of brightness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, check out the second row - corresponding to a Sodium atom. You will see that the brightness is present at &lt;strong&gt;discrete&lt;/strong&gt; locations in wavelength, and most of the wavelengths have no brightness. This is in stark contrast to the thermal radiation, and is followed similarly by all other elements listed in the rows below Sodium. But note that the pattern, or location &amp;amp; brightness of these &lt;strong&gt;spectral lines&lt;/strong&gt; of different elements is unique for each element. In a sense, spectral lines can be thought of as a fingerprint of atoms and molecules. Just like each human has a unique set of fingerprints, similarly each atom or molecule has a specific set of spectral lines as its signature. These lines you see are bright in specific wavelengths, and are called &lt;strong&gt;emission lines&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vishal_chromosphere/image3_vishal_line.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 2: Examples of many spectrum (=spectra). On the bottom most axis, the wavelength increases from 4000 &amp;Aring; (left) to more than 7000 &amp;Aring; (right). The top row shows what is called a continuous spectrum, which depends only on the temperature of the object. Each subsequent row shows how much bright light is in each wavelength, for different atoms listed to the left.
Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://openstax.org/books/astronomy/pages/5-3-spectroscopy-in-astronomy &quot;&gt;OpenStax &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers study the spectral lines of different objects like stars, galaxies, etc, and try to figure out which all atoms, ions and molecules are present in the object of study. Remember, what I have shown in Fig. 2 is the light coming from one vertical slit - that is why, the spectral lines are all seen as vertical lines. But this need not be the case - I can also look at approximately one point on the Sun (or even average over the vertical line), for example, and get its spectrum out. This exercise will give us a result similar to Fig. 3, where we just have the brightness of light for every wavelength. This is the kind of spectrum astronomers generally analyze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vishal_chromosphere/image2_vishal_line.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 3: The intensity of various spectral lines as a function of wavelength. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chiantidatabase.org/qug.html&quot;&gt;CHIANTI&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A side note here: The spectrum shown Fig. 3 is the brightness (or rather the &lt;strong&gt;intensity&lt;/strong&gt;) for every wavelength. We can then construct a similar spectrum for a large region of the Sun, and obtain such spectra for each point. Now, if we consider the intensity at, let’s say 2796 Å for each point, we will get an image similar to the last panel in Fig. 1. How cool is that!&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will now have many questions: why is the spectrum of individual elements only at specific wavelengths, and not everywhere? What conditions give rise to the &lt;em&gt;brightness&lt;/em&gt; of these lines? First off, you find the spectrum of elements at discrete wavelength locations because these arise from atomic transitions between two approximately fixed energy levels. The &lt;em&gt;quantum&lt;/em&gt; of Quantum mechanics gives rise to this discrete nature&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Next, the spectrum itself depends on, among other parameters, 4 critical properties: the temperature of the region where the spectrum is generated, density of the material giving rise to the spectrum, velocity of this material, and turbulence&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. These properties, under certain circumstances, can be easily inferred from just the spectrum of an atom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, note that the material which emits this light is a fluid (more precisely, plasma) in our case. Hence, the temperature and density of the plasma determine if a given spectral line will even form. So just knowing the fact that a given line is seen tells us the possible range of values temperature and quantity can take. Next, the brightness of the line is in most cases dominated by the density of plasma – more density, more brightness, but you do have the effect of atomic physics and temperature. Third, the wavelength where we expect the line brightness to peak can be shifted to different wavelengths too! This is called &lt;strong&gt;Doppler shift&lt;/strong&gt;. If the plasma is moving towards us, the shift is toward shorter wavelengths (called &lt;strong&gt;Blueshift&lt;/strong&gt;), and if the plasma is moving away from us, the shift is toward longer wavelengths (called &lt;strong&gt;Redshifts&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Finally, if you see in Fig. 3, the line does not immediately peak at one wavelength. Rather, it starts to increase from one wavelength, reaches a maximum, and then reduces. This is called the &lt;strong&gt;line width&lt;/strong&gt;, and is determined by the temperature, and turbulence in the plasma. Turbulence basically is a measure of how much fluctuation of different spatial sizes is present in the fluid - it is yet another measure of what the plasma we consider is like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So TLDR in summary, using spectral lines, we can get an estimate of local temperature, velocity, density and turbulence of these plasma parcels through spectral lines. So what is the big idea?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big idea is that some specific regions on the Sun are thought to give rise to a stream of particles called the solar wind. We know that these regions are important, but we don’t know at what height the solar wind starts to form. Now, the solar wind is basically a stream of particles coming out of the Sun. So if you are looking “down” on the Sun, you will see that the particles are coming towards you. This means the spectral line which the particles emit will be blueshifted. So the basic idea is that we study these Doppler shifts for plasma which correspond to different wavelengths (and so different heights and temperatures, like Fig. 1), and see where the blueshifts start!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, these regions, which are thought to give rise to the solar wind, are called &lt;em&gt;Coronal holes&lt;/em&gt; (CHs) - because they are seen as dark patches in the solar corona. In Fig. 4b below, all dark regions belong to CHs, while the brighter regions belong to &lt;em&gt;Quiet Sun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (QS). These regions appear very different in the solar corona. However, if we check what these regions look like at lower heights called the &lt;strong&gt;chromosphere&lt;/strong&gt;, the differences are reduced (see Fig. 4a)! Why so? Has this “vanishing” of difference got anything to do with the solar wind? Can we do specific studies of these regions, and figure out what causes these differences? Are they dependent on the underlying magnetic field in any way? This was our primary objective of study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this juncture, I should tell you that scientists have done extensive studies of the CHs and QS regions in the corona, and all of the information I have presented in the last two or so paragraphs was generated in the last three decades. So we do stand on the shoulders of other giants – while we do bring our own thought process to the table!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vishal_chromosphere/image5_vishal_line.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 4: An image of the CHs and surrounding QS region in the upper chromosphere (left panel) and the corona (right panel). The green lines demarcate CHs from QS in both the figures.
Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.04287&quot;&gt;Vishal.U et al., 2021 &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to our work: we studied &lt;strong&gt;one&lt;/strong&gt; spectral line (yep, just one line, and you will see how much information we can infer from it!), and its properties across both the CHs and QS regions. This line forms due to a transition of the C+ ion (called CII by astrophysicists) at a wavelength of 1334 Å. How do we know the correct wavelength? We can perform controlled experiments in labs on Earth and figure it out. Now, you have already seen how there is not a great difference between CH and QS in the intensity image of Fig. 4a. Similar results hold if we look at what the plasma velocity and line width are in Fig. 5. This tells us that if I were to &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; tell you where the CH and QS regions are, you cannot figure them out from either the intensity, velocity, or the width of the C II line. Thus, on a gross scale, the CH and QS are very similar!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting things happen if we account for the underlying magnetic field. How do we do this? We ask: what is the intensity in CH and QS at similar magnetic field strengths? Similarly, what are the velocities and line widths? The underlying magnetic field strength&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; might be similar, but the structure of the magnetic field can be different! The structure of magnetic field (a.k.a magnetic topology) is important, because we know that the CHs are regions where the magnetic field comes out predominantly in open lines&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, while in QS the same magnetic field comes as short closed loops. These differences are seen clearly in the corona – but are they also seen in the chromosphere?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vishal_chromosphere/image4_vishal_line.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 5: Velocity (left) and line width (right) of the C II line in CH and QS. The positive velocity is called “redshift” and tells how fast plasma is moving away from us, while the negative velocity is called “blueshift”, and tells how fast plasma is moving towards us. The larger line width means the line is broader, indicating larger turbulence effects and some non trivial effects.
Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.04287&quot;&gt;Vishal.U et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out it is the case! We can indeed differentiate between CH and QS if we consider regions with similar magnetic field strength. In Fig. 6, the black dots correspond to the average of quantity in Y-axis (Intensity, velocity, width) for regions with similar magnetic field strength (in X-axis). On an average, you see that the QS intensity is larger than the CH intensity in Fig. 6a – reminiscent of the differences in the corona, and seen statistically here. So one question is answered: CHs and QS are already differentiated in the chromosphere, but you can see this only statistically!&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, look at panel (b) of the same figure. The velocity is mostly positive - indicating plasma moving away from us, and down towards the photosphere. Thus, the chromosphere is, on average, flowing downwards into the Sun. However, it is interesting to see that at 40 Gauss, a switchover occurs: for less field strength, the QS has plasma flowing down faster, while it is CH for larger field strength. This is counter intuitive – if the solar wind comes out and towards us in the CH, why is plasma moving away from us in CH?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, see panel (c) of the same figure. The line width is seen to increase with field strength. This tells us that the profiles are getting broader, possibly implying larger turbulence with increasing field strength. Here too, CHs are broader than QS for large field strengths!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vishal_chromosphere/image7_vishal_line.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 6: Different properties of CH (black) and QS (orange) as a function of magnetic field strength (|B|).
Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.04287&quot;&gt; Vishal.U et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things don’t stop here. The velocity panel in Fig. 6b raises many questions. And so, we repeat the analysis with a tweak - this time, we consider the blueshifts and redshifts separately. Why so? This is important to understand if the field strength has preferentially some effect on the blueshifts and redshifts, which get averaged out in Fig. 6b. And so, we check what the speeds look like in Fig.7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In panel (a) of Fig. 7, the CHs have larger blueshifts over QS, telling us plasma is indeed preferentially moving towards us in the CHs. Thus, in principle, these blueshifts could be a signature of the solar wind. Now we are in business!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In panel (b), we check what the downflows look like. It seems for regions with large field strength, plasma is flowing into the Sun faster in CHs over QS. This was the signature which confused us in Fig. 6b. Why does the CH, which is understood to be a source of particles coming out towards the Earth, have particles going into the Sun, and away from the Earth preferentially? Are we doing something wrong? Or are the spectral profiles, and thus the process which generates these lines different in CHs and QS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out it is not the case. I will not show the plot here (already there is an overdose of information – too much of a good thing is also not good! :P), but we find that the spectral profiles are very similar in both CH and QS. Thus, it tells us that the processes which give rise to these profiles are similar in both the regions – the differences are coming out only because of the differences in the magnetic field topology of CHs and QS!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/vishal_chromosphere/image6_vishal_line.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 7: The velocity variation with magnetic field strength, for regions with only upflows (left) and only downflows (right) for CHs (black) and QS (orange).
Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.04287 &quot;&gt; Vishal.U et al., 2021 &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, through this work, we find that the CHs and QS might appear similar overall, but the differentiation in chromosphere is seen clearly if we consider regions with similar magnetic field strength. This differentiation is seen clearly as less intensity and excess line width in CHs over QS. The differentiation is clearly seen to arise primarily due to the magnetic field topology, and not due to fundamental differences in the way these lines form. However, our work poses a bunch of fundamental questions: Why is plasma flowing faster away from us in CHs over QS, when these CHs are supposed to be the sources of solar wind? Does this “redshift” bear any relation to the solar wind? How do these results tie up with analysis done for lines which form at higher temperatures (and hence, in the transition region &amp;amp; corona), and lower temperatures (lower &amp;amp; mid chromosphere)? And do the blueshifts we find in Fig. 7b have any relation with the solar wind?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To know more, and understand what happens next, keep watching this space!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021arXiv210904287U/abstract&quot;&gt; Properties of the C II 1334 Å line in Coronal Hole and Quiet Sun as observed by IRIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Vishal Upendran&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Durgesh Tripathi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Inter University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics, Pune, 411007, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;But don’t worry too much. The amount of X-rays given in hospitals do not cause any harm! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is an exercise for you - go look up why we see the Sun more yellow than green! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To know more on why this is the case, refer to my other article on the coronal heating problem! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As we will see later, plasma flowing up or down will change this location! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Check out this cool &lt;a href=&quot;https://openstax.org/books/astronomy/pages/5-3-spectroscopy-in-astronomy&quot;&gt;reference&lt;/a&gt; for more information. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Technically I should call it “non-thermal effect”, and it may result due to various reasons. Turbulence is supposedly one of the reasons giving rise to this effect. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Checkout this cool link for more info on &lt;a href=&quot;https://imagine.gsfc.nasa.gov/features/yba/M31_velocity/spectrum/doppler_more.html&quot;&gt;Doppler shifts&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I have talked in detail on the Coronal holes in the solar wind article, and on Quiet Sun in the nanoflare heating article. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Magnetic field strength = Bx2+By2+Bz2. The individual B can be different, while the sum squared remains the same! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When I say open, I mean that these field lines close at distances far larger than the size of our CH, on the Sun. Remember, we cannot have truly open fields since magnetic monopoles do not exist! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Note that this question was also answered by Pradeep Kayshap et al 2018 for the Mg II line, which also forms in the chromosphere. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/solar-chromosphere-spectral-lines-vishal</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/solar-chromosphere-spectral-lines-vishal</guid>
        
        <category>Solar chromosphere</category>
        
        <category>solar wind</category>
        
        <category>spectral lines</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Astrobiology: Exploring the universe for signs of extra-terrestrial life</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The only life forms we know about are the ones that exist on Earth. Due to advancements in space exploration, it has become possible to send rovers, probes, space crafts, and telescopes in further deep space. With the help of these space missions and various other tools, astrobiologists are trying to find signatures of life on other planets, exoplanets, and various moons.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.	Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;Is life a cosmic phenomenon?&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;Are we alone in the universe?&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us have wondered about it at some point in our lives. Perhaps only a few would have wondered about what exactly is life. This might sound philosophical at first but it is equally scientific. Astrobiology tries to find answers to all these questions. It is the science that seeks to understand the story of life in the universe. We have not found explicit evidence of life so far but with unceasing curiosity and an inherent urge for exploration, scientists have discovered a lot. Being a multidisciplinary field, Astrobiology brings people with diverse backgrounds together to achieve a common goal – the search for life beyond Earth and beyond the solar system. The origin of life on Earth is a great mystery and therefore scientists are investigating the problem in several different ways.  Some are studying life on our own planet. Some are seeking out life or fossil life on other planets or moons in our solar system. Others are trying to detect life in other solar systems, either by measuring life’s effects on the atmospheres of distant planets or by measuring artificial radiation like radio signals that may be produced by advanced life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.	Life on Earth:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only know the nature of life as it exists on Earth. It is built around compounds that contain elements such as carbon, nitrogen, hydrogen and oxygen. Complex sequences of these elements bond together, forming the very building blocks of life. They form essential organic molecules, such as carbohydrates, amino acids, lipids and nucleic acids (DNA and RNA). However, these organic molecules did not naturally exist on Earth during the Hadean eon (4.0 billion years ago and preceding the existence life forms). The elements required existed only in inorganic form, bound up within the rocks, atmosphere and the early ocean.
It is estimated that life on Earth began at least 3.5 billion years ago, because that is the age of the oldest rocks with fossil evidence of life on Earth. Researchers suggest that in order to understand how life began on Earth, we need to understand the specific environmental conditions and other requirements that must be satisfied to allow this to occur. What are the habitability requirements of known Earth life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental habitability requirements are certainly some of the commonalities of life on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;•	Energy:&lt;/strong&gt;
A source of energy is necessary for metabolism and to maintain the functions carried out by a cell. Life on Earth uses either solar energy or chemical energy sources that include both organic (carbon) compounds and inorganic elements and molecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;•	Common essential elements:&lt;/strong&gt;
All known Earth life uses the same main set of elements to form biomolecules (CHNOPS) and shares a common carbon-based biochemistry. Carbon is an excellent element from which to build life, because carbon forms macromolecules with a variety of other elements and itself. Carbon forms primarily covalent bonds (compared to ionic bonds), and carbon-based molecules are stable in the presence of water and oxygen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;•	Solvent:&lt;/strong&gt;
A solvent to host chemical interactions is considered a universal requirement for all life. With extensive evidence that all Earth life needs water specifically as the solvent, many astrobiologists consider water to be the most probable solvent for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When considering whether an environment or planet is habitable, at a minimum, scientists take into account the potential energy source (or sources), the ambient chemical composition and whether this composition is suitable to build biomass, and the availability of a solvent. Additionally, there are physical constraints upon life (e.g., temperature, pressure, pH, salinity, radiation, metal toxicity) such that the presence of these habitability requirements may be necessary but not sufficient for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.1 Life on Earth is divided into three domains:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Archaea, Bacteria, and Eukarya (or Eucarya);&lt;/b&gt; Single-celled organisms are common in all three domains, and all organisms in the domains Archaea and Bacteria are single-celled. All multicellular organisms fall within the domain Eukarya. The term ‘‘prokaryotes’’ has traditionally been used to describe single-celled organisms that do not contain a nucleus, organelles, or a cytoskeleton (collectively, the domains Bacteria and Archaea). The majority of life on Earth is microbial, and astrobiologists extrapolate from that fact to conclude that the majority of any extraterrestrial life that may possibly exist is also likely to be microbial. Archaea and Bacteria are the focus of astrobiological studies due to the diversity of metabolic strategies utilized by them and their ability to thrive in extreme habitats, their pivotal role in Earth’s biogeochemical cycling, and the fact that single-celled organisms dominated the early history of life on Earth. Bacteria and Archaea harbour the vast majority of the genetic diversity of life on Earth. Scientists estimate that, to date, less than 1% of microbial life has been successfully cultivated (e.g., grown in the laboratory). Therefore, molecular methods that do not require cultivation are also used to detect the presence and genetic capabilities of microbes through DNA (metagenomics), RNA and gene expression activity (metatranscriptomics), and transcribed proteins (metaproteomics). These techniques have demonstrated that microbial populations are highly complex and that we have only begun to elucidate the full extent and capabilities of microbial life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 1: A phylogenetic tree based on rRNA data, emphasizing the separation of bacteria, archaea, and eukaryotes, as proposed by Carl Woese, George E. Fox et al. in 1990. Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.87.12.4576&quot;&gt;Carl Woese et al. (1990)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2 Prevalence of life in extreme environments:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When space agencies first began to explore the Solar System, scientists were not sure what they would find on the surfaces of planets like Mars and Venus. When space missions revealed Mars to be a frigid desert, and Venus a boiling cauldron, void of any obvious signs of life, astrobiologists began to wonder… what are the limits of habitability for life as we know it? How hot is too hot? How cold is too cold? How much acid can cells handle, and how little water can life survive on? Answering questions like these opened an entire field of study known as &lt;b&gt;extremophile research&lt;/b&gt;, where scientists examine the adaptations of organisms in conditions that are considered ‘extreme’ for life on Earth. These hardy lifeforms can help us better understand how life as we know it might originate, evolve, and reproduce in harsh environments in the Solar System and beyond. On a tour of extreme environments on Earth, a good place to start is with terrestrial hot springs. Good examples include Yellowstone National park in the United States, Rotorua in New Zealand and Puga hot spring in Ladakh, India These environments were the first to draw the interest of astrobiologists that study the limits of life on Earth, and they are arguably the first environment in which an extremophile, Thermus aquaticus was isolated and documented by scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 2: Aerial view of Grand Prismatic Spring; Hot Springs, Midway &amp;amp; Lower Geyser Basin, Yellowstone National Park. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/features/yell/slidefile/thermalfeatures/hotspringsterraces/midwaylower/Images/17708.jpg&quot;&gt;Jim Peaco, National Park Service&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These springs are where geothermally heated water from underground rises to the planet’s surface. They can act as a source of water, energy, and nutrients for living cells. The water boiling up from below can carry a wide variety of minerals and reduced chemical species that certain microbes can use as a source of energy. Microorganisms have been found here living in pools of up to 206 degrees Fahrenheit (97ºC). The composition of the water depends on many different factors, such as its source and the types of rock and soil it travels through. It’s not just the heat that challenges life’s survival in hot springs. Some springs have water that is very acidic, others have water that is extremely alkaline. Gases at concentrations poisonous to humans, and other animals, bubble up with the water. The rock and liquid can contain heavy metals like arsenic and lead, along with lots of other minerals and particulates. Some pools can be extremely salty, and are rich in potassium and sulphate. High temperatures also mean less dissolved oxygen, so many hydrothermal pools are low in oxygen content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The multitude of harsh conditions present in terrestrial hot springs also means that it isn’t only thermophiles that live in these environments. There are acidophiles, alkaliphiles, and many other types of organisms. Sometimes scientists find extremophiles that use multiple adaptations to survive (polyextremophiles). On Earth, wherever we find liquid water, we find life, whether in bubbling hot springs, drops of brine inside ice, or films of water around minerals deep in the crust.
Up until 1977, scientists believed that all life on Earth was in some way dependent upon sunlight for energy. The discovery of hydrothermal vents showed that life could thrive independent of the Sun. Suddenly, scientists had an Earthly example of how life might survive on ocean worlds in the outer Solar System, such as Jupiter’s moon Europa, or Saturn’s moon Enceladus. These moons are thought to harbor oceans of dark, liquid water beneath their icy surfaces. If hydrothermal vents are present, those oceans could be habitable for life as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3	How do we search for signs of life beyond Earth?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astrobiological exploration is founded upon the premise that biosignatures encountered in space will be recognizable as presence of extraterrestrial life. A &lt;b&gt;biosignature&lt;/b&gt; is any substance – such as an element, isotope, or molecule – or phenomenon that provides scientific evidence of past or present life. The usefulness of a biosignature is determined not only by the probability of life creating it but also by the improbability of non-biological (abiotic) processes producing it. Concluding that evidence of an extraterrestrial life form (past or present) has been discovered requires proving that a possible biosignature was produced by the activities or remains of life. As with most scientific discoveries, discovery of a biosignature will require evidence building up until no other explanation exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we can look for atmospheric gases such as oxygen or methane that can be produced by life. Such planetary features that indicate life are biosignatures. The simultaneous presence of oxygen and methane is evidence for life because these two gases should quickly react with each other unless a biosphere is producing great amounts of them, which prevents equilibrium. Microbial life will readily consume hydrogen or carbon monoxide gas, so an abundance of either of these might be considered an &lt;b&gt;anti-biosignature&lt;/b&gt; for a planet in the habitable zone.
&lt;b&gt;Eg.&lt;/b&gt; The presence of methane in the atmosphere of Mars is an area of ongoing research. Because of its tendency to be destroyed in the atmosphere by photochemistry, the presence of excess methane on a planet can be an indication that there must be an active source. With life being the strongest source of methane on Earth, observing a disequilibrium in the methane abundance on another planet could be a viable biosignature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 3: This illustration portrays possible ways that methane might be added to Mars&apos; atmosphere (sources) and removed from the atmosphere (sinks). NASA&apos;s Curiosity Mars rover has detected fluctuations in methane concentration in the atmosphere. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/jpl/msl/pia19088&quot;&gt;NASA/JPL-Caltech&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.	Habitability in the solar system:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Earth it is absolutely logical to explore habitability of planets in our solar system. Planet Mars, in the inner solar system is a potential candidate to search for life beyond Earth. Simultaneously, moon of Jupiter (Europa) and moons of Saturn (Titan and Enceladus) in the outer solar system are also promising and extensive research is currently being conducted. The type of life that we are considering is simple, comparable to microbes, and the guiding principle concerns liquid water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.1 Mars:&lt;/strong&gt;
Many have imagined Mars, unlike Venus, as a potential abode for life. The atmosphere of Mars is much thinner than Earth’s. The Red Planet’s atmosphere contains more than 95% carbon dioxide and much less than 1% oxygen. Temperatures on Mars average about -81 degrees F. However, temperature’s range from around -220 degrees F in the wintertime at the poles, to +70 degrees F over the lower latitudes in the summer.
Mars Global Surveyor, which orbited from 1997 to 2006, mapped Mars and imaged sedimentary layers that implied many geologic cycles of erosion and deposition. In the early 21st century, the Mars Odyssey and Mars Express orbiters, along with Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter, discovered areas of clay minerals and salts, which may have formed in liquid water. Twin Mars Exploration Rovers landed in 2004, and found fossilized ripples from past liquid water and sedimentary rocks, while in 2008, NASA’s Phoenix Lander dug up subsurface ice in a polar region and measured soluble salts in the soil. Finally, in 2012, Curiosity Rover trundled towards a 5-kilometre-high mountain of sedimentary beds within a 150- kilometre-diameter crater named Gale. It found mudstones deposited from water. Nowadays, astrobiological interest in Mars concerns either biological traces from billions of years ago or microbial-like life that might possibly endure in the subsurface or underground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 4: Curiosity rover on a Martian sand dune. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/image-feature/jpl/pia20316/curiosity-self-portrait-at-martian-sand-dune&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mars’s current surface is hostile to life for three reasons. First, while ice exists for sure, no liquid water has been identified. The polar caps are water ice, topped with carbon dioxide ‘dry ice’ that grows when about 30 per cent of the atmosphere freezes at the winter pole. Also, above mid latitudes, ice cemented soil or permafrost lies just beneath the surface. In the tropics, afternoon temperatures in the top centimetre of soil rise above freezing, but there, ice turns to vapour before melting temperatures are reached. A second problem is no ozone layer, allowing harmful ultraviolet sunlight to reach the surface. Third, chemical reactions in the atmosphere make hydrogen peroxide— which settles to the surface, where they can destroy organics. While the surface is unpromising, geothermal heat underground might allow liquid water and life to exist. Evidence that liquid water used to be present suggests that Mars was once more habitable than today. Fluvial (stream-related) features in the landscape, including gullies, dried-up river valleys, deltas, and enormous channels are also indicative of the same. Moreover, the soil and rocks contain minerals that form in the presence of liquid water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.2 Jovian moon Europa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Galileo mission detected an induced magnetic field in Europa (a moon of Jupiter), providing compelling evidence for an ocean of liquid water beneath the surface. While the top surface of Europa is not habitable, it is still relevant to discuss here for several reasons: (1) surface materials may reflect the chemistry of a subsurface ocean and help us understand the conditions available to life there, and (2) materials brought to the surface from the ocean below may be the only way we can detect signs of life (e.g., organic matter or other biosignatures characterized spectroscopically on a future mission). Radiation from high-energy particles caught in Jupiter’s magnetic field causes oxidation of surface materials as the energy from radiation knocks electrons out of atoms. Radiolytically produced oxidants at the surface include O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. These may be subsequently cycled into the ice shell and ocean on timescales on the order of the age of the surface, 106 years, which is quite young on geological timescales, so these compounds could potentially oxidize more reduced chemical species in the ocean below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image5 : Europa, a jovian moon. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://photojournal.jpl.nasa.gov/catalog/PIA00502&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.3 Icy moons of Saturn :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.3.1 Enceladus :&lt;/strong&gt;
Enceladus is Saturn’s sixth largest moon and has active geology. In 2005, the spacecraft Cassini started multiple close flybys of Enceladus, revealing its surface and environment in greater detail. It orbits Saturn in an elliptical fashion resulting in varying gravitational forces from Saturn that flex and heat Enceladus. For reasons that are not fully understood, the heating is concentrated under Enceladus’ South pole. There, icy particles and gas spray out of parallel fractures dubbed tiger stripes. The jets contain traces of methane, ammonia, and organic compounds, along with salt. Enceladus has a rocky core, an icy shell, and an underground sea beneath the area of the jets. The jackpot combination of organic molecules, energy, and liquid water implies that life might exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image6.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 6 : Narrow jets of gas and icy particles erupt from the south polar region of Enceladus, contributing to the moon&apos;s giant plume. A cycle of activity in these small-scale jets may be periodically lofting extra particles into space, causing the overall plume to brighten dramatically. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/feature/jpl/enceladus-jets-surprises-in-starlight&quot;&gt;NASA/JPL/Space Science Institute&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.3.2 Titan :&lt;/strong&gt;
Titan, the largest moon of Saturn, is also of astrobiological interest because it is the only satellite in the Solar System to have a thick atmosphere. In fact, the air pressure at Titan’s surface is 1.5 bar, which is 50 per cent larger than that at the Earth’s surface. The atmosphere of 95 per cent nitrogen and 5 per cent methane provides a 10°C greenhouse effect, but the sunlight at Saturn’s distance is one hundred times less intense than at Earth, so Titan’s surface is incredibly cold at –179°C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 7 : NASA&apos;s Cassini spacecraft sees bright methane clouds drifting in the summer skies of Saturn&apos;s moon Titan, along with dark hydrocarbon lakes and seas clustered around the north pole. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/images/pia21615-northern-summer-on-titan&quot;&gt;NASA/JPL/Space Science Institute&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Titan’s atmosphere contains a smoggy haze of hydrocarbons. At high altitude, ultraviolet sunlight breaks up methane molecules (CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;) and subsequent reactions build up hydrocarbons including ethane (C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;), acetylene (C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;), propane (C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;), benzene (C&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;), and reddish-brown particles containing polyaromatic hydrocarbons. The particles are called tholins. The products derived from methane sediment out of the atmosphere. In fact, about 20 per cent of Titan’s surface is covered in tropical dunes that are made of sand-sized particles, which are at least coated with organics if not made of them. At the poles, over 400 lakes are mixtures of liquid propane, ethane, and methane, with extraordinary beaches made of particles of benzene and acetylene.
Methane on Titan behaves like water on Earth and forms clouds, rain, and rivers. Most of our knowledge about Titan comes from the Cassini–Huygens mission, which arrived in 2004. Huygens landed on Titan in 2005. Titan flexes too much to be entirely solid, which is evidence that Titan has a subsurface ocean which might exist below an icy crust. Two types of life might exist on Titan: Earth-like life in the subsurface ocean; and non-DNA based life or life which has a different biochemistry in the hydrocarbon lakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.	Habitability beyond solar system :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding exoplanets is crucial before identifying a habitable one. With the vast distances involved, the search is difficult but nonetheless astronomers have developed two classes of methods. The first, indirect detection, looks for stellar properties, such as position or brightness, which are affected by the presence of unseen planets. The second is direct detection of a planet with an image or a spectrum of its light.
For astrobiology, the most important techniques are direct detections that capture light from a planet. Direct detection is challenging because a planet is a dim body close to a vastly brighter star. Nonetheless, telescopes in space, such as the Hubble Space Telescope, James Webb Telescopes and extremely large telescopes on the ground have accomplished direct detection using a coronagraph, which is a mask to block the starlight. With density measurements, there are increasing clues about which exoplanets are made of gas, rock, water, or some mixture. We care most about exoplanets with liquid water right at the surface. These have the chance of a biosphere that pumps lots of gases into an atmosphere. In principle, such biogenic gases are detectable in the light from the planet and might indicate life.
If a planet is too far away from its host star it ices over, and if it’s too close it’s too hot for liquid water. The term habitable zone (HZ) refers to the region around a star in which an Earth-like planet could maintain liquid water on its surface at some instant in time. We specify a particular time because stars age and brighten or dim, so the HZ moves. The closest star to Earth is a triple-star system called Alpha Centauri which is at a 4.25 – 4.35 light years distance. The list of potentially habitable exoplanets is mostly based on estimates of habitability by the Habitable Exoplanets Catalog (HEC), and data from the NASA Exoplanet Archive. The HEC is maintained by the Planetary Habitability Laboratory at the University of Puerto Rico at Arecibo. Surface planetary habitability is thought to require orbiting at the right distance from the host star for liquid surface water to be present, in addition to various geophysical and geodynamical aspects, atmospheric density, radiation type and intensity, and the host star’s plasma environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.	Conclusion :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astrobiology is intriguing and challenging at the same time. Research done on origin of life and extremophiles is used to extrapolate to other planets and various moons in the solar system. Astrobiologists are primarily interested in the subsurface water oceans of these planets. Overall, follow the water has been the motto. All space agencies keep executing ambitious space missions probes, rovers, spacecrafts, telescopes, etc. Another aspect of Astrobiology which pushes science boundaries is exoplanet search. Habitable planets beyond our solar system are actively being sought after. Bio-signatures help us detect presence of Earth-like life in our solar system and beyond it. With the advancement in technology for space exploration one can expect that humans will exist as a multiplanetary species in future. There is a possibility that we are alone in the universe or who knows we might find life elsewhere. Till then let’s keep our fingers crossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6.	References :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ntrs.nasa.gov/citations/20180004101&quot;&gt;NASA Astrobiology Primer v2.0&lt;/a&gt; Shawn D. Domagal-Goldman and Katherine E. Wright&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.veryshortintroductions.com/view/10.1093/actrade/9780199586455.001.0001/actrade-9780199586455&quot;&gt;Astrobiology- A Very Short Introduction&lt;/a&gt; by David C. Catling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wiley.com/en-ie/Astrobiology:+Understanding+Life+in+the+Universe,+2nd+Edition-p-9781119550358&quot;&gt;Astrobiology : Understanding life in the Universe&lt;/a&gt; by Charles Cockell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/astrobiology-shreya/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/astrobiology-shreya/</guid>
        
        <category>Astrobiology</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrobiology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A list of scholarships for women in Science</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A significant fraction of the advances in science and technology arises due to seminal contributions by women - all the while tackling a series of battles against social norms and skewed opportunities. Even today, there exists a lack of representation of women in higher education, scientific research and industry. For instance, women make up almost 43% of STEM (i.e. Science Technology Engineering and Medicine) graduates in the country, but just 14% scientists and engineers in universities/institutions. A “leaky STEM pipeline” is formed as only 3-6% of women enroll for a PhD in STEM. Even though many injustices exist as hurdles to women empowerment, various governments and organizations have come forward in combating these issues.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most effective ways to empower women is through education. An educated woman has the capability, knowledge and independence to take up various avenues in life independently - especially in STEM. Education starts not just at a very specialized stage, but right from primary school – where children are instilled with the dreams of exploring the edge of the universe to breaking open the smallest of particles. Poverty, the unfortunate condition that plagues a large part of our country is especially detrimental to the education of girls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, in this article, we present our humble attempt at compiling a set of scholarships which are aimed at covering the education costs of girls. We have presented the scholarship data in three groups - school education, undergraduate studies, and post graduation. For each group we have presented the eligibility criteria and the scholarship amount in multiple columns, while we have linked the homepage of each scholarship for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not claim this to be an exhaustive list - in fact, this will be a “living” document which shall get updated as and when we get more information. If you, the reader, think we have missed an important scholarship scheme, please give us a shout out through the comments section below, or by contacting us directly through the form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;../scholarship.html&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;1200&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/scholarship-women-science</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/scholarship-women-science</guid>
        
        <category>popular</category>
        
        <category>women-in science</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
