<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> Welcome to CosmicVarta.</title>
    <description> Platform for promoting Indian astronomy research to the public.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 20:13:56 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 20:13:56 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sir C. V. Raman: Raman effect and beyond</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We Indians celebrate &lt;strong&gt;National Science Day&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;strong&gt;28th February&lt;/strong&gt; each year to mark the &lt;strong&gt;discovery of the Raman effect&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;Sir C. V. Raman&lt;/strong&gt;. Some of Raman’s discoveries like the &lt;strong&gt;Raman effect (for which he was awarded the Nobel prize), Raman-Nath theory, his studies on Brillouin scattering, the soft mode process&lt;/strong&gt;, etc. are so well known and outstanding, that they tend to overshadow many of his other elegant and significant contributions to the science. We attempt to highlight a few of Raman’s discoveries such that they &lt;strong&gt;portray a more complete picture of Sir C. V. Raman and his contributions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/cvraman.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Sir Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman&lt;br /&gt;(7 November 1888 - 21 November 1970)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sir C. V. Raman&lt;/strong&gt; occupies a very special place in the &lt;strong&gt;scientific landscape of India&lt;/strong&gt;. His contributions to science were monumental both in &lt;strong&gt;scale and scope&lt;/strong&gt;. He also played a pivotal role in &lt;strong&gt;shaping Indian science institutions and redefined the way in which science was done in India&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Max Born&lt;/strong&gt;, a nobel prize winning german scientist who was instrumental in the development of the quantum mechanics, had this to say about Raman,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;
“There is no Indian physicist of the rank of Raman. No man can compare with him in vigor or intensity.”
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-curious-case-of-a-relentless-experimentalist&quot;&gt;The curious case of a relentless experimentalist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the year 1921. You could find a turbaned Indian man on a ship returning from Europe to India, running all around, with his nicol prisms and cardboard tubes, collecting sea water from the depths of the ocean. The visual beauty of the Mediterranean ocean had bewitched him.
Not so long ago, Lord Rayleigh had shown that the blue color of the sky is due to scattering of light by air molecules. However, according to Lord Rayleigh, the blue color of the deep ocean was due to reflection of the sky in the water.
Raman showed, by a simple experiment he performed on board the ship, that the blue color of the ocean is due to molecular scattering and not just due to the reflection of the sky. He quenched the sky’s reflection with a nicol prism at the Brewster angle and found that the blue color &lt;i&gt;“far from being impoverished by suppression of the sky reflection was wonderfully improved thereby”&lt;/i&gt;.
In 1922, he wrote the celebrated monograph &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/110505a0&quot;&gt;“Molecular Diffraction of Light”&lt;/a&gt; and so began the saga of a single-minded man pursuing his vision with a stamina and persistence never seen before, which eventually lead to the discovery of the Raman effect and many other outstanding contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weak-fluorescence&quot;&gt;Weak Fluorescence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 1923, KR Ramanathan, one of Raman’s students, studied the scattering of light in water. Sunlight was focussed on the liquid and the scattered light was observed through a system of complementary filters, each filter completely cutting off the light transmitted by the other. Nothing should have been observed if there had been no change of color during the scattering process. However, a track of scattered light could be observed showing there was indeed a change in the color of light during scattering. This was attributed to a “weak fluorescence” due to impurities which were believed to be present. Raman was not convinced with this explanation though.
This “weak fluorescence” was not completely depolarised (as true fluorescence should have been) and the amount of depolarisation changed with wavelength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-raman-effect&quot;&gt;THE RAMAN EFFECT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/raman_spectra.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Sir C. V. Raman with the spectrograph (Top) and the first Raman spectra photographed (Bottom)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/raman_spectra_news.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Newspaper announcements of the discovery of the Raman effect
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 1927, the so-called polarised “weak fluorescence” was observed again by S Venkateswaran in pure glycerine with greater intensity. Due to limited availability of S Venkateswaran, Raman persuaded KS Krishnan, one of his brightest students, to set up experiments to find “weak fluorescence” in various materials. Raman and Krishnan worked together continuously and detected the polarized “weak fluorescence” in all the liquids, gasses and solids they examined.
According to Krishan, Raman personally verified all the liquids exhibited this phenomenon. Raman was so excited about the discovery that he rushed to Krishan’s home at night to inform him that their observations were related to the Kramers-Heisenberg process they were looking for all these years.
A note was sent to &lt;strong&gt;the Nature journal&lt;/strong&gt; about the discovery. However, Raman continued his experiments, mostly by himself since the observed phenomenon was not yet fully understood.
On &lt;strong&gt;February 28th 1928&lt;/strong&gt;, Raman examined the scattered light with a direct vision spectroscope and found that the classical and modified scattering appear in the spectrum as separate regions with a distinct dark region between them, a clear demonstration of a change of wavelength in scattering.
The &lt;strong&gt;Nobel Prize in Physics 1930&lt;/strong&gt; was awarded to Raman &lt;strong&gt;“for his work on the scattering of light and for the discovery of the effect named after him.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/nobel_prize.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Raman’s Nobel medal and citation
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;indian-musical-instruments-and-acoustics&quot;&gt;Indian musical instruments and acoustics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before Raman started working on the scattering of Light, he was fascinated by waves… sound waves! Raman’s father, R Chandrasekhara Iyer was a teacher of Physics and Mathematics and a proficient violinist. That must have influenced him to take interest in the physics of sound waves. Raman himself played violin. At the age of 16, when he was a student of the Presidency college, Madars, Raman commenced his acoustic research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/veena.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Illustration of a Veena
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He investigated whether his intuition that the veena produces the most exquisite musical sound is due to sentiment or has a sound physical basis. The bridge of the veena is so cunningly constructed that the Helmholtz law, which states that the position at which the string is plucked cannot be a node, is violated. Thus this instrument produces innumerable harmonics making its sound closest in harmonic content to the human voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/tabla.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;The mridangam and tabla produce a succession of musically harmonic overtones in the same way as any stringed instrument
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sharp ear with a keen interest in music can detect musical overtones in the sound of the mridangam and the tabla. Raman discovered that the heterogeneous loading of their membranes can produce harmonics - so that in the hands of the masters, the Indian drum is similar to a stringed instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diffraction-of-light-by-ultrasonic-waves---raman-nath-theory&quot;&gt;Diffraction of light by ultrasonic waves - Raman-Nath Theory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light is a form of electromagnetic radiation. Young’s double slit experiment conclusively showed that the interference pattern can be obtained from interaction of light with matter. How about the interaction of light with matter waves!
Raman-Nath theory explained a remarkable optical phenomenon that occurs when a parallel beam of light is diffracted by ultrasonic waves. In modern electro-optic instrumentation, the phenomenon of diffraction of light by ultrasonic waves is utilized in acousto-optic spectrometers, which analyze the electrical signal to obtain its power spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;colors-in-nature&quot;&gt;Colors in Nature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raman always had a huge fascination for colors. In the institute that he had built for himself after retirement (now Raman Research Institute), he started building his collection of colorful minerals gathered from all across the world. The collection includes limestones, marbles, alabaster, gypsums, tourmalines, agates, quartzites, jades, amethysts, fluorites, micas, serpentines, iolites, malachites, lapis lazuli and feldspars. Raman studied several of the exquisite optical phenomena displayed by these minerals. Due to lack of basic facilities during the initial days of his new institute, he had to mostly rely on the beam of sunlight to explore the optics of these substances. Even with such simple setups, it is remarkable that he could extract a substantial amount of information about these minerals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/mineral_01.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/mineral_02.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Raman’s collection of minerals
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birds are a delight to watch! Raman was very curious about the optical characteristic and the color distribution in birds, since it was so different in different parts of the same bird, in different specimens and in different species that no single explanation would suffice. He would invoke every known optics concept to try to explain these phenomena. He published only one paper on this topic; however talked about it a lot. The interest was not just limited to birds though. “Birds, Beetles and Butterflies” was his favorite title for the talk. He gave dozens of lectures on this subject, each one unique!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;diamond&quot;&gt;Diamond&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after the discovery of the Raman effect, C Ramaswamy, Raman’s younger brother, asked him to suggest a research problem which he could pursue. Seeing the diamond ring of the newly wed Ramaswamy sported on his finger, Raman suggested the study of scattering in diamond. The famous 1332 cm&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; Raman line of diamond was discovered in the spectrum. Using a 140-carat diamond that was borrowed from the Maharaja of Darbhanga, Bhagavantam, one of Raman’s pupils confirmed this result and also recorded the complex luminescence spectrum around 4152 &lt;span&gt;Å&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raman says this about diamonds,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;
“With their perfect geometric forms and their smooth lustrous beauty they look absolutely fresh from nature’s crucible, although actually taken from sedimentary formations a thousand million years old. The strongly marked curvature of the crystal faces and the smoothly rounded edges are a surprising feature of these crystals”
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/science_day_raman_ketan_images/raman_diamond.PNG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Sir C. V. Raman with beloved diamond
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In continuation with his work on diamonds, he also carried out pioneering studies of the thermo-optic behavior of other solids, their photo-elastic and magneto-optic properties, fluorescence, second order Raman effect, infrared spectroscopy, etc.
&lt;strong&gt;It is perhaps not well known that X-ray topography was discovered in this laboratory while studying the imperfections in diamond.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also worked on lattice dynamics, visual perception and many more topics and made contributions in those areas. It is almost impossible to give a complete description of his diverse research interests and achievements in a single article. More elaborate descriptions about the scientific works of Raman can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://ia803102.us.archive.org/6/items/cvramanpictorial00bang/cvramanpictorial00bang.pdf&quot;&gt;“C.V. Raman : A pictorial biography”&lt;/a&gt; a compilation by S Ramaseshan and C Ramachandra Rao.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pioneer-of-scientific-research-in-india&quot;&gt;Pioneer of scientific research in India&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout his career, Raman played an integral role in the development of the Institutes that he was part of. During the early 1900s, most of the Indian universities were teaching universities. There was a general belief that new science can not grow in the country and all the young bright minds were sent abroad for ‘training’. Raman, setting his own example, &lt;strong&gt;cultivated the culture of scientific research in India.&lt;/strong&gt;
He made an active effort to bring the best minds in the world, like Max Born, Schrodinger, Ewald, Peierls, Kuhn and many more to India. He thought, bringing such great minds could start a scientific movement in the country. Unfortunately, only Max Born could accept his invitation.
Raman founded &lt;strong&gt;the Indian Academy of sciences&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;1934&lt;/strong&gt; with the main objective of &lt;strong&gt;promoting progress and upholding the cause of science&lt;/strong&gt;. Central to this mission was to publish scientific monographs and journals through which research discoveries could be disseminated worldwide. The proceedings of the Indian Academy of sciences was considered as one of the top journals up until the 1950s. The annual meetings of the academy, so called &lt;strong&gt;‘traveling circus’&lt;/strong&gt;, were the main source of science encouragement in the country, with Raman usually being the &lt;strong&gt;star performer&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the academy publishes &lt;strong&gt;twelve journals&lt;/strong&gt; in different areas of science and science education, in addition to &lt;strong&gt;more than fifty books&lt;/strong&gt; that have been published over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: All the images in the article are taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ia803102.us.archive.org/6/items/cvramanpictorial00bang/cvramanpictorial00bang.pdf&quot;&gt;“C.V. Raman : A pictorial biography”&lt;/a&gt; a compilation by S Ramaseshan and C Ramachandra Rao.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgments&quot;&gt;Acknowledgments:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thank Suarabh Singh (Scientist, RRI Bangalore) for his timely inputs, K. Manjunath (Library, RRI Bangalore) and V. S. Naresh (Administration, RRI Bangalore) for allowing access to the RRI archives, without which this article would not have been possible. We also thank the RRI trust for their support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ia803102.us.archive.org/6/items/cvramanpictorial00bang/cvramanpictorial00bang.pdf&quot;&gt;“C.V. Raman : A pictorial biography”&lt;/a&gt; - A compilation by S Ramaseshan and C Ramachandra Rao, published by Indian Academy of Sciences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/110505a0&quot;&gt;“Molecular Diffraction of Light”&lt;/a&gt; - Published in the Nature journal in 1922&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dspace.rri.res.in/bitstream/2289/2193/1/1922%20Asutosh%20Mookerjee%20Silver%20Jubilee%20V2%20p179-185.pdf&quot;&gt;“The acoustical knowledge of the ancient Hindus”&lt;/a&gt; - Published in Asutosh Mookerjee Silver Jubilee Volume in 1922&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/science_day_raman_ketan/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/science_day_raman_ketan/</guid>
        
        <category>Featured</category>
        
        <category>General</category>
        
        <category>Indian National Science Day</category>
        
        
        <category>Featured</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A list of scholarships for women in Science</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A significant fraction of the advances in science and technology arises due to seminal contributions by women - all the while tackling a series of battles against social norms and skewed opportunities. Even today, there exists a lack of representation of women in higher education, scientific research and industry. For instance, women make up almost 43% of STEM (i.e. Science Technology Engineering and Medicine) graduates in the country, but just 14% scientists and engineers in universities/institutions. A “leaky STEM pipeline” is formed as only 3-6% of women enroll for a PhD in STEM. Even though many injustices exist as hurdles to women empowerment, various governments and organizations have come forward in combating these issues.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most effective ways to empower women is through education. An educated woman has the capability, knowledge and independence to take up various avenues in life independently - especially in STEM. Education starts not just at a very specialized stage, but right from primary school – where children are instilled with the dreams of exploring the edge of the universe to breaking open the smallest of particles. Poverty, the unfortunate condition that plagues a large part of our country is especially detrimental to the education of girls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, in this article, we present our humble attempt at compiling a set of scholarships which are aimed at covering the education costs of girls. We have presented the scholarship data in three groups - school education, undergraduate studies, and post graduation. For each group we have presented the eligibility criteria and the scholarship amount in multiple columns, while we have linked the homepage of each scholarship for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not claim this to be an exhaustive list - in fact, this will be a “living” document which shall get updated as and when we get more information. If you, the reader, think we have missed an important scholarship scheme, please give us a shout out through the comments section below, or by contacting us directly through the form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;../scholarship.html&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;1200&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/scholarship-women-science</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/scholarship-women-science</guid>
        
        <category>popular</category>
        
        <category>women-in science</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Voices of the Women in Science - A list of books on women scientists </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Progress is possible only when everyone capable of contributing is given an equal chance irrespective of gender, community and nationality. While there is a long way to go before this gap is fulfilled, it should be noted that we as a community have made considerable strides in meeting this agenda. Even at the dawn of independence, the majority of women were not even given a chance to study but now, in 70 years, we can happily say that women are not only earning degrees and doctorates but actively leading the world on major scientific, technological and industrial fronts!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) disciplines in India, as is in every other country, have an unequal gender work environment. In this regard, the United Nations General Assembly has declared February 11 as the &lt;strong&gt;International Day of Women and Girls in Science&lt;/strong&gt; to inspire and engage women and girls in STEM, with the hope that more girls take up science and research as a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the number of women in science and technology is less, their contributions are not! In order to celebrate their contributions, we at &lt;strong&gt;CosmicVarta&lt;/strong&gt; have collated a list of books that commemorate the immense contribution that women across the world have made to science with an intention to inspire and arouse a scientific temper in the reader. These books show us how these trailblazers, pioneers and path-breakers’ lives were and what inspired them to become scientists! This list is definitely not exhaustive and we hope that many more books will be written on the contemporary women scientists as well the future stars. Here is the list of books we have compiled:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
img {
  float: left;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-those-magnificent-women-and-their-flying-machines-isros-mission-to-mars&quot;&gt;1. Those Magnificent Women and their Flying Machines: ISRO’S Mission to Mars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Minnie Vaid, ‎ Speaking Tiger Books LLP, 2019&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/Those-Magificent-Women-3.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

The sky is definitely not the limit for Indian women scientists. India became the first Asian country to reach Mars, in 2013, that too in its first attempt. This mission, among others, was led by a group of brilliant and dedicated women scientists of ISRO. This book narrates how these magnificent women overcame gender-barriers and succeeded to achieve the impossible!   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/44578585-those-magnificent-women-and-their-flying-machines&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-kalpana-chawla-a-life&quot;&gt;2. Kalpana Chawla: A Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Anil Padmanabhan, Penguin, 2003&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/Kalpana-Chawla-a_life.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

Kalpana Chawla was the first woman of Indian origin to become an astronaut. Undeniably, she is an inspiration to millions of Indians, and not just women. Most school currilulum also have a chapter dedicated to this hero! While Kalpana Chawla died when returning from her second space flight on-board the space shuttle 'Columbia' in 2003, she is immortalized in this book.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3207063-kalpana-chawla&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-sunita-williams-a-star-in-space&quot;&gt;3. Sunita Williams: A Star in Space&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Aravinda Anatharaman, Puffin, 2014&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/sunita_williams.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

In simple words, the author brings to life the astronauts's amazing journey to reach the stars. Sunita Williams had to settle for second choices in her life multiple times, but by giving her best in everything, she became a swimmer turned pilot turned Astronaut! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25900000-sunita-williams&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-lilavatis-daughters-the-women-scientists-of-india&quot;&gt;4. Lilavati’s Daughters: The Women Scientists of India&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ramaswamy and Rohini Godbole, Indian Academy of Sciences, 2008&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/lilavathis_daughters.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;


This book is a collection of 100 biographical essays of Indian woman scientists working in a variety of fields such as astrophysics, botany, bio-organic chemistry, genetics These stories explain beautifully what being a woman scientist in India encompasses. It is a must read for every science enthusiast and college student.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8103504-lilavati-s-daughters&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-the-girls-guide-to-a-life-in-science&quot;&gt;5. The girl’s guide to a life in science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rohini Godbole, Ram Ramaswamy, Mandakini Dubey, Indian Academy of Sciences, 2014&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/the_girls_guide.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

Twenty five celebrated Indian women scientists, from the field of Physics to Zoology, give an overview of how they chose science as a career. The book deals with several questions of how, when, where and why that you might need to guide you for a life with science. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/31298592-the-girl-s-guide-to-a-life-in-science&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-scientifically-yours-selected-indian-women-scientists&quot;&gt;6. Scientifically Yours: Selected Indian Women Scientists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Gouhar Raza, Vigyan Prasar, 2016&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/scientifially_yours.jpeg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

This book consistes of interviews with some of the pioneering Indian women scientists and their rise to success in their repsective fields which is predominatly male-dominated. It showcases how these women used the obstacles they faced as a step to climb ahead instead of letting it be a wall obstructing them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/31214207-scientifically-yours&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-a-jewel-unearthed-bibha-chowdhuri-the-story-of-an-indian-woman-scientist&quot;&gt;7. A Jewel Unearthed: Bibha Chowdhuri: The Story of an Indian Woman Scientist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Singh, Rajinder; Roy, Suprakash C	Shaker, Verlag GmbH, Germany, 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/a_jewel_unearthed.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

This is a biography on the life and research of the Indian woman physicist, Bibha Chowdhuri. Born a hundred years ago, she displayed enormous courage and determination to choose a carrer in physics and work in the field of cosmic rays. Stories such as these show us how hard women struggled to make sure that opportunities are not lost to future generations of women and along the way become torch-bearers to break gender-barriers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/43783181-a-jewel-unearthed&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-31-fantastic-adventures-in-science-women-scientists-in-india&quot;&gt;8. 31 Fantastic Adventures in Science: Women Scientists in India&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Aashima Freidog and Nandita Jayaraj,	Puffin,	2019&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/31_adventures.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;
Thanks to the giantesses who came before us, there are hundreds of women standing on their shoulders today, working in the Indian academia. This book explores the life of thirty-one women scientists who work on diverse subjects, from environmental biotechnology to particle physics, palaeobiology to astrophysics. Through their innovative research, they help unravel the mysteries of the universe, find methods to live sustainably, cure life-threatening diseases and study animals and plants that are long gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50189302-31-fantastic-adventures-in-science&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-rocket-girl-the-story-of-mary-sherman-morgan-americas-first-female-rocket-scientist&quot;&gt;9. Rocket Girl: The Story of Mary Sherman Morgan, America’s First Female Rocket Scientist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;George D Morgan,	Prometheus Books,	2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/rocket_girl.jpg

&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

Mary Sherman's life was a complete mystery, thanks to the classified work she was involved in for most of her life. But when her son discovered that America was able to launch rockets mainly because if her contributions, he uncovered her life's story and presented it for the world to know in this biography. What he reveals is as fascinating as it is mysterious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17247967-rocket-girl&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-look-up-henrietta-leavitt-pioneering-woman-astronomer&quot;&gt;10. Look Up! Henrietta Leavitt, Pioneering Woman Astronomer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Robert Burleigh,	Simon &amp;amp; Schuster/Paula Wiseman Books,	2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/look_up.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;


Henrietta Leavitt measured star positions and sizes from photographs taken by the telescope at the Harvard College Observatory. Henrietta observed that certain stars had a fixed pattern to their changes which later made it possible for astronomers to measure distances, leading to our present understanding of the vast size of the universe. Henrietta's story makes a great inspirational read for young researchers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/15781175-look-up&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;11-the-glass-universe-how-the-ladies-of-the-harvard-observatory-took-the-measure-of-the-stars&quot;&gt;11. The Glass Universe: How the Ladies of the Harvard Observatory Took the Measure of the Stars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dava Sobel, Viking, 2016&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/The_Glass_Universe.jpg

&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

This is an extraordinary tale of a group of women who worked together and helped produce much of the data on which our understanding of the universe progressed during the 19th and 20th centuries. They carefully analyzed around half a million glass photographic plates which contained images of the universe taken from the Harvard telescopes. They helped discern what stars were made of, divided the stars into meaningful categories for further research, and found a way to measure distances across space by starlight.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29496512-the-glass-universe&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;12-rise-of-the-rocket-girls-the-women-who-propelled-us-from-missiles-to-the-moon-to-mars&quot;&gt;12. Rise of the Rocket Girls: The Women Who Propelled Us, from Missiles to the Moon to Mars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Nathalia Holt, Back Bay Books, 2017&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/rise_of_rocket_girls.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

'Rise of the Rocket Girls' is a story of women 'human computers', who displayed their mathemetical prowess to calculate the velocities and trajectories of rockets as well as to deisgn the actual rockets and satellites that allowed for the exploration of the solar system!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40363555-rise-of-the-rocket-girls&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;13-margaret-and-the-moon-how-margaret-hamilton-saved-the-first-lunar-landing&quot;&gt;13. Margaret and the moon: how Margaret Hamilton saved the first lunar landing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dean Robbins, Knopf Books for Young Readers (Children’s book), 2017&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/Margaret_and_the_moon.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

While the image of man landing on moon is an immortalized part of pop culture, another image has gained its prominent place: a woman smiling beside a stack of paper her height. Meet Margaret Hamilton, the woman who write the codes by hand to make the moon landing possible in this biography. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/29439789-margaret-and-the-moon&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;14-what-stars-are-made-of-the-life-of-cecilia-payne-gaposchkin&quot;&gt;14. What stars are made of: The life of Cecilia Payne-Gaposchkin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Donovan Moore, Harvard University Press, 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/What_stars_are_made_of.png

&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;


Cecilia Payne-Gaposchkin was an innovator who theorized with greatest of accuracies about the substance of stars. This book narrates the immense struggles Cecilia had to go through while doing what she loved, science. The read is a story of devotion and tenacity that speaks powerfully to our own time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/48982701-what-stars-are-made-of&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;15-dorothy-hodgkin-a-life&quot;&gt;15. Dorothy Hodgkin: a life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Georgina Ferry, Granta Books, 1999&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/Dorothy_Hodgkin.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:220px;height:300px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

A biography of Britain's only female Nobel Prize-winning scientist, a crystallographer who was also an active peace campaigner and mover through the highest levels of the British establishment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2602023-dorothy-hodgkin&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;16-nobel-prize-women-in-science-their-lives-struggles-and-momentous-discoveries&quot;&gt;16. Nobel Prize Women in Science: Their Lives, Struggles, and Momentous Discoveries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sharon Mcgrayne, Henry (Joseph) Press, 2001&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/Nobel_Prize_Women_in_Science.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;


The Nobel Prize awardee list shows an astonishing disparity in the representation of women scientists. This book narrates the lives and achievements of 15 women scientists who have won a Nobel Prize or part of a Nobel Prize- winning project. Even in the midst of relenless discrimination, their love for science pushed them for science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/149285.Nobel_Prize_Women_in_Science&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;17-the-fossil-hunter-dinosaurs-evolution-and-the-woman-whose-discoveries-changed-the-world&quot;&gt;17. The Fossil Hunter: Dinosaurs, Evolution, and the Woman Whose Discoveries Changed the World&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Shelley Emling, St. Martin’s Press, 2009&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/The_Fossil_Hunter.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

The book narrates the unsung story of Mary Anning, a twelve year who discovered the first dinosaur skeleton--of an ichthyosaur--while fossil hunting on the cliffs of Lyme Regis, England. The inspiration behind popular tongue-twister &quot;She Sells Sea Shells by the Seashore&quot;, she attracted the attention of fossil collectors and the scientific world alike. Her peculiar finds helped lay the groundwork for Charles Darwin's theory of evolution, laid out in his On the Origin of Species. Darwin based Mary's fossilized creatures as irrefutable evidence that life in the past was nothing like life in the present. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/6538811-the-fossil-hunter&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;18-the-madame-curie-complex-the-hidden-history-of-women-in-science&quot;&gt;18. The Madame Curie Complex: The Hidden History of Women in Science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Julie Des Jardins, The Feminist Press, 2010&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/The_Madame_Curie_Complex.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

The book explains why sciences are predominantly considered a male-centric job with a historic context. The book compares the lives of women scientists with their male contemporaries to demonstrate how the gendered culture of science molds the methods, structure, and experience of the work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6472839-the-madame-curie-complex&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;19-headstrong-52-women-who-changed-science-and-the-world&quot;&gt;19. Headstrong: 52 Women Who Changed Science and the World&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rachel Swaby, Broadway Books,	2015&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/Headstrong.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

Emmy Noether (her mathematical theorem stands as a backbone of modern physics), Maria Gaetana Agnesi (the first woman to be appointed as a university mathematics professor), Sally Ride (first American woman in space), Yvonne Brill (worked on the chemical propulsions which enabled man to travel to the moon), Rosalyn Sussman Yalow (co-winner of the 1977 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine), Inge Lehmann (discovered that the earth has an inner core). These are just few of the 'Headstrong' women who have been instrumental in major breakthroughs from the 17th to 19th centuries. This book contains stories of 52 women who were the best in their fields, while encouraging and inspiring a new generation of girls to put on their lab coats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22856166-headstrong&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;20-solving-the-puzzle-under-the-sea-marie-tharp-maps-the-ocean-floor&quot;&gt;20. Solving the Puzzle Under the Sea: Marie Tharp Maps the Ocean Floor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Robert Burleigh,	Simon &amp;amp; Schuster/Paula Wiseman Books (Children’s book), 	2016&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/Solving_the_Puzzle_Under_the_Sea.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

This illustrated biography narrates the story of Marie Tharp, a pioneering woman scientist and the first person to ever successfully map the ocean floor. Taught to think big by her father who was a cartographer, Marie wanted to map the bottom of the Atlantic Ocean. Despite failures and challenges where Marie would be turned away from a ship as having a woman on board was “bad luck”, Marie was determined to succeed. By mapping the ocean floor, Marie helped us better understand the planet we call home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25785790-solving-the-puzzle-under-the-sea&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;21-women-in-science-50-fearless-pioneers-who-changed-the-world&quot;&gt;21. Women in Science: 50 Fearless Pioneers Who Changed the World&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rachel Ignotofsky,	Ten Speed Press,	2016&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/Women_in_Science.jpg

&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

With beautiful, colourful illustrations, this book takes us on 50 inspiring journeys, each with one women scientist who left no stones unturned in their persuit of truth through science. They defied the society for their ambitions and become inspirations to millions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/27405561-women-in-science&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;22-radioactive-how-irène-curie-and-lise-meitner-revolutionized-science-and-changed-the-world&quot;&gt;22. Radioactive!: How Irène curie and Lise Meitner Revolutionized Science and Changed the world&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Winifred Conkling,	Algonquin Books,	2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/radioactive.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

The book presents the story of two women, Irène Curie and  Lise Meitner, who did ground breaking in a male-dominated field of science. Curie was denied admission to the French Academy of sciences due to her gender, even though she had been awarded with the Nobel Prize. Meitner’s unique insight was critical to the revolution in science that led to nuclear energy and the race to build the atom bomb, yet her achievement was left unrecognized by the Nobel committee.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24886042-radioactive&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;23-the-immortal-life-of-henrietta-lacks&quot;&gt;23. The Immortal Life of Henrietta Lacks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rebecca Skloot, Picador, 2019&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/The_immortal_life_of_Henrietta_Lacks.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

This book narrates the story of Henrietta Lacks, a poor Southern tobacco farmer who worked as an enslaved farm help.However, her cells has become one of the most important tool in medicine: the first “immortal” human cells to be grown in culture. Her vital for developing the polio vaccine, uncovered secrets of cancer, viruses among others. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6493208-the-immortal-life-of-henrietta-lacks&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;24-fantastically-great-women-scientists-and-their-stories&quot;&gt;24. Fantastically Great Women Scientists and Their Stories&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kate Pankhurst, Bloomsbury Children’s Books (Children’s book),	2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/woman_science_day_books/Fantastically_Great_Women_Scientists.jpg
&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1&quot; style=&quot;width:270px;height:350px;margin-right:15px;margin-bottom:20px;&quot; /&gt;

This book is a celebration of the women who made some of the world's most important scientific breakthroughs. Featuring Mae Jemison, Marie Curie, Elizabeth Blackwell, Janaki Ammal, Caroline Herschel, Katia Krafft, Tu Youyou and Rosalind Franklin, the book throws light on the lives of these incredible female scientists whose hard work, persistence and grit has changed our understanding of science, and of course broken down the typical gender roles attributed to women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57019582-fantastically-great-women-scientists-and-their-stories&quot;&gt;Read the book review on Goodreads.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a platform for promoting astronomy research among the public, we hope that these books guide you on your path towards a meaningful life with science. Do let us know which books you will be reading or if we have missed any of your favorite women scientist’s book in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/books-on-women-list</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/books-on-women-list</guid>
        
        <category>popular</category>
        
        <category>women-in science</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mass of the Black Hole in the nearby AGN: Mrk 590</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most of the massive galaxies in the Universe host a supermassive black hole (SMBH) at their center. A minority among them are known as active galaxies and host active galactic nuclei (AGNs). These AGN are believed to be powered by the accretion of matter onto the  SMBH and the emission from such accreting systems can have important effects on the host galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central regions of such AGN are so compact to be spatially resolved by any current imaging techniques, with the exception of the broad-line region (BLR) being resolved in two nearby AGN using recent interferometric observations carried out on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eso.org/public/teles-instr/paranal-observatory/vlt/&quot;&gt;Very Large Telescope&lt;/a&gt; of the European Southern Observatory. The angular size of the majority of the AGN is so small to be resolved using existing interferometric facilities. Therefore,  alternative methods are needed to probe the central regions of AGN. One such technique is reverberation mapping, where time resolution is used as a proxy for spatial resolution.  This technique allows one to determine the mass of the SMBH, the extent of the BLR, and the dusty torus that surrounds the SMBH. This technique works on the principle of measuring the time delay between the flux variations in an ionizing source and the flux variations from the surrounding regions irradiated by the central ionization source.  Implementation of this method to find the extent of the BLR and subsequently measure the  SMBH mass is usually carried out by spectroscopic monitoring observations which is not only a tedious process but also consumes an enormous amount of telescope time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/reverberation-mapping-clagn-amit/fig1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: Subaru spectrum of Mrk 590. The broad B, R and narrow Hα and S II filters are also over-plotted. Image source &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.02055&quot;&gt;: arXiv:2110.02055&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative to spectroscopic monitoring observations is the method of photometric reverberation which is simple and cheap in terms of observing time. This method relies on photometric monitoring observations of the AGN through suitably selected narrow-band filters to catch the redshifted emission line response, while another filter (either narrow band or broad band)  is required to trace the continuum flux . A recent work titled:  &lt;strong&gt;Changing look AGN Mrk 590: Broad-line region and black hole mass from photometric reverberation mapping&lt;/strong&gt; led by Amit Kumar Mandal has used the technique of photometric reverberation mapping to find the extent of the BLR in a nearby AGN, Mrk 590, located at a redshift (z) =0.026, where the SII narrowband filter is able to monitor the Hα emission line. A few active galaxies are found to undergo a transition from Type 1 characterized by strong emission lines, to Type 1.8 or 1.9, with weak or no broad emission lines, or vice versa. These galaxies are known as &lt;em&gt;changing look AGN&lt;/em&gt;. Mrk 590 is such a changing look AGN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/reverberation-mapping-clagn-amit/fig2.png&quot; /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: The BLR size- luminosity relation for Mrk 590 (red star) in this study. Also plotted is the same relation for all other objects whose BLR sizes are available through previous reverberation mapping campaigns. Image source &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.02055&quot;&gt;: arXiv:2110.02055&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From photometric observations carried out during July to December 2018, using a moderate size  60 cm robotic telescope located at the Cerro Tololo Inter-American Observatory, the research group was able to find the radius of the BLR of Mrk 590 to be 21.44&lt;sup&gt;+1.49&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;position: relative; left: -0.0em;&quot;&gt;-2.11&lt;/sub&gt; days. Using this lag, and an optical spectrum of the source obtained with the 8.2 m Subaru  Telescope, the research led by Dr. Amit Kumar Mandal was able to measure the mass of the SMBH in Mrk 590 as 1.96&lt;sup&gt;+0.15&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;position: relative; left: -0.0em;&quot;&gt;-0.21&lt;/sub&gt;
x 10&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt; M &lt;sub&gt;⦿&lt;/sub&gt;, where M &lt;sub&gt;⦿&lt;/sub&gt; is the mass of the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021MNRAS.508.5296M/abstract&quot;&gt; Changing look AGN Mrk 590: broad-line region and black hole mass from photometric reverberation mapping&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Amit Kumar Mandal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Malte Schramm, Suvendu Rakshit, C. S. Stalin, Bovornpratch Vijarnwannaluk, Wiphu Rujopakarn, Saran Poshyachinda, Vladimir V. Kouprianov, Joshua B. Haislip, Daniel E. Reichart, Ram Sagar, Blesson Mathew&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt;
Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India – 560034;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Department of Physics, CHRIST (Deemed to be University), Hosur Road, Bengaluru, Karnataka India – 560029&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/reverberation-mapping-clagn-amit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reverberation-mapping-clagn-amit</guid>
        
        <category>Cosmology</category>
        
        <category>Fast Radio Bursts</category>
        
        <category>Galaxy dark matter halos</category>
        
        <category>Radio transient sources</category>
        
        <category>Quasar absorption line spectroscopy</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Astrobiology: Exploring the universe for signs of extra-terrestrial life</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The only life forms we know about are the ones that exist on Earth. Due to advancements in space exploration, it has become possible to send rovers, probes, space crafts, and telescopes in further deep space. With the help of these space missions and various other tools, astrobiologists are trying to find signatures of life on other planets, exoplanets, and various moons.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.	Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;Is life a cosmic phenomenon?&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;Are we alone in the universe?&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us have wondered about it at some point in our lives. Perhaps only a few would have wondered about what exactly is life. This might sound philosophical at first but it is equally scientific. Astrobiology tries to find answers to all these questions. It is the science that seeks to understand the story of life in the universe. We have not found explicit evidence of life so far but with unceasing curiosity and an inherent urge for exploration, scientists have discovered a lot. Being a multidisciplinary field, Astrobiology brings people with diverse backgrounds together to achieve a common goal – the search for life beyond Earth and beyond the solar system. The origin of life on Earth is a great mystery and therefore scientists are investigating the problem in several different ways.  Some are studying life on our own planet. Some are seeking out life or fossil life on other planets or moons in our solar system. Others are trying to detect life in other solar systems, either by measuring life’s effects on the atmospheres of distant planets or by measuring artificial radiation like radio signals that may be produced by advanced life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.	Life on Earth:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only know the nature of life as it exists on Earth. It is built around compounds that contain elements such as carbon, nitrogen, hydrogen and oxygen. Complex sequences of these elements bond together, forming the very building blocks of life. They form essential organic molecules, such as carbohydrates, amino acids, lipids and nucleic acids (DNA and RNA). However, these organic molecules did not naturally exist on Earth during the Hadean eon (4.0 billion years ago and preceding the existence life forms). The elements required existed only in inorganic form, bound up within the rocks, atmosphere and the early ocean.
It is estimated that life on Earth began at least 3.5 billion years ago, because that is the age of the oldest rocks with fossil evidence of life on Earth. Researchers suggest that in order to understand how life began on Earth, we need to understand the specific environmental conditions and other requirements that must be satisfied to allow this to occur. What are the habitability requirements of known Earth life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental habitability requirements are certainly some of the commonalities of life on Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;•	Energy:&lt;/strong&gt;
A source of energy is necessary for metabolism and to maintain the functions carried out by a cell. Life on Earth uses either solar energy or chemical energy sources that include both organic (carbon) compounds and inorganic elements and molecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;•	Common essential elements:&lt;/strong&gt;
All known Earth life uses the same main set of elements to form biomolecules (CHNOPS) and shares a common carbon-based biochemistry. Carbon is an excellent element from which to build life, because carbon forms macromolecules with a variety of other elements and itself. Carbon forms primarily covalent bonds (compared to ionic bonds), and carbon-based molecules are stable in the presence of water and oxygen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;•	Solvent:&lt;/strong&gt;
A solvent to host chemical interactions is considered a universal requirement for all life. With extensive evidence that all Earth life needs water specifically as the solvent, many astrobiologists consider water to be the most probable solvent for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When considering whether an environment or planet is habitable, at a minimum, scientists take into account the potential energy source (or sources), the ambient chemical composition and whether this composition is suitable to build biomass, and the availability of a solvent. Additionally, there are physical constraints upon life (e.g., temperature, pressure, pH, salinity, radiation, metal toxicity) such that the presence of these habitability requirements may be necessary but not sufficient for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.1 Life on Earth is divided into three domains:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Archaea, Bacteria, and Eukarya (or Eucarya);&lt;/b&gt; Single-celled organisms are common in all three domains, and all organisms in the domains Archaea and Bacteria are single-celled. All multicellular organisms fall within the domain Eukarya. The term ‘‘prokaryotes’’ has traditionally been used to describe single-celled organisms that do not contain a nucleus, organelles, or a cytoskeleton (collectively, the domains Bacteria and Archaea). The majority of life on Earth is microbial, and astrobiologists extrapolate from that fact to conclude that the majority of any extraterrestrial life that may possibly exist is also likely to be microbial. Archaea and Bacteria are the focus of astrobiological studies due to the diversity of metabolic strategies utilized by them and their ability to thrive in extreme habitats, their pivotal role in Earth’s biogeochemical cycling, and the fact that single-celled organisms dominated the early history of life on Earth. Bacteria and Archaea harbour the vast majority of the genetic diversity of life on Earth. Scientists estimate that, to date, less than 1% of microbial life has been successfully cultivated (e.g., grown in the laboratory). Therefore, molecular methods that do not require cultivation are also used to detect the presence and genetic capabilities of microbes through DNA (metagenomics), RNA and gene expression activity (metatranscriptomics), and transcribed proteins (metaproteomics). These techniques have demonstrated that microbial populations are highly complex and that we have only begun to elucidate the full extent and capabilities of microbial life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 1: A phylogenetic tree based on rRNA data, emphasizing the separation of bacteria, archaea, and eukaryotes, as proposed by Carl Woese, George E. Fox et al. in 1990. Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.87.12.4576&quot;&gt;Carl Woese et al. (1990)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2 Prevalence of life in extreme environments:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When space agencies first began to explore the Solar System, scientists were not sure what they would find on the surfaces of planets like Mars and Venus. When space missions revealed Mars to be a frigid desert, and Venus a boiling cauldron, void of any obvious signs of life, astrobiologists began to wonder… what are the limits of habitability for life as we know it? How hot is too hot? How cold is too cold? How much acid can cells handle, and how little water can life survive on? Answering questions like these opened an entire field of study known as &lt;b&gt;extremophile research&lt;/b&gt;, where scientists examine the adaptations of organisms in conditions that are considered ‘extreme’ for life on Earth. These hardy lifeforms can help us better understand how life as we know it might originate, evolve, and reproduce in harsh environments in the Solar System and beyond. On a tour of extreme environments on Earth, a good place to start is with terrestrial hot springs. Good examples include Yellowstone National park in the United States, Rotorua in New Zealand and Puga hot spring in Ladakh, India These environments were the first to draw the interest of astrobiologists that study the limits of life on Earth, and they are arguably the first environment in which an extremophile, Thermus aquaticus was isolated and documented by scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 2: Aerial view of Grand Prismatic Spring; Hot Springs, Midway &amp;amp; Lower Geyser Basin, Yellowstone National Park. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/features/yell/slidefile/thermalfeatures/hotspringsterraces/midwaylower/Images/17708.jpg&quot;&gt;Jim Peaco, National Park Service&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These springs are where geothermally heated water from underground rises to the planet’s surface. They can act as a source of water, energy, and nutrients for living cells. The water boiling up from below can carry a wide variety of minerals and reduced chemical species that certain microbes can use as a source of energy. Microorganisms have been found here living in pools of up to 206 degrees Fahrenheit (97ºC). The composition of the water depends on many different factors, such as its source and the types of rock and soil it travels through. It’s not just the heat that challenges life’s survival in hot springs. Some springs have water that is very acidic, others have water that is extremely alkaline. Gases at concentrations poisonous to humans, and other animals, bubble up with the water. The rock and liquid can contain heavy metals like arsenic and lead, along with lots of other minerals and particulates. Some pools can be extremely salty, and are rich in potassium and sulphate. High temperatures also mean less dissolved oxygen, so many hydrothermal pools are low in oxygen content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The multitude of harsh conditions present in terrestrial hot springs also means that it isn’t only thermophiles that live in these environments. There are acidophiles, alkaliphiles, and many other types of organisms. Sometimes scientists find extremophiles that use multiple adaptations to survive (polyextremophiles). On Earth, wherever we find liquid water, we find life, whether in bubbling hot springs, drops of brine inside ice, or films of water around minerals deep in the crust.
Up until 1977, scientists believed that all life on Earth was in some way dependent upon sunlight for energy. The discovery of hydrothermal vents showed that life could thrive independent of the Sun. Suddenly, scientists had an Earthly example of how life might survive on ocean worlds in the outer Solar System, such as Jupiter’s moon Europa, or Saturn’s moon Enceladus. These moons are thought to harbor oceans of dark, liquid water beneath their icy surfaces. If hydrothermal vents are present, those oceans could be habitable for life as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3	How do we search for signs of life beyond Earth?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astrobiological exploration is founded upon the premise that biosignatures encountered in space will be recognizable as presence of extraterrestrial life. A &lt;b&gt;biosignature&lt;/b&gt; is any substance – such as an element, isotope, or molecule – or phenomenon that provides scientific evidence of past or present life. The usefulness of a biosignature is determined not only by the probability of life creating it but also by the improbability of non-biological (abiotic) processes producing it. Concluding that evidence of an extraterrestrial life form (past or present) has been discovered requires proving that a possible biosignature was produced by the activities or remains of life. As with most scientific discoveries, discovery of a biosignature will require evidence building up until no other explanation exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we can look for atmospheric gases such as oxygen or methane that can be produced by life. Such planetary features that indicate life are biosignatures. The simultaneous presence of oxygen and methane is evidence for life because these two gases should quickly react with each other unless a biosphere is producing great amounts of them, which prevents equilibrium. Microbial life will readily consume hydrogen or carbon monoxide gas, so an abundance of either of these might be considered an &lt;b&gt;anti-biosignature&lt;/b&gt; for a planet in the habitable zone.
&lt;b&gt;Eg.&lt;/b&gt; The presence of methane in the atmosphere of Mars is an area of ongoing research. Because of its tendency to be destroyed in the atmosphere by photochemistry, the presence of excess methane on a planet can be an indication that there must be an active source. With life being the strongest source of methane on Earth, observing a disequilibrium in the methane abundance on another planet could be a viable biosignature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 3: This illustration portrays possible ways that methane might be added to Mars' atmosphere (sources) and removed from the atmosphere (sinks). NASA's Curiosity Mars rover has detected fluctuations in methane concentration in the atmosphere. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/jpl/msl/pia19088&quot;&gt;NASA/JPL-Caltech&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.	Habitability in the solar system:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Earth it is absolutely logical to explore habitability of planets in our solar system. Planet Mars, in the inner solar system is a potential candidate to search for life beyond Earth. Simultaneously, moon of Jupiter (Europa) and moons of Saturn (Titan and Enceladus) in the outer solar system are also promising and extensive research is currently being conducted. The type of life that we are considering is simple, comparable to microbes, and the guiding principle concerns liquid water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.1 Mars:&lt;/strong&gt;
Many have imagined Mars, unlike Venus, as a potential abode for life. The atmosphere of Mars is much thinner than Earth’s. The Red Planet’s atmosphere contains more than 95% carbon dioxide and much less than 1% oxygen. Temperatures on Mars average about -81 degrees F. However, temperature’s range from around -220 degrees F in the wintertime at the poles, to +70 degrees F over the lower latitudes in the summer.
Mars Global Surveyor, which orbited from 1997 to 2006, mapped Mars and imaged sedimentary layers that implied many geologic cycles of erosion and deposition. In the early 21st century, the Mars Odyssey and Mars Express orbiters, along with Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter, discovered areas of clay minerals and salts, which may have formed in liquid water. Twin Mars Exploration Rovers landed in 2004, and found fossilized ripples from past liquid water and sedimentary rocks, while in 2008, NASA’s Phoenix Lander dug up subsurface ice in a polar region and measured soluble salts in the soil. Finally, in 2012, Curiosity Rover trundled towards a 5-kilometre-high mountain of sedimentary beds within a 150- kilometre-diameter crater named Gale. It found mudstones deposited from water. Nowadays, astrobiological interest in Mars concerns either biological traces from billions of years ago or microbial-like life that might possibly endure in the subsurface or underground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 4: Curiosity rover on a Martian sand dune. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/image-feature/jpl/pia20316/curiosity-self-portrait-at-martian-sand-dune&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mars’s current surface is hostile to life for three reasons. First, while ice exists for sure, no liquid water has been identified. The polar caps are water ice, topped with carbon dioxide ‘dry ice’ that grows when about 30 per cent of the atmosphere freezes at the winter pole. Also, above mid latitudes, ice cemented soil or permafrost lies just beneath the surface. In the tropics, afternoon temperatures in the top centimetre of soil rise above freezing, but there, ice turns to vapour before melting temperatures are reached. A second problem is no ozone layer, allowing harmful ultraviolet sunlight to reach the surface. Third, chemical reactions in the atmosphere make hydrogen peroxide— which settles to the surface, where they can destroy organics. While the surface is unpromising, geothermal heat underground might allow liquid water and life to exist. Evidence that liquid water used to be present suggests that Mars was once more habitable than today. Fluvial (stream-related) features in the landscape, including gullies, dried-up river valleys, deltas, and enormous channels are also indicative of the same. Moreover, the soil and rocks contain minerals that form in the presence of liquid water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.2 Jovian moon Europa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Galileo mission detected an induced magnetic field in Europa (a moon of Jupiter), providing compelling evidence for an ocean of liquid water beneath the surface. While the top surface of Europa is not habitable, it is still relevant to discuss here for several reasons: (1) surface materials may reflect the chemistry of a subsurface ocean and help us understand the conditions available to life there, and (2) materials brought to the surface from the ocean below may be the only way we can detect signs of life (e.g., organic matter or other biosignatures characterized spectroscopically on a future mission). Radiation from high-energy particles caught in Jupiter’s magnetic field causes oxidation of surface materials as the energy from radiation knocks electrons out of atoms. Radiolytically produced oxidants at the surface include O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, and CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;. These may be subsequently cycled into the ice shell and ocean on timescales on the order of the age of the surface, 106 years, which is quite young on geological timescales, so these compounds could potentially oxidize more reduced chemical species in the ocean below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image5 : Europa, a jovian moon. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://photojournal.jpl.nasa.gov/catalog/PIA00502&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.3 Icy moons of Saturn :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.3.1 Enceladus :&lt;/strong&gt;
Enceladus is Saturn’s sixth largest moon and has active geology. In 2005, the spacecraft Cassini started multiple close flybys of Enceladus, revealing its surface and environment in greater detail. It orbits Saturn in an elliptical fashion resulting in varying gravitational forces from Saturn that flex and heat Enceladus. For reasons that are not fully understood, the heating is concentrated under Enceladus’ South pole. There, icy particles and gas spray out of parallel fractures dubbed tiger stripes. The jets contain traces of methane, ammonia, and organic compounds, along with salt. Enceladus has a rocky core, an icy shell, and an underground sea beneath the area of the jets. The jackpot combination of organic molecules, energy, and liquid water implies that life might exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image6.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 6 : Narrow jets of gas and icy particles erupt from the south polar region of Enceladus, contributing to the moon's giant plume. A cycle of activity in these small-scale jets may be periodically lofting extra particles into space, causing the overall plume to brighten dramatically. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/feature/jpl/enceladus-jets-surprises-in-starlight&quot;&gt;NASA/JPL/Space Science Institute&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.3.2 Titan :&lt;/strong&gt;
Titan, the largest moon of Saturn, is also of astrobiological interest because it is the only satellite in the Solar System to have a thick atmosphere. In fact, the air pressure at Titan’s surface is 1.5 bar, which is 50 per cent larger than that at the Earth’s surface. The atmosphere of 95 per cent nitrogen and 5 per cent methane provides a 10°C greenhouse effect, but the sunlight at Saturn’s distance is one hundred times less intense than at Earth, so Titan’s surface is incredibly cold at –179°C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/astrobiology_shreya_images/image7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Image 7 : NASA's Cassini spacecraft sees bright methane clouds drifting in the summer skies of Saturn's moon Titan, along with dark hydrocarbon lakes and seas clustered around the north pole. Image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/images/pia21615-northern-summer-on-titan&quot;&gt;NASA/JPL/Space Science Institute&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Titan’s atmosphere contains a smoggy haze of hydrocarbons. At high altitude, ultraviolet sunlight breaks up methane molecules (CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;) and subsequent reactions build up hydrocarbons including ethane (C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;), acetylene (C&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;), propane (C&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;), benzene (C&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;H&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;), and reddish-brown particles containing polyaromatic hydrocarbons. The particles are called tholins. The products derived from methane sediment out of the atmosphere. In fact, about 20 per cent of Titan’s surface is covered in tropical dunes that are made of sand-sized particles, which are at least coated with organics if not made of them. At the poles, over 400 lakes are mixtures of liquid propane, ethane, and methane, with extraordinary beaches made of particles of benzene and acetylene.
Methane on Titan behaves like water on Earth and forms clouds, rain, and rivers. Most of our knowledge about Titan comes from the Cassini–Huygens mission, which arrived in 2004. Huygens landed on Titan in 2005. Titan flexes too much to be entirely solid, which is evidence that Titan has a subsurface ocean which might exist below an icy crust. Two types of life might exist on Titan: Earth-like life in the subsurface ocean; and non-DNA based life or life which has a different biochemistry in the hydrocarbon lakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.	Habitability beyond solar system :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding exoplanets is crucial before identifying a habitable one. With the vast distances involved, the search is difficult but nonetheless astronomers have developed two classes of methods. The first, indirect detection, looks for stellar properties, such as position or brightness, which are affected by the presence of unseen planets. The second is direct detection of a planet with an image or a spectrum of its light.
For astrobiology, the most important techniques are direct detections that capture light from a planet. Direct detection is challenging because a planet is a dim body close to a vastly brighter star. Nonetheless, telescopes in space, such as the Hubble Space Telescope, James Webb Telescopes and extremely large telescopes on the ground have accomplished direct detection using a coronagraph, which is a mask to block the starlight. With density measurements, there are increasing clues about which exoplanets are made of gas, rock, water, or some mixture. We care most about exoplanets with liquid water right at the surface. These have the chance of a biosphere that pumps lots of gases into an atmosphere. In principle, such biogenic gases are detectable in the light from the planet and might indicate life.
If a planet is too far away from its host star it ices over, and if it’s too close it’s too hot for liquid water. The term habitable zone (HZ) refers to the region around a star in which an Earth-like planet could maintain liquid water on its surface at some instant in time. We specify a particular time because stars age and brighten or dim, so the HZ moves. The closest star to Earth is a triple-star system called Alpha Centauri which is at a 4.25 – 4.35 light years distance. The list of potentially habitable exoplanets is mostly based on estimates of habitability by the Habitable Exoplanets Catalog (HEC), and data from the NASA Exoplanet Archive. The HEC is maintained by the Planetary Habitability Laboratory at the University of Puerto Rico at Arecibo. Surface planetary habitability is thought to require orbiting at the right distance from the host star for liquid surface water to be present, in addition to various geophysical and geodynamical aspects, atmospheric density, radiation type and intensity, and the host star’s plasma environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.	Conclusion :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astrobiology is intriguing and challenging at the same time. Research done on origin of life and extremophiles is used to extrapolate to other planets and various moons in the solar system. Astrobiologists are primarily interested in the subsurface water oceans of these planets. Overall, follow the water has been the motto. All space agencies keep executing ambitious space missions probes, rovers, spacecrafts, telescopes, etc. Another aspect of Astrobiology which pushes science boundaries is exoplanet search. Habitable planets beyond our solar system are actively being sought after. Bio-signatures help us detect presence of Earth-like life in our solar system and beyond it. With the advancement in technology for space exploration one can expect that humans will exist as a multiplanetary species in future. There is a possibility that we are alone in the universe or who knows we might find life elsewhere. Till then let’s keep our fingers crossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6.	References :&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ntrs.nasa.gov/citations/20180004101&quot;&gt;NASA Astrobiology Primer v2.0&lt;/a&gt; Shawn D. Domagal-Goldman and Katherine E. Wright&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.veryshortintroductions.com/view/10.1093/actrade/9780199586455.001.0001/actrade-9780199586455&quot;&gt;Astrobiology- A Very Short Introduction&lt;/a&gt; by David C. Catling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wiley.com/en-ie/Astrobiology:+Understanding+Life+in+the+Universe,+2nd+Edition-p-9781119550358&quot;&gt;Astrobiology : Understanding life in the Universe&lt;/a&gt; by Charles Cockell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/astrobiology-shreya/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/astrobiology-shreya/</guid>
        
        <category>Astrobiology</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrobiology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Shedding Light on the Cosmic Web with Fast Radio Bursts</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fast Radio Bursts are millisecond-duration radio transients of extragalactic origin. Their dispersion measures are sensitive to the presence of ionized matter along their lines of sight. This unique measurable makes FRBs a promising cosmological probe that can shed light on a hitherto invisible matter reservoir that constitutes the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of Fast Radio Bursts (FRBs) is one of the fastest developing fields of astronomical research.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Discovered serendipitously only in 2007 by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2007Sci...318..777L/abstract&quot;&gt;Lorimer et al&lt;/a&gt;, FRBs are bright, millisecond-duration transient radio events. According to some &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2013Sci...341...53T/abstract&quot;&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt;, thousands of FRBs occur in the sky daily. If one could see the sky in the radio frequencies, they would look like Fig.1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/frb_sunil/image1.gif&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: An artist’s rendition of what FRBs look like in the radio wavelengths. &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/146295242&quot;&gt;Credit: NRAO outreach&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most FRBs detected have extragalactic origins with the only exception being two &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2020PASP..132c4202B/abstract&quot;&gt;recently discovered&lt;/a&gt; radio pulse emissions from a Milky Way &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnetar&quot;&gt;magnetar&lt;/a&gt;, a compact remnant of a supernova that sports extremely strong magnetic fields, SGR 1935+2154. As the FRB pulses travel through space, they are dispersed by plasma (ionized matter) that permeates the universe, just like sunlight disperses in a prism into a rainbow. This means the higher frequency components of the pulse travel faster than the lower frequency waves. Fig. 2 shows the dispersed pulse reported by Lorimer et al. The amount of dispersion is quantified by the Dispersion Measure (DM). DM is defined as the line-of-sight integral of electron density, weighted by the cosmological scale factor. In Fig. 2, the DM essentially tells you how far apart the 1.5 GHz and 1.2 GHz components are. Measuring DM therefore relies on accurately estimating the arrival delay between the high and low frequencies constituting the light and since the delay is of the order of a few seconds. Lorimer et al could not account for the burst’s large DM using estimates of matter density within our galaxy alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was very much this dispersion that led Lorimer et al to postulate they are extragalactic in origin. In fact, it was several times larger and the burst was estimated to have originated at a distance of &amp;lt;1 Gigaparsec (Gpc). The sharp FRB pulse is therefore quite a unique and powerful probe of ionized matter on cosmological scales. Previously available cosmological probes of matter like quasar absorption lines are largely “blind” to ionized matter as fully ionized hydrogen and helium (which makes up most of the universe) do not produce any line features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/frb_sunil/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: The dispersed pulse of the Lorimer Burst. The dark curve is the FRB event. The horizontal axis shows the time relative to a reference. The higher frequency components of the pulse come before the low frequency components and thus the curve goes from the top-left to bottom-right. The shape of the curve is governed by plasma physics. The inset image shows the pulse when all the frequencies are aligned (i.e. the curve is straightened) and summed over. Note how sharp the pulse is compared to the total time of the FRB event (~0.4 s).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emission or absorption line features are manifestations of the quantum nature of an atom. In the ionized state, i.e. when  atoms are stripped of their electrons, there is no quantum system to produce said features. Furthermore, continuum (i.e. non line-like) emission from electrons/ions in the intergalactic medium is extremely hard to detect due to its sparsity. FRB dispersions on the other hand provide a direct measure of the line-of-sight integrated ionized matter density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to their transient nature, it is only recently that FRBs have been localized in the sky with a precision better than an arcsecond thanks to advances in radio interferometry. The first FRB to be precisely localized was FRB 20121102 (by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017ApJ...834L...7T/abstract&quot;&gt;Tendulkar et al&lt;/a&gt; in 2017), which using the American Very Large Array (VLA), was pinpointed to a small, highly star-forming galaxy at a redshift of 0.19. This FRB was first detected by the Arecibo telescope in 2012 and then since the source burst repeatedly albeit sporadically over the years, it was finally captured with the radio interferometer that is the VLA in 2017. In 2018, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019Sci...365..565B/abstract&quot;&gt;Bannister et al&lt;/a&gt; detected and simultaneously localized the FRB 20180924 thanks to the Australian Square-Kilometer-Array Pathfinder (ASKAP) and a new technique of performing radio interferometry. ASKAP consists of several large radio antenna pointing in the same direction in the sky. The telescope essentially looks for a transient in the non-interferometric mode&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, i.e. without correlating the signal from its individual antennae, to maximize the area of the sky scanned. The moment it detects a transient, the data in its buffer gets dumped to an external storage space for post-detection correlation and subsequently localization. Since the first detection, ASKAP has localized several FRBs and will continue doing so. Precise localization is crucial in pegging the FRB’s distance as the pulse itself does not carry precise information about the redshift&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. Localization is crucial to identify the host galaxy and spectroscopic follow-up observations of the host yield the redshift or distance estimate&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/frb_sunil/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: UV image of the FRB 20190608 host galaxy showing the active starforming regions (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApJ...922..173C/abstract&quot;&gt;Chittidi et al 2020&lt;/a&gt;). The red circle/white rectangle shows the radio-derived location of the FRB which is coincident with one of the starforming clumps.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the dispersion and the distance to the FRBs, one can start constraining the matter distribution in the foreground universe. One FRB sightline that we studied in detail was that of FRB 20190608 (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2020ApJ...901..134S/abstract&quot;&gt;Simha et al 2020&lt;/a&gt;). This FRB was localized to a spiral galaxy at redshift 0.3215 in the Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) footprint. A UV Hubble image of the galaxy showed that the FRB originated from one of the star-forming clumps within a spiral arm (Fig. 3). Due to its fortunate location within the SDSS database, we had extensive spectroscopic information of the field galaxies. This informed us about the location of foreground galaxies relative to the sightline and thus, with some modeling, the contribution of different foreground electron reservoirs to the FRB DM. Being an integrated quantity, the DM can be split into multiple parts corresponding to the source of electrons. That is,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
DM&lt;sub&gt;FRB&lt;/sub&gt; = DM&lt;sub&gt;MW&lt;/sub&gt; + DM&lt;sub&gt;halos&lt;/sub&gt; + DM&lt;sub&gt;IGM&lt;/sub&gt; + DM&lt;sub&gt;host&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here DM&lt;sub&gt;MW&lt;/sub&gt; is the contribution from the Milky Way interstellar medium (ISM) and halo, DM&lt;sub&gt;host&lt;/sub&gt; is a similar term but for the host galaxy, DM&lt;sub&gt;halos&lt;/sub&gt; is from the gas present in intervening galactic halos and DM&lt;sub&gt;IGM&lt;/sub&gt; is from the diffuse filamentary gas that permeates the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observable_universe#Large-scale_structure&quot;&gt;cosmic web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;. In our work, we aimed to estimate each of these individual subcomponents from optical observations. For the Milky Way, we used models of the ISM electron distribution constructed using galactic pulsars (NE2001; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2003astro.ph..1598C/abstract&quot;&gt;Cordes and Lazio 2003&lt;/a&gt;). We modeled the gas distribution of the halo as a modified NFW profile (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019MNRAS.485..648P/abstract&quot;&gt;Prochaska and Zheng 2019&lt;/a&gt; for details). In total, of the 340 pc cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;of the FRB DM, we estimated roughly 80 pc cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; arising from the Milky Way. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApJ...922..173C/abstract&quot;&gt;Chittidi et al 2020&lt;/a&gt; estimated the DM&lt;sub&gt;host&lt;/sub&gt;~100 pc cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt; using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integral_field_spectrograph&quot;&gt;integral field unit&lt;/a&gt; (IFU)&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; observations with the Keck Cosmic Web Imager (KCWI) and the same halo model as the one used for the Milky Way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the SDSS and WISE photometry available for the field galaxies in tandem with the spectroscopic redshifts, we estimated the stellar masses of foreground galaxies. Then, using the stellar-to-halo-mass ratio from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2013MNRAS.428.3121M/abstract&quot;&gt;Moster et al 2013&lt;/a&gt;, we estimated their halo masses. Assuming that the halo gas typically extends up to one virial radius&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;, we determined which halos intersect the FRB sightline and then using our modified NFW halo gas model, determined their DM contributions. We estimated DM&lt;sub&gt;halos&lt;/sub&gt; ~ 20 pc cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimating DM&lt;sub&gt;IGM&lt;/sub&gt; was perhaps the most challenging as one cannot directly observe diffuse filamentary gas, its presence is generally inferred indirectly. However, since we had access to the SDSS galaxy redshifts, we could, in theory, reconstruct the cosmic web density using them as tracers. Thus, we leveraged the Monte-Carlo &lt;i&gt;Physarum Machine&lt;/i&gt; (MCPM) model introduced by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2020ApJ...891L..35B/abstract&quot;&gt;Burchett et al&lt;/a&gt; in 2020 to do exactly this. The algorithm is inspired by the motion of Physarum polycephalum or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3rWk6h0Syog&quot;&gt;slime mold&lt;/a&gt;. The mold efficiently searches for food particles and produces a filamentary network connecting them in its wake. Modeling the galaxies as “food”, one can produce a steady-state slime mold particle density with MCPM and translate this to physical matter density by calibrating against dark matter density in cosmological simulations. The result (see Fig. 4) is an estimate of gas density along the sightline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/frb_sunil/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: Cosmic web density “reconstruction” using the MCPM algorithm for the FRB 20190608 sightline. Though galaxies were cone-searched around the FRB, as it is located in one of the narrow strips of SDSS, there were more spectra available in one direction (top) than the other (side) and thus our model doesn’t appear conical.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this model, we estimated DM&lt;sub&gt;IGM&lt;/sub&gt; ~ 110 pc cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;. Thus just using optical data, we were able to estimate DMFRB and closely match the radio measurement. Our model uncertainties are fairly large (~30%) but nevertheless, this work was a proof of concept that FRB DMs can inform us about the matter distribution in the universe. Furthermore, if this analysis is performed on multiple sightlines, we can start laying statistical constraints on some of the key model parameters that were only assumed in this work e.g. the fraction of the universe’s baryons in the filamentary gas and the fraction of halo gas present in the hot (&amp;gt;10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; K) ionized phase. In fact, our future work on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021arXiv210900386L/abstract&quot;&gt;FLIMFLAM&lt;/a&gt; (FRB Line-of-sight Ionization Measurement with Lightcone AAOmega Mapping) survey intends to achieve ~ 10% constraints on these parameters using ~25 sightlines. We are currently collecting spectroscopic redshifts of field galaxies along multiple sightlines and hope to start producing preliminary results within the next year. FRB-aided cosmology promises exciting research in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] See &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019A%26ARv..27....4P/abstract&quot;&gt;Petroff et al&lt;/a&gt; 2019 for an excellent review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://astronomy.curtin.edu.au/research/craft/&quot;&gt;CRAFT webpage&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41550-018-0597-7&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; for more details on the survey and the telescope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Though the dispersion is correlated to the distance, there are many sources of uncertainty in the DM-redshift relation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] Astronomers use redshift as a proxy for distance when it comes to cosmological scales. This is thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hubble%27s_law&quot;&gt;Hubble relation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] This is the large-scale structure of matter in the universe. As dark matter (and regular matter) condensed gravitationally after the Big Bang, it created halos and filamentary structures connecting halos, giving it a web-like appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6] IFUs are specialized instruments that can take images as well as spectra of the field-of-view simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7] A virial radius of a halo is the radius from its center within which the halo dark matter density is roughly 200 times larger than the background value. Think of it as the radial extent of the halo matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021ApJ...921..134S/abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Estimating the Contribution of Foreground Halos to the FRB 180924 Dispersion Measure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Sunil Simha&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Nicolas Tejos, J. Xavier Prochaska, Khee-Gan Lee, Stuart D. Ryder, Sebastiano Cantalupo, Keith W. Bannister, Shivani Bhandari and Ryan M. Shannon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; University of California, Santa Cruz, CA 95064, United States&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/shedding-light-cosmic-web-sunil</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/shedding-light-cosmic-web-sunil</guid>
        
        <category>Cosmology</category>
        
        <category>Fast Radio Bursts</category>
        
        <category>Galaxy dark matter halos</category>
        
        <category>Radio transient sources</category>
        
        <category>Quasar absorption line spectroscopy</category>
        
        
        <category>Cosmology and Nongalactic Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Identifying emission-line stars from a large spectroscopic database</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We present a catalog of 3339 hot emission-line stars (ELS) identified from 451,695 O, B, and A type spectra, provided by the LAMOST DR5 release. We developed an automated python routine that identified 5437 spectra having a peak between 6561 and 6568~Å. False detections and bad spectra were removed, leaving 4138 good emission-line spectra of 3339 unique ELS. We re-estimated the spectral type of 3307 spectra as the LAMOST Stellar Parameter Pipeline (LASP) did not provide accurate spectral types for these emission-line spectra. As Herbig Ae/Be stars show higher excess in near-infrared and mid-infrared wavelengths than Classical Ae/Be stars, we used 2MASS and WISE photometry to distinguish them. Finally, we report 1089 Classical Be, 233 Classical Ae, and 56 Herbig Ae/Be stars identified from the LAMOST DR5. In addition, 928 B[em]/A[em] stars and 240 CAe/CBe potential candidates are identified. From our sample of 3339 hot emission-line stars, 2716 ELS identified in this work do not have any record in the SIMBAD database and they can be considered as new detections. Identification of such a large homogeneous set of emission-line spectra will help the community to study the emission phenomenon in detail without worrying about the inherent biases when compiling from various sources.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand what emission line stars (ELS) are, one needs to know about the spectrum of a star. Each star has its own unique spectrum, analogous to the fingerprint of humans. A spectrum can be used to identify the properties of the star such as its temperature, chemical composition and (indirect) physical constraints. So clearly, spectroscopy of cosmic objects can reveal lots of information about the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let us ask a more basic question. What is a spectrum? To understand this, imagine a rainbow on a rainy day. A rainbow is formed when the sunlight passes through the water molecules suspended in the air after the rain. As the sunlight moves through a spherical water droplet, it gets dispersed into various colours ranging from Violet to Red. This is a real-life example of spectroscopy. The light from a stellar object, when passed through a slit or a prism (the optical equivalent of the spherical water droplet), gets split into various colours. If the light from the star is as ideal as white light is, which is made up of all the colors with equal intensity, we would get a beautiful color gradient with all colors shining equally. However, the universe is not that simple. The spectrum of a star will have bright and dark lines, similar to the way we have ridges and valleys in our fingerprint (Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1:  A representative high-resolution spectrum showing the visible light of alpha Boo. The black lines in this spectrum are caused due to various metallic elements present in the photosphere of the cool giant alpha Boo.
Image source:&lt;a hrefsridharan1_emission_stars_database=&quot;https://noirlab.edu/public/images/noao-arct/&quot;&gt;N.A.Sharp, NOIRLab/NSF/AURA)
 &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These bright and dark lines (or emission and absorption lines) are the most crucial information of the spectrum. They tell us about the atomic and molecular processes going on in the top most layer of the star which is known as the photosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An absorption line is formed in the spectrum when light of a certain wavelength is absorbed by an atom or a molecule. Similarly, an emission line is formed when light of a certain wavelength is emitted (or radiated) by an atom or a molecule. To put it simply, when an atom ‘absorbs’ light, it goes into a higher energy level and when it ‘emits’ light, it comes down to a lower energy level as shown in Figure 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 2: The above plots show the absorption and emission process as caused by the excitation and de-excitation of electrons around the nucleus.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webassign.net/labsgraceperiod/ucscgencheml1/lab_6/manual.html&quot;&gt;webassign &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spectrum of a star is the information that gives us the intensity at each wavelength of light. An observed stellar spectrum consists of the blackbody continuum, absorption lines and in some cases, emission lines. The blackbody continuum in the visible and infrared region is due to the thermal emission of the star and the absorption lines are seen because the ‘cooler’ photosphere absorbs light at certain wavelengths. These two components are seen in the spectrum of all the stars because it arises due to the basic structure of stars. Now let us come to the topic of this article, ELS. Emission lines arise from a hot, gaseous region around the star that is formed due to some special nature of the star. The type of stars that show emission lines in their spectrum are called Emission line stars (ELS). You can call them the rebellious group of star families, who want to be unique by showing emission lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various types of ELS known to us today (and its analogues)
Pre-main sequence (PMS) stars - young, naughty teenagers creating chaos
Classical Be stars - people with midlife crisis
Wolf-Rayet stars - old, wise people
Even though ELS comprises stars in various evolutionary phases, in most cases the emission arises from the equatorial circumstellar disc which is made of gas and dust. The formation mechanism of circumstellar disc varies between different classes. For example, in PMS stars the circumstellar disc is the accretion disc through which material is added to the star from its surroundings. In Classical Be stars, the disc is formed due to rapid spinning of the star which pushes away material from the star to its surroundings. So it should be noted that even though we put stars with emission lines into a single category of ELS, they are very different from each other. Hence, we need to classify them based on their photometric properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aim&quot;&gt;Aim:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As large-scale spectroscopic surveys collect a large number of spectra every night, we need to identify special classes of stars such as ELS and classify them into different categories for the research community to study various emission mechanisms. This is the motivation for the work titled “Discovery of 2716 hot emission-line stars from LAMOST DR5’’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data&quot;&gt;Data:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Large Sky Area Multi-Object Fiber Spectroscopic Telescope (LAMOST) is a multi-object telescope that can observe around 4000 stars in one night. By its 5th data release (DR5), it had accumulated around 9 million spectra from 2011-2017 which are available to the community. We made use of this huge database to increase the number of ELS stars known to us. One interesting fact about LAMOST is that the majority of  observed stars are in the Galactic anticenter direction. This is particularly important because the earlier studies which have identified ELS have not looked into this direction of the sky. So this opened up an opportunity to study ELS in previously less explored parts of the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;analysis&quot;&gt;Analysis:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this work, we took O, B and A type stars (Teff ranging from 30000 K to 10000 K) from the LAMOST DR5 database (for an explanation of different spectral types, look into Anusha R’s CAe article). We restricted ourselves to these spectral types because the main aim of this was to identify new Classical Be/Ae and Herbig Be/Ae stars. Once we removed bad quality (Signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) &amp;lt; 10)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; spectra from our list, we used an open-source python package called ‘scipy.signal’ to identify emission peaks. The entire definition of ELS rests on the presence of one of the most commonly found emission line, Hα at 6563 Å. We searched and picked out spectra with the Hα line anywhere between 6561 Å and 6568 Å. This range was selected to take into effect the instrumental calibration defect (if any) and the doppler shift that may be seen in a few stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We identified 4138 spectra that belong to 3339 unique ELS stars from our analysis. To classify stars into different categories such as CBeAe or HBeAe, we need an accurate spectral type for each spectrum. The LAMOST automated pipeline does provide a spectral type for each spectrum which did not turn out to be accurate due to the presence of emission lines. This introduced the necessity for us to re-estimate spectral type for each spectrum. We followed a technique called template matching. We made use of the MILES stellar spectral library for this purpose. For each spectrum, we matched the templates from MILES library to our target spectrum and identified the best fit. Then the spectral type of the best fit template was assigned to the target spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to differentiate between Classical Be/Ae and Herbig Be/Ae stars, we made use of the inherent difference between them known as Infrared (IR) excess. Herbig Be/Ae stars, being young stars, have lots of gas and dust around them in addition to a circumstellar disc. This extra gas and dust reprocesses the energy from the star and emits them in infrared wavelengths. Due to this, the HAeBe stars are brighter in IR wavelengths than CBe stars. Hence we use the photometric data&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; available to us to differentiate them based on colors and spectral indices. The breakup of various classes identified in this work is given in the table below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;  Table 1: Statistical break-up of various classes identified in this work.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.08025&quot;&gt;Table 1 of the review paper) &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We visually examined the Hα line features belonging to each class and reported their statistics. Finally, a representative spectrum of major classes is presented in Figure 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/sridharan1_emission_stars_database/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 3: This plot shows a representative spectrum belonging to each of Oe*, CBe, CAe, HBe, HAe, B[em], and A[em] classes. Red dotted lines denote [NII] lines at 6548 and 6584 ̊A and green solid lines denote [SII] lines at 6717 and 6731 ̊A. The spectra are normalized using laspec open source python package.

Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.08025&quot;&gt; Figure 7 of the review paper &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-scope&quot;&gt;Future Scope:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research work identifies new ELS stars from a large database and classifies them into various categories based on their photometric properties. As the data collection capabilities increase day-to-day, the need for such works increases. We have multiple follow-up works in the fray which uses the LAMOST database effectively in identifying and study the properties of CBeAe and HAeBe stars in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2021arXiv210808025B/abstract&quot;&gt; Discovery of 2716 hot emission-line stars from LAMOST DR5 &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Shridharan Baskaran&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Blesson Mathew, Nidhi S, Anusha R, Arun R, Sreeja S. Kartha, Yerra Bharat Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; CHRIST (Deemed to be University), Bangalore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Signal-to-noise ratio or SNR is a quantity which defines the quality of a spectrum. More the SNR, the better the spectrum. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Photometry (in astronomical context) means measurement of brightness of a star. The brightness of a star observed through filters of different wavelengths can be used to decode information about the star. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Photometry_(astronomy)&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/sridharan_emission_stars_database</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/sridharan_emission_stars_database</guid>
        
        <category>Emission-line stars</category>
        
        <category>Catalog</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bar Buckling and Boxy/Peanut Bulges as the Tracer of Dark Matter Halo Shape</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Galaxies reside in the deep potential of invisible matter called dark matter. Their dynamics is significantly affected by the distribution of dark matter around them. Distribution of dark matter around galaxies is usually known as dark matter halo. Most of the previous studies of galaxies assumed spherical dark matter halos. But, cosmological simulations of structure formation suggest that the dark matter halo can vary in shape. It can also have non-spherical shape (e.g. oblate and prolate) which can significantly influence the evolution of the galaxy. In this study, Astronomer from IIA, Bangalore and SJTU, China have studied the effect of non-spherical dark matter halos on the buckling of the bars and formation of boxy/peanut shape bulges. They perfomed a set of numerical simulation for varying dark matter halo shape and traced the formation of bars and boxy/peanut shape bulges.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at the clear night sky, you may find a white bright band stretching from north to south in the sky. It is nothing but our home galaxy, the Milky Way. There are trillions of galaxies in our observable Universe. Galaxies are gravitationally bound systems of stars, gas, dust, and invisible matter called dark matter. Galaxies come in different shapes and sizes ranging from spherical - like a ball to disk - like a round plate. Since most of the disk galaxies have spiral arms, they are also called spiral galaxies. Depending on the presence of a bar, a spiral galaxy could be a barred spiral or unbarred spiral. Disk galaxies usually possess a dense collection of stars in their centres which is termed as the bulge. Bulges can range from nearly spherical to as flat as the disk of galaxies. Our Milky way has a boxy/peanut shape flat bulge which is supposed to have formed from the thickening of the bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ankit1_bar_buckling_dark_matter/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1: Example of unbarred and barred galaxies.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://ned.ipac.caltech.edu/&quot;&gt;NED
 &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The matter we can see in a galaxy is far less than its actual matter content. More than 80% of the total galaxy mass is invisible to us. Only the motion of the stars or gas in the galaxy shows the presence of dark matter. This invisible matter is commonly referred to as dark matter. Due to the presence of an enormous amount of dark matter in the galaxy, the dynamics of the stars is remarkably affected by the distribution of the dark matter. In the past, there have been several detailed studies of the galaxies assuming the spherical distribution of dark matter in the galaxies. There are very limited works that consider the non-spherical distribution of dark matter for the study of galaxies. In the present paper, Ankit Kumar and the team have investigated the effect of non-spherical dark matter distribution on the bar buckling and the formation of boxy/peanut flat bulge like that seen in our Galaxy. Bar buckling is a bar thickening mechanism where the bar suddenly bends out of the disk of the galaxy. Bar buckling can be simply understood using a practical example of a beam or pillar. Say, there is a vertically standing beam and you start increasing the load on it. Then at some point, it will suddenly bend somewhere in the middle (or may collapse). This sudden change is called the buckling of the beam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ankit1_bar_buckling_dark_matter/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 2: Examples of oblate, spherical, and prolate dark matter halos in a disk galaxy.

Image source: Author.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authors have used the supercomputing facility to generate mock realistic disk galaxies and to evolve them in time. The distribution of dark matter in the galaxies ranges from oblate to prolate including spherical one. Oblate distribution (or oblate halo) looks like the shape formed on squeezing a sphere from its top and bottom whereas prolate distribution (or prolate halo) is similar to the shape formed on stretching a sphere from its top and bottom. To trace the formation and evolution of the bar and buckling events, they used Fourier analysis and found that the galaxies in prolate halos form bar earlier than the galaxies in oblate halos. Also, the bar in prolate halos buckles before the bar in the oblate halos. Fourier analysis is the method to decompose any general function or structure into simple trigonometric functions or structures with definite frequencies (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourier_series&quot;&gt; this article  &lt;/a&gt; for Fourier series).
Buckling events are very rarely observed. To date, there are only 8 confirmed galaxies that are currently going through the buckling events. In this study, Ankit Kumar and the team found three distinct buckling events for the bar in the prolate halo. It is the first time where more than two buckling events in a bar have been detected in any study. The total duration of buckling is longer for the bar in the prolate halo. The rarity of buckling in observations and longer duration buckling in the prolate halos lead authors to conclude that most of the dark matter halos could be oblate and spherical in shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ankit1_bar_buckling_dark_matter/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; A clear buckling of the iso-density contour can be seen in the outer bar of the prolate halo during the 3rd buckling event. It also shows the formation and growth of peanut shape bulge after bar buckling.
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/509/1/1262/6406514&quot;&gt; Kumar et. al. 2021. &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each buckling event makes the bar thick in size. First buckling thickens the innermost region of the bar while the succeeding bucklings thicken the outer regions of the bar. As a result of these thickening boxy/peanut shape flat bulge forms. Since the bar in the prolate halo shows more buckling events as compared to the oblate halo, the bar in prolate halo thickens the most and forms the most thicker boxy/peanut shape bulge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article-abstract/509/1/1262/6406514?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt; The effect of dark matter halo shape on bar buckling and boxy/peanut bulges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Ankit Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Mousumi Das, and Sandeep Kumar Kataria&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt;
Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India – 560034; Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India – 560012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/bar-buckling-dark-matter-ankit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/bar-buckling-dark-matter-ankit/</guid>
        
        <category>Galaxies</category>
        
        <category>Bar Buckling</category>
        
        <category>Boxy/Peanut shape bulges</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Measuring the age of the Universe: An overview</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A popular article exploring how the age of the Universe was calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://cosmicvarta.in/measuring-the-age-sun-moon-gourav&quot;&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt; has already provided a flavour of how scientists use mathematics combined with knowledge obtained from physics to reveal numerous hidden secrets of nature such as the age of the Earth, the Moon and even the Solar System. But the story does not end here. It literally cannot. This is because the curiosity of human beings is unquenchable. Naturally, any curious mind will ask the next question, what is the age of the universe? Fortunately, the power of human intellect combined with the supreme efficiency of mathematics and physics have provided an answer to this almost impossible to solve question also. We now know with reasonable confidence that our universe is around 13.8 billion (i.e. 1380 crore since 1 billion = 100 crore) years old. But, how do we measure the age of the universe? To know the answer, one has to study ‘cosmology’. This might be one of the most thrilling detective stories of all time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cosmology is the study of the size, structure and evolution of the universe — in other words, the &lt;em&gt;geography&lt;/em&gt; of the universe as a single system. In cosmology, our subject is the whole universe, defined as all matter and energy in existence anywhere, observable or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;birth-of-cosmology&quot;&gt;Birth of cosmology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most fundamental questions of humanity is the question of origins:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Where did we come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question runs deeper than the origins of any one person and delves into questions of where did life, our planet, and the entire universe come from. Many cultures have avoided the notion of an origin to the universe by placing their creation stories in a cycle. Buddhist and Hindu origins stories measure the birth, death, and rebirth of the universe in units of 4 trillion years, which is a day in the life of Brahma. At night, all matter is absorbed into the spirit of the sleeping Brahma. At dawn, when Brahma awakes, matter reappears and the cycle continues. The Greek Stoics saw the universe as being created from fire, only to be destroyed by fire, and so on. Cosmological cycles are also found in the cultures of the Maya and the Aztec.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of modern cosmology began with Albert Einstein and Edwin Hubble. From Einstein’s theories, the shape of space is described as being warped by gravity. From the observations of Hubble, we learned the universe is expanding. Together these two men described the evolving shape of space and they opened up a new field of science called cosmology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-big-bang-model&quot;&gt;The Big Bang model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern theory of the origin of the universe starts with the idea of expanding space. Georges Lemaître was a priest and a mathematician, an unassuming man who had beaten the giants of physics to the punch in deducing that the universe could be expanding. In 1929, Lemaître was the first to hypothesize a revolutionary idea: at one time, the universe might have been as small as an atomic nucleus. He proposed that the universe derived from a cosmic singularity, &lt;em&gt;a day without a yesterday&lt;/em&gt; when the universe was infinitely small and infinitely curved, and all matter and energy were concentrated in a single point. Many astrophysicists found the idea bizarre and distasteful and English theorist Fred Hoyle disparaged the idea with the name &lt;em&gt;big bang&lt;/em&gt;. The label stuck, and scientists continue to call the description of the creation of the universe the Big Bang model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gourav_measuring_age_universe/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1: According to the Big Bang model, the universe expanded from an extremely dense and hot state and continues to expand today
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_Big_Bang_theory&quot;&gt;Wikipedia &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big Bang model forces us to consider the idea of cosmic evolution. The universal recession of galaxies implies that the universe is evolving, and it has not always been in the same state. Our observations of nearby galaxies represent a single frame in a movie that has been playing for billions of years. We can wind the tape backwards, seeing snapshots of a progressively older universe, by observing sets of galaxies at progressively larger distances, and thus at progressively larger look back times. (Since light takes time to travel, we see objects far away as they looked when the light was released rather than as they are now.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we look back into the early universe, we can see the galaxies move closer together. Observationally, we can’t see all the way back to the first moments, but we can see times when galaxies were just forming, and the large scale structures — the cosmic walls and voids — were just starting to form. If we could look further back, we’d see that as the universe gets smaller; its volume contracts until all the mass are smashed together in a tiny universe. The mass that formed galaxies and stars breaks down into a seething hot gas, as the universe tends toward a state of infinite temperature and density. Thinking of the Big Bang as an explosion is tempting, but it is also misleading. In an explosion on Earth, debris flies through space. In the Big Bang, the initial singularity contains all space and matter. Time itself begins with the big bang. The evolution of the universe is the unfolding of time and space from a condition of incredible heat and density to cold and enormous state billions of years later. This bang had no center, it had no past and it simply was the sudden beginning of everything in an expanding geometry that may or may not be finite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific story of creation says that everything — you and the Earth and the Sun and the Milky Way and all the billions of galaxies — emerged from a tiny dense dot of energy and matter that unfolded into the universe we see now. It sounds as fantastic as any of the creation myths of older cultures. How do we know that the big bang actually occurred? There are three primary pieces of evidence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Galaxies are taking part in a universal expansion as indicated by the linear relation between distance and redshift (the Hubble relation).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The abundance of the lightest elements can be explained by fusion in the universe when it was young and dense and hot (cosmic nucleosynthesis).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Space is filled with the radiation from the early hot phase, now diluted and reduced in energy to the level of microwaves (the cosmic microwave background).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Describing each of these concepts is beyond the scope of this article. But the Hubble relation mentioned in the first point bears huge importance in measuring the age of the universe. Hence, I shall take the opportunity to discuss in brief the Hubble relation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hubble-relation-or-hubbles-law&quot;&gt;Hubble relation or Hubble’s law&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hubble relation, popularly known as the Hubble’s law or Hubble–Lemaître law is considered the first observational basis for the expansion of the universe and today serves as one of the pieces of evidence most often cited in support of the Big Bang model. Although widely attributed to Edwin Hubble, the notion of the universe expanding at a calculable rate was first derived from the general relativity equations in 1922 by Alexander Friedmann. Friedmann published a set of equations, now known as the Friedmann equations, showing that the universe might expand, and presenting the expansion speed if this was the case. Then Georges Lemaître, in a 1927 article, independently derived that the universe might be expanding, observed the proportionality between the recessional velocity of and distance to distant bodies and suggested an estimated value of the proportionality constant, which when corrected by Hubble became known as the Hubble constant. Then in 1929, Edwin Hubble confirmed the existence of cosmic expansion and determined a more accurate value for the constant that now bears his name. Hubble inferred the recession velocity of the objects from their redshifts, many of which were earlier measured and related to velocity by Vesto Slipher in 1917.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gourav_measuring_age_universe/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 2: Georges Lemaître
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georges_Lema%C3%AEtre&quot;&gt;Wikipedia &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gourav_measuring_age_universe/image3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 3: Edwin Hubble
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/biography/Edwin-Hubble&quot;&gt;Britannica &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/gourav_measuring_age_universe/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 4: Fred Hoyle
Image source:&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/science/2010/oct/03/fred-hoyle-nobel-prize&quot;&gt;The Guardian &lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The law is often expressed by the equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;v = H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;D   (1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where, v is the recessional velocity, typically expressed in km/s.
H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; is Hubble’s constant and corresponds to the value of H (often termed the Hubble parameter which is a value that is time-dependent and which can be expressed in terms of the scale factor) in the Friedmann equations taken at the time of observation denoted by the subscript 0. This value is the same throughout the universe for a given comoving time.
D is the proper distance (which can change over time, unlike the comoving distance, which is constant) from the galaxy to the observer, measured in megaparsecs (Mpc), in the 3-space defined by given cosmological time.
The reciprocal of H0 is the Hubble time. This constant term H0 help us to estimate the age of the universe. Let me now discuss in brief how it does so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;age-of-the-universe&quot;&gt;Age of the Universe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Einstein, Lemaitre, and others solved the equations of general relativity, they were able to describe how the size of the universe has changed with time. Astronomers use the symbol R to represent the scale or size of the universe at any time. You can think of R as the size of the universe, but more accurately it represents the distance between any two well-separated places. The cosmological principle says that any two points are moving apart at the same rate. Thus, the entire history of the universe is described by the way that R varies with time. Since the universe is expanding, R has been continuously increasing for billions of years. Remember that R describes the expansion of space that carries galaxies apart — the galaxies themselves are not expanding. Galaxies are just markers of expanding space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Big Bang model even provides a prediction for the age of the universe. If we imagine the evolving universe as a movie, the birth of the universe is the time in the distant past when all matter and radiation was crushed in a state of infinite temperature and density. The scale factor, R, was zero. Space had not yet begun to unfold. There are three ways to constrain the age of the universe. But in many ways, looking at the expansion rate of the universe is one of the easiest ways to figure out the universe’s age. This technique looks at the current expansion rate and then running it backwards to determine when today’s universe must have been compressed down to a single point. Mathematically, the age of the universe is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;t&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; = 1 / H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;f (Ωr Ωm Ωλ;…)    (2)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where t&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; is the current age, H0 is the current expansion rate, and f is a correction that takes into consideration the mass, energy, and other characteristics of the universe. For this method to work, you need to not only know the current expansion rate but also how this rate has changed over time due to the effects of gravity and the effect of dark energy (Ωλ;), which is pushing the universe apart. The best published value for the expansion rate is H&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;=70.6 ± 3.1 (km/sec) / Mpc. This means that every Megaparsec of space expands roughly 70.6 km each second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on stellar evolution models, we estimate the oldest globular star clusters are between 11 and 13 billion years old. Apart from these two techniques, the most trusted means of determining the age of the universe comes from very precise measurements of the cosmic microwave background (CMB) radiation. The CMB is a diffuse, uniform background of microwave radiation that comes from all directions in the sky. This CMB is the electromagnetic radiation which is the remnant from an early stage of the universe, also known as &lt;em&gt;relic radiation&lt;/em&gt;. First observed accidentally by the radio engineers Arno Penzias and Robert Wilson in 1965, CMB is a crucial piece of evidence that supports the big bang model for the origin of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three space missions, in particular, have been instrumental in measuring this radiation in finer and finer detail and with better and better precision. NASA’s Cosmic Background Explorer (COBE) took data from 1989 to 1996 and it was the first to detect tiny variations in the intensity of the radiation. Next came the Wilkinson Microwave Anisotropy Probe (WMAP), launched by NASA in 2001. WMAP took data for a decade and its very accurate measurements put constraints on a set of parameters of the big bang model. The current state-of-the-art experiment is ESA’s Planck mission, launched in 2009. The level of accuracy of Planck data is tens of thousands of times greater than the discovery measurements of Penzias and Wilson. Based on the WMAP measurements and theoretical models, the universe is estimated to be 13.82 ± 0.12 billion years old. This is the most quoted age used by astronomers and is consistent with both other measurements within their errors. Remarkably, you can see that this value is very close to what has been estimated using the Hubble constant in equation 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very early in the history of mankind, ignorance of nature and fear of the unknown naturally made men religious. So God played a central role in primitive societies. They tried to answer every question with the help of God. As time passed, with experience and intellect men could understand more and more of the natural phenomenon. I have mentioned in my previous article that if one looks at the long march of human understanding, one will find that science begins with the idea that we can understand our role in the universe using logic and observation. Today humans have come a long way. And mathematics has truly acted as the most essential weapon in almost every known field, including astronomy. By now any reader will understand that in these two articles, I’ve discussed in brief how mathematics in simple form also has helped in the development of astronomy and human knowledge as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Birth of Time: How We Measured The Age Of The Universe; John Gribbin; Weidenfeld &amp;amp; Nicolson; 1999. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.in/books/about/The_Birth_of_Time.html?id=aWG3QgAACAAJ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&quot;&gt;Reference 1 &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Astronomy: The Solar System and Beyond; Michael A. Seeds, Dana E Backmann; Wadsworth Publishing Co Inc; 6th Ed: 2009. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6765882-astronomy&quot;&gt;Reference 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Planetary Science; Michael M. Woolfson, George H.A. Cole; CRC Press; 2013. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.co.in/books/about/Planetary_Science.html?id=B17OBQAAQBAJ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&quot;&gt;Reference 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;History of Astronomy: A Very Short Introduction; Michael Hoskin; Oxford University Press; 2008. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/589339?journalCode=isis&quot;&gt;Reference 4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Astrophysical Techniques; C R Kitchin; CRC Press; 2013. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/266150873_Astrophysical_Techniques_Sixth_Edition_by_CRKitchin&quot;&gt;Reference 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/measurig_age_uiverse_gourav</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/measurig_age_uiverse_gourav</guid>
        
        <category>popular</category>
        
        <category>age_of_universe</category>
        
        <category>big_bang</category>
        
        
        <category>General</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Futuristic gravitational wave observations to resolve dichotomy of compact objects</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Gravitational waves are invisible ripples in space travel at the speed of light. It is generated in different scenarios, such as when two celestial bodies orbit around each other, an isolated body with tri-axial symmetry spins, inhomogeneity in matter distribution in the early universe, etc. Gravitational-wave astronomy aims to study these waves to improve the understanding of objects such as white dwarfs, neutron stars, and black holes, events such as supernovae, and processes including those of the early universe shortly after the Big Bang. The article describes how futuristic gravitational wave observatories can be used to resolve the dichotomy of compact objects.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, astronomy primarily relies on electromagnetic radiation. Over the past hundred years, various interesting astronomical objects have been discovered with gamma-ray detectors to radio telescopes. In recent years, gravitational wave astronomy has opened a new window to probe various exciting objects, and we can now look into the universe from a very different perspective. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LIGO&quot;&gt;LIGO&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virgo_interferometer&quot;&gt;Virgo&lt;/a&gt; gravitational wave detectors have so far made tens of detections from the merger of various compact objects. These are ground-based detectors operating at frequencies more than 1  Hz. As time progresses, these detectors have been upgraded continuously to increase their sensitivities so that we can look objects residing at further distances. Moreover, around 2035, a space-based gravitational wave mission, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elisascience.org&quot;&gt;LISA&lt;/a&gt; is planned to launch, which would operate at less than 1 Hz frequency. Many interesting objects such as galactic binaries, massive binaries, extreme mass ratio inspirals, etc., emit gravitational radiation at less than 1 Hz frequencies. Hence the current ground-based detectors cannot detect these objects, and LISA is planned to probe them. It is important to note that none of these objects are isolated in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, a group of researchers have claimed that LISA might detect some isolated compact objects too. The term compact objects primarily represent white dwarfs, neutron stars, and black holes. White dwarfs are the end state of stars with mass less than &lt;math&gt; (10
&amp;#177;2) M&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt;, where M&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt; ~2 x 10&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt; kg is the mass of the sun, in which the hydrogen fusion has stopped. One such object is the super-Chandrasekhar white dwarf. Over the past couple of decades, various researchers have detected more than a dozen over-luminous &lt;a href=&quot;http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/Astro/snovcn.html&quot;&gt;type Ia supernovae&lt;/a&gt;. Based on these observations, they have inferred that these supernovae have to be originated from massive white dwarfs, which violate the standard Chandrasekhar mass limit of 1.4 M&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt;. As a result, these objects are often termed as super-Chandrasekhar white dwarfs. It has been shown that if a white dwarf possesses strong magnetic fields at the center, such white dwarfs can indeed hold mass more than 1.4  M&lt;sub&gt;⊙&lt;/sub&gt;. Moreover, if such a white dwarf rotates in such a way that there is a misalignment between its magnetic and rotation axes, it can emit continuous gravitational waves. These researchers have explicitly shown that if a white dwarf has a strong central field but a weaker field at its surface, LISA can detect it within 1 year of detection period. On the other hand, if the white dwarf possesses a strong surface field or a weak central field, LISA will not be able to detect it. However, such white dwarfs can be detected by some other futuristic detectors, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20100526050722/http://trs-new.jpl.nasa.gov/dspace/bitstream/2014/37836/1/05-2157.pdf&quot;&gt;BBO&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://tamago.mtk.nao.ac.jp/spacetime/decigo_e.html&quot;&gt;DECIGO&lt;/a&gt;, etc. In this way, LISA can directly confirm the existence of super-Chandrasekhar white dwarfs (Fig. 1). Note that signal-to-noise ratio (S/N) is proportional to the square root of observation time (T) such that S/N increases with the observation time and the signal is more likely to be detected (see Section 1.4 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2019Univ....5..217S/abstract&quot;&gt;Sieniawska &amp;amp; Bejger, 2019, Universe 5, 217&lt;/a&gt;). This likeliness of detection is due to the increase in observation period and not due to the increase in sensitivity of the detectors. If S/N &amp;GreaterEqual; 5, such a signal can be detected by a gravitational wave detector (see Section~2.1 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/415/2/1849/1044522?login=true&quot;&gt;Pitkin, 2011, MNRAS, 415, 1849&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/math&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_to_resolve_dichotomy_of_compact_objects_surajit_images/image_1a.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(a) Poloidally dominated white dwarf.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_to_resolve_dichotomy_of_compact_objects_surajit_images/image_1b.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(b) Toroidally dominated white dwarf&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 1: Gravitational wave S/N as a function of integration time for a white dwarf with central density= 2 × 10&lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt; g cm&lt;sup&gt;−3&lt;/sup&gt;. The thick orange line corresponds to &amp;lt;S/N&amp;gt; ≈ 5.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gravitational wave astronomy is also helpful to resolve the dichotomy of some other objects too. There are some isolated compact objects, named &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.physics.mcgill.ca/~pulsar/magnetar/main.html&quot;&gt;soft gamma repeater~(SGR) and anomalous X-ray pulsar~(AXP)&lt;/a&gt;, which are mostly believed to be neutron stars as they are found to be associated with supernova remnants. However, some of them do not have a supernova remnant association, and their magnetic field is also unknown. Hence, some researchers have also shown that some of their features can be explained assuming they are white dwarfs. To resolve this controversy, the researchers have shown that gravitational wave astronomy is also a helpful tool. It was shown that if they are neutron stars, no proposed gravitational wave detector can detect them. On the other hand, if they are white dwarfs, they can be detected by BBO and DECIGO detectors within 1 year of detection period. The exact time needed for the detection is dependent on the magnetic field configuration and its strength (Fig. 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_to_resolve_dichotomy_of_compact_objects_surajit_images/image_2a.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(a) Poloidally dominated white dwarf.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_to_resolve_dichotomy_of_compact_objects_surajit_images/image_2b.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(b) Toroidally dominated white dwarf&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_to_resolve_dichotomy_of_compact_objects_surajit_images/image_2c.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(c)  Neutron star with radius 14 km.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; Figure 2:  Gravitational wave S/N as a function of integration time for 1RXS J170849.0−400910. In the parentheses of parts (a) and (b), the radius of the white dwarf in the units of km is mentioned. For part (c), in the parentheses, the dominant magnetic field configuration in neutron star is mentioned.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, gravitational wave astronomy will be a useful tool to resolve dichotomy related to various compact objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/508/1/842/6371126&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Resolving dichotomy in compact objects through continuous gravitational waves observation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Surajit Kalita&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tushar Mondal, Christopher A. Tout, Tomasz Bulik, Banibrata Mukhopadhyay&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://iisc.ac.in/&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_compact_objects_surajit</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/futuristic_gravitational_wave_observations_compact_objects_surajit</guid>
        
        <category>Gravitational waves</category>
        
        <category>Neutron Stars</category>
        
        <category>White dwarfs</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
