<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> Welcome to CosmicVarta.</title>
    <description> Platform for promoting Indian astronomy research to the public.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 20:50:07 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 20:50:07 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Star-forming S0 Galaxies in SDSS-MaNGA: fading spirals or rejuvenated S0s?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Galaxies are the building blocks of our universe. A comprehensive theory of how galaxies evolve with cosmic time is key to understanding how the universe turns out the way it is today. Decades of observational, theoretical and computational efforts have been devoted to this purpose. Despite this, observations continue throwing challenges that theories of galaxy evolution cannot explain. In this work, we try to address one such challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the basis of their morphology, i.e. appearance, galaxies can be divided into three classes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Spirals: Spiral galaxies possess a flat rotating disc with spiral arms.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The S0s: S0 galaxies possess a flat rotating disc, but lack spiral arms. Quite often, the side-view of S0s takes the shape of a convex lens, thus in the old days S0s were called Lenticulars.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Ellipticals: Elliptical galaxies, on the other hand, are 3-D ellipsoidal distribution of stars, and do not have any disc-like structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical examples of the three classes are illustrated in Fig. 1 below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin_images/image1a.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin_images/image1b.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin_images/image1c.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: Typical example of a Spiral (top), an S0 (middle) and an Elliptical (bottom) galaxy. (Credits: &lt;a href=&quot;http://skyserver.sdss.org/dr17/&quot;&gt;SDSS, HSC-SSP sky-server&lt;/a&gt;
)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through galaxy formation theories, we know that Spiral galaxies continuously form new stars. Spiral galaxies contain beautiful spiral arms - the places where new stars are born. On the other hand, S0 and elliptical galaxies are found to have stopped any kind of active star formation. But, it turns out that there exist some S0 galaxies in the nearby universe, which are actively star-forming. In our work, we identify a sample of 120 star-forming S0 galaxies in a large galaxy survey known as the SDSS-MaNGA survey. The images of some of these galaxies is shown in Fig. 2 below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin_images/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Very deep HSC-SSP telescope images of some of our star-forming S0 galaxies. (Credits: &lt;a href=&quot;http://skyserver.sdss.org/dr17/&quot;&gt;SDSS, HSC-SSP sky-server&lt;/a&gt;
)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peculiar nature of these star-forming S0s leads us to quite a few questions. First of all, where does the star-formation happen in these galaxies? The spirals have well defined regions where new stars are born - the spiral arms. No such structure is present in the S0s. 
In order to answer this question, we will have to probe within these galaxies and find out where new stars are being born. We cannot do this with the conventional spectroscopic and photometric methods, since they give us the light of the entire galaxy as a whole. This does not allow us to resolve the details inside the galaxy. This is where the revolutionary MaNGA survey comes to the rescue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is so special about the MaNGA survey?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important observables of a galaxy is its spectrum. Spectrum is awesome compared to photometry. Photometry just gives you the total light emitted by the galaxy over a broad range of wavelengths. Whereas, with a spectrum you get the light of the galaxy at every wavelength! That is a lot more information! The spectrum can be used to derive various physical properties of the galaxy, like the Star-Formation Rate (SFR), stellar mass, chemical composition etc. 
In the past decade, most galaxy surveys were equipped with single-aperture spectroscopy. This means you got the spectrum of the entire galaxy as a whole. However, in recent times, advancement in technology has led to the development of Integral Field Spectrographs (IFS). IFS provides us with the spectrum of various spatial regions of a galaxy in a single observation. Let’s understand this in more detail. 
The image of a galaxy is divided into numerous spatial regions (similar to pixels in a photographic image). Each such region is called a spaxel (short for spatial-pixel), and we can obtain the spectrum of each spaxel.&lt;br /&gt;
Because of these spaxels, we get excellent resolution over the 2D image of the galaxy.  With the spectrum of each spaxel, we get the 2D resolved image in each wavelength! Thus, in some sense, IFS provides us with 3D information about the galaxy. The first two axes are the spatial X and Y coordinates, and the third axis is the wavelength. This is illustrated in Fig. 3 below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin_images/image3a.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin_images/image3b.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Top - MaNGA obtains spatially resolved spectra of a galaxy. The galaxy image is divided into various spatial regions, called spaxels. Each spaxel has a spectrum. This leads to what is called a 3D galaxy data-cube (bottom). The first two axes are the spatial X and Y axis of the galaxy image. We obtain the galaxy image at each wavelength (which is the third axis). (Credits: Dana Berry / SkyWorks Digital Inc., David Law, and the SDSS collaboration; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sdss.org/surveys/manga/&quot;&gt;https://www.sdss.org/surveys/manga/&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eso.org/public/&quot;&gt;ESO&lt;/a&gt;
)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SDSS-MaNGA is one such IFS survey. It enables us to study properties of a galaxy in a spatially resolved manner. Thus, we shall be able to understand the physical processes going on in our star-forming S0 galaxies in great detail. In particular, this will help us probe the interiors of these galaxies and find out where the new stars are being born!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start by studying how the Star-Formation Rate (SFR) of the star-forming S0s varies with the distance from the center of the galaxy. This will give us insights about the site and spatial extent of star-formation in these peculiar galaxies. 
When we studied the star formation as a function of distance from the galaxy center for the star-forming S0s, we found that they are forming new stars close to their center. This is opposite to what happens in Spiral galaxies, since most of their star-formation happens in the spiral arms present in the disc - i.e. away from the center. This is a very interesting result about the star-forming S0s, which was not known before!
Having answered where the star-formation is happening in these star-forming S0s, now we get to the even bigger question - why are they forming new stars (being S0s, they are not supposed to do that!) ? In order to answer this question, we would want to go deeper into the past of these galaxies. 
A lot of research suggests that S0 galaxies form from Spiral galaxies. When new stars are no longer being born in a Spiral galaxy, the spiral arms slowly start to fade - and eventually disappear. This leads to a galaxy which has a disc, but no spiral arms - i.e. an S0. So, the star-forming S0s could be a population of Spiral galaxies whose spiral arms have faded, but some star-formation activity is still going on in the center - i.e. a last burst of star-formation. This is just one hypothesis with regards to the formation of star-forming S0s.
Alternatively, the star-forming S0s could be a population of the usual S0s (with no star-formation), whose star-formation has been somehow revived. They could also be something totally out of the box - a galaxy population with a distinct past of its own!
The above hypotheses suggest that there can be various possible connections and comparison points between the star-forming S0s, star-forming Spirals and the usual S0s with no star-formation (also known as quenched S0s). To probe these connections, we construct control samples of star-forming spirals and quenched S0s, in addition to our main sample of star-forming S0s.
Now, a main property that distinguishes different classes of galaxies is how compact the spatial distribution of their stars is. An excellent way to probe this compactness is through the galaxy size - mass relation. The galaxy size is to be plotted on the Y-axis, and its stellar mass on the X-axis. It is well known that different classes of galaxies nicely separate out in this plot. We construct the size - mass relation for our star-forming S0s, star-forming Spirals and the usual quenched S0s in Fig. 4. This will help us to compare and contrast the three galaxy populations, in lieu of the hypotheses presented before regarding the star-forming S0s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin_images/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: Galaxy size (Y-axis) v/s galaxy stellar mass (X-axis) for star-forming S0s (SF-S0s), star-forming Spirals (SF-Sps) and quenched S0s (Q-S0s). Solid line denotes the median trend. (Credits: Authors)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the size - mass plane, the star-forming S0s are quite similar to the quenched S0s, and are different from star-forming Spirals. This suggests that the star-forming S0s are not fading spirals, and are likely to be the usual S0s whose star-formation has been somehow revived! This is another very interesting result which was not confirmed before!
Now the next natural question is, what caused the revival of star-formation in our star-forming S0s? One way in which this can happen is if another gas-rich galaxy merged with our S0, and brought in the necessary Hydrogen gas required for forming new stars. This other galaxy must be significantly less massive than our S0, so that the merger does not end up completely deforming our S0. Such mergers are called minor mergers. 
One key signature of whether a galaxy has undergone a recent minor merger is in the motion of its stars and gas. The minor merger will cause some perturbations to the main galaxy, causing the velocity of stars and gas to get disturbed, as opposed to a coherent rotation around the galaxy center. But how do we study the velocities of stars and gas within these galaxies? Again, MaNGA Integral Field Spectroscopy comes to the rescue! 
Another very useful quantity that can be derived from a spectrum is the velocity of the object along the line of sight, using the principle of Doppler effect (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://spiff.rit.edu/classes/phys301/lectures/doppler/doppler.html&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt; for more details). Using the MaNGA IFS, we obtain the velocities of stars and gas in various regions of our star-forming S0s.
We find that more than 50% of our star-forming S0s have disturbed stellar and gas velocities. In a few cases, we even find the stars and gas rotating in opposite directions about the galaxy center (Fig. 6) !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin_images/image5a.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin_images/image5b.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 5: Example of a counter-rotating star-forming S0. Stars (top) and gas (bottom) rotate in the opposite sense. The gas has likely come from a smaller galaxy that has merged with the main galaxy! (Credits: Authors)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such disturbed and incoherent stellar and gas velocities indicate instabilities triggered by a recent minor merger. This merger could have brought in the necessary gas for reviving the star-formation in the star-forming S0s. Thus, we infer that minor mergers are the most likely cause for the revival of star-formation in our star-forming S0s!
To summarize, in this work, we have been able to answer many questions about these mysterious objects called star-forming S0s. We found that the star-forming S0s form new stars primarily in their central regions, which is opposite to what happens in Spiral galaxies. We also inferred that the star-forming S0s are likely the usual S0s (which do not form new stars), in which star-formation activity has been somehow revived. We conclude that minor merger with a gas-rich galaxy has likely caused this revival. Thus, we have made good progress in solving the mystery behind the existence of star-forming S0s! Moreover, in the bigger picture, our work highlights the importance of minor-mergers as a complex ingredient that shapes how galaxies evolve with time!
Still, quite a few concerns remain. We have 120 galaxies in this work, and ideally, we would like to have a larger sample to constrain our findings better. Many large IFS surveys are coming up in the future, and we look forward to them. Moreover, the star-forming gas of these star-forming S0s needs to be analyzed in more detail to fully confirm whether it has come from another galaxy. Molecular gas observations from radio telescopes and better resolution IFS observations will be very helpful in this pursuit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Himansh and Kavin would like to thank Prof. Yogesh Wadadekar for helpful feedback on this article. Also, a sincere thanks to the Cosmicvaarta editor Kshitija Kelkar, whose constructive suggestions significantly improved the quality of this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/513/1/389/6561635&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Star-forming S0 Galaxies in SDSS-MaNGA: fading spirals or rejuvenated S0s?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Himansh Rathore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kavin Kumar, Preetish K Mishra, Yogesh Wadadekar, Omkar Bait&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Department of Physics, Indian Institute of Technology Bombay, Powai, Mumbai, Maharashtra 400076, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/star_formation_sdss_himansh_kavin</guid>
        
        <category>Galaxies</category>
        
        <category>SDSS</category>
        
        <category>MaNGA</category>
        
        <category>galaxy morphology</category>
        
        <category>S0</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Dimming of Betelgeuse: A Stellar Tipping Point?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Great Dimming of Betelgeuse (alpha Orionis) in late 2019 puzzled astronomers across the globe. The star appeared the faintest in all its modern recorded history. The mystery mounted as it quickly regained brightness in the next few months, and showed interesting patterns of light variations post dimming. Previously, we had investigated the light curve of Betelgeuse from the perspective of nonlinear dynamics and time series analysis (George et al. 2020). We found signatures of a dynamical transition causing a permanent change in the pulsation dynamics of the star. Here, we discuss these results and present further evidence obtained by analysing multiwavelength data from the star, including visible and infrared radiation.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to spot the constellation Orion in the summer night sky—it looks like a hunter or a shepherd with its waist (or belt) characterised by three stars in a straight line. The shoulder of Orion, Betelgeuse, varies in brightness irregularly, so much so that these variations are noticeable to the naked eye! It is therefore classified as a semiregular variable star—an object of fascination since ancient times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Great_Dimming_Betelgeuse_sneha/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: (left) The star Betelgeuse (as seen by the Hubble telescope) and its size in comparison to Earth’s and Jupiter’s orbit. (right) Location of Betelgeuse in the Orion constellation. 
Source: http://hubblesite.org/newscenter/archive/1996/04/ Credit: Andrea Dupree (Harvard-Smithsonian CfA), Ronald Gilliland (STScI), NASA and ESA.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brightness of astronomical objects is measured in terms of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apparent_magnitude&quot;&gt;apparent magnitude&lt;/a&gt;: a reverse logarithmic scale to measure how bright the object appears from the Earth. The full moon registers at about -12.9 on this scale while the Sun is at -26.7. For &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stellar_pulsation&quot;&gt;pulsating variable stars&lt;/a&gt;, this quantity changes periodically as the star repeats cycles of expansions and contractions. Some stars pulsate in a simple periodic manner (corresponding to the so-called fundamental frequency) while others show a more complicated pattern with interfering periods (or frequencies). These additional periods (or corresponding frequencies) can be identified using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aavso.org/sites/default/files/education/vsa/Chapter11.pdf&quot;&gt;complex analysis of the light curve&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analysis of the light curve of Betelgeuse shows a primary period of ~425 days, a secondary period of ~5.9 years and a possible tertiary period of ~180 days. Following these periodicities, its visible brightness can usually go as high as 0.0 and as low as 1.3 in apparent magnitude. At 9 million years old, it is expected to go supernova in the next 100,000 years, and when it does, it will be a spectacular event in the night sky (if we survive until then). Perhaps for this reason, speculations of the impending supernova made headlines when an unprecedented dimming in the star was reported in late 2019 by Prof. Edward Guinan in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.astronomerstelegram.org/?read=13341&quot;&gt;Astronomer’s Telegram&lt;/a&gt;. With a reported apparent magnitude of 1.5614, it was the faintest in its history of modern observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Great_Dimming_Betelgeuse_sneha/image2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Betelgeuse seen with VLT/SPHERE-ZIMPOL before (January 2019) and during (December 2019) the Great Dimming. © ESO/M. Montargès et al.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several hypotheses have been suggested to explain the unprecedented event. These include formation of a dust cloud, gigantic star spots, or an overlapping of the primary and secondary periods. The observed dimming was later confirmed in Infrared as well &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-3881/ac19b5&quot;&gt;(Harper et al., 2021)&lt;/a&gt;, complicating the mystery because the greater part of its radiation actually belongs to the infrared/near-infrared spectrum. Now, like all stars, Betelgeuse emits radiation at all parts of the electromagnetic spectrum, but the intensity at a given wavelength is governed by different factors. The surface temperature, for example, governs the peak observed in the thermal spectrum but there could be localised temperature changes on the surface (star spots), driven by large convection cells. Presence of dust and gas in the circumstellar environment affects the visible region and causes scattering in the UV. Any changes in pulsation also affects the different layers of the star, reflected as variations in different wavelengths. Moreover, these phenomena can happen together, further complicating the interpretation of observed radiation. In the context of Great Dimming of Betelgeuse, it therefore makes sense to ask whether it was a temporary, peripheral phenomenon (such as star spots or dust cloud), or something else, such as changes to the pulsation dynamics (which would likely affect the star as a whole). With this perspective, we investigated the light curve of the star prior to the dimming in all these wavelengths. We start by treating the star as a dynamical system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;multistable-dynamical-systems&quot;&gt;Multistable dynamical systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loosely speaking, a &lt;strong&gt;dynamical system&lt;/strong&gt; is one that evolves in time according to a set of predefined rules. Mathematically, it is a system whose behaviour in time is described by a set of differential equations, subject to some parameters and initial conditions (and external influences). Swinging pendula, celestial bodies in motion, population growth in ecosystems, neuronal synapses, etc., can all be studied as dynamical systems. Some of these systems can exist in one of many possible states. Such &lt;strong&gt;multi-stable&lt;/strong&gt; systems are very interesting and can serve as models of real systems. Let us understand them with the help of a toy model with two possible stable states as illustrated in figure 3:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Great_Dimming_Betelgeuse_sneha/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Schematic representation of a multistable dynamical system. It can be in any state on the curve depending on parameters and initial state, etc. But given enough time, it will occupy either of the stable states, A or B (indicated by the green ball).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when the system existing in state A is perturbed a little, it oscillates around and eventually settles to A. Alternatively, if initially in state B, and given some tiny perturbation, it will eventually settle back down to B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A critical transition in such a system refers to a sudden change in the state, leading to a contrasting dynamics. In our example, it would mean the system going from A to B (or vice-a-versa). The melting of sea ice in recent times and the historically green Sahara becoming a desert, are often cited as examples of such transitions. These transitions are notoriously difficult to anticipate because they happen suddenly. Such transitions are ubiquitous but most recognized in ecology, psychology, and climate. In recent decades, a whole body of literature has focused on the development of so-called &lt;em&gt;Early Warning Signals (EWS)&lt;/em&gt;, that detect such transitions well in advance. Most of these EWS rely on the assumption of &lt;em&gt;Critical Slowing Down&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;critical-slowing-down-and-ews&quot;&gt;Critical Slowing Down and EWS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us imagine that the structure (or stability landscape) from figure 3 is governed by a system parameter β. Increasing β makes the well corresponding to state A shallower, decreasing the system resilience in this state. Decreased resilience implies that any displacement from state A will now be endured longer, increasing correlation in time. This will also reflect in longer return times (captured in recurrence based quantifiers) and increased fluctuations, causing large variance. This phenomenon is commonly known as &lt;strong&gt;Critical Slowing Down (CSD)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Great_Dimming_Betelgeuse_sneha/image4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: In normal conditions (left), small perturbations to the stable state A do not last long and fluctuations are small. But at higher values of system parameter β, the resilience of system in state A decreases, schematically illustrated here as a shallower structure (right). This results in large fluctuations in time (above, right) even with small perturbations, along with longer return times to the stable state.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a certain point, the system reaches a tipping point where the tiniest of disturbance can take the system to the alternate stable state, B. This is called &lt;strong&gt;bifurcation-induced tipping&lt;/strong&gt; (there also exist other types of tipping such as noise-induced tipping and rate-induced tipping, which are beyond the scope of discussion of this article). At this point, the resilience indicators show characteristic trends such as increase in statistical variance (due to perturbations persisting over long time), autocorrelation at lag-1 (correlation in the present state and immediate past state), increase in Hurst exponent (a measure of autocorrelations in the data over different time lags), etc. Similarly, longer return times cause systematic trends in recurrence-based quantifiers. Such trends indicate the existence of a tipping point and are therefore collectively known as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.early-warning-signals.org/?page_id=480&quot;&gt;Early Warning Signals (EWS)&lt;/a&gt; of a dynamical transition. It can be noted that although the example discussed here is a very simple one, CSD and associated EWS have been applied in more nuanced contexts in different areas ranging from psychology, finance, ecology and climate change, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;critical-transition-in-betelgeuse&quot;&gt;Critical transition in Betelgeuse&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to Betelgeuse, we considered it as a dynamical system and analysed the light curve data collected by the The American Association of Variable Star Observers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aavso.org/&quot;&gt;(AAVSO)&lt;/a&gt;. We identified some of the EWS in this data prior to dimming. The process consists of taking subsequent windows (sections) of the light curve in a sliding fashion (i.e. with some overlap), moving a few data points at a time. Then, statistical measures for these windows are calculated and plotted against time, as shown in the figure 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Great_Dimming_Betelgeuse_sneha/image5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 5: Variation in the (a) Autocorrelation at lag 1 and (b) Variance calculated from the light curve of Betelgeuse upto the dimming (red), during the dimming (blue) and post dimming (green). The left panels (figures 1a and 1b) show the variation from 1990 onwards using a window size of 300 points on data binned every 10 days. The right panels zoom into a region around the dimming, with data binned every 5 days with a window size of 40. &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.aavso.org/webobs/results/?star=000-BBK-383&amp;amp;num_results=200&quot;&gt;Based on the data from AAVSO database&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, these measures rise prior to the dimming, and serve as strong evidence of a dynamical transition preceded by CSD. Now, we know that the variability in the light curve of Betelgeuse is primarily governed by pulsation. EWS in the data, therefore, hint at a transition affecting its pulsation dynamics. Of course, the credibility of these results relies on statistical significance (further details in the paper). However, there is another way we can verify the existence of a transition—by looking at the variation in other wavelengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;variations-in-other-wavelengths&quot;&gt;Variations in other wavelengths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The radiation of a star comprises of different components of the electromagnetic spectrum. These components originate due to different stellar processes. In the case of Betelgeuse, the greatest part of electromagnetic radiation is in the infrared. In fact, Betelgeuse is the brightest star in infrared as seen from Earth! Naturally, the variations in this part of the spectrum are highly relevant to understand the dynamics of Betelgeuse. The multiwavelength data discussed in the paper has been taken with permission from &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-3881/ac19b5&quot;&gt;Harper et al. (2021)&lt;/a&gt;. It consists of a simplified three-filter system devised by &lt;a href=&quot;https://adsabs.harvard.edu/pdf/1992JAVSO..21...42W&quot;&gt;Wing et al. (1992)&lt;/a&gt; for red variable stars. Wing A filter is dominated by the TiO 719 nm (narrow band) and the Wing B and C filters are continuum bands centred around 750 nm and 1024 nm respectively. These filters are carefully selected to measure the infrared magnitude, colour and the spectral type of the star. The primary use of this filter system is for estimating surface temperature of these stars. In addition, this data also includes measurements in the V-band centred around 555 nanometer (nm), that can be compared to the same region in the AAVSO data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Great_Dimming_Betelgeuse_sneha/image6.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 6: Variation of intensity in Betelgeuse, as captured in Vis/V band AAVSO data (grey), V-band photometry from Wasatonic laboratory (blue), and Infrared Wing three-filter (A: green, B: orange, C: red) data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is apparent from figure 6 that the dimming was simultaneous in all wavelengths! Further, we calculated the cross-correlation among these wavelengths, and found a systematic decrease before dimming as shown in figure 7:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Great_Dimming_Betelgeuse_sneha/image7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 7: Pearson correlation coefficient calculated for each pair of wavelengths, indicated here in different colours. These correlations in time decrease prior to dimming.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dimming could be just a normal cycle of the star but brightness variations in the past have never been so extreme (within the limits of available data). Since the infrared radiation comes from deeper layers of the star, we conclude that the dimming was not a surface phenomena. Further, since the dimming was simultaneous in all bands, we can argue that it was related to a dynamical process that affected the whole star, making change in pulsation dynamics the natural answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-current-state-of-the-stellar-matter&quot;&gt;The current state of the (stellar) matter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the measurements post dimming seem to validate the dynamical transition. For example, the brightening of the star was almost as quick as the dimming, and the next seasonal cycle was ‘rounder’ than ever! Moreover, later studies found increased prominence of the ~180 day period. These observations suggest a permanent change to the pulsation dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Great Dimming of Betelgeuse continues to astonish us, even with all the new data we have from Hubble and other sources. Possibilities range from a dynamical transition or overlapping of periodic cycles, to a dust cloud or a large star spot, but (sadly) almost certainly not a supernova! Betelgeuse is a complex star—full of mystery—and we excitedly await to observe and understand more about it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2111.09218&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Evidence for dynamical changes in Betelgeuse using multi-wavelength data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt;  Sneha Kachhara&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Sandip V. George, Ranjeev Misra, and G. Ambika&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Science Education and Research (IISER) Tirupati, Tirupati, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/Great_Dimming_Betelgeuse_sneha</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Great_Dimming_Betelgeuse_sneha</guid>
        
        <category>early warning signals</category>
        
        <category>stellar dynamics</category>
        
        <category>dynamical systems</category>
        
        <category>critical transition</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How do astronomers understand the evolution of young stars in star clusters?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This article is based on the paper published in the Journal of Astrophysics &amp;amp; Astronomy. The article shows the results of our deep optical photometric observations of a young cluster NGC 1893 taken with the 3.6m Devasthal Optical Telescope. Based on the optical data obtained with the data along with the Gaia data, we characterized the young stars in the central region of the cluster and determined their age, mass and membership. We found that the distribution of masses of young low-mass stars in the cluster is similar to that of other Galactic clusters.  Our analysis suggested a primordial mass segregation in the cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stars form out of dense clouds made up of molecular gas and dust. A majority of these stars emerge as groups or clusters. Star clusters contain stars that are gravitationally stable against dispersion for reasonably long periods of time. Stars in a cluster have the same age and chemical composition (metallicity) but differ in mass and hence are found in different evolutionary stages, allowing astronomers to test stellar evolution theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent observational studies of nearby star-forming regions show that more than half of their young stars are associated with groups of ten or more stars. Therefore, young star clusters are crucial to understand the physical processes involved in the birth and evolution of stars and star clusters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/evolution_young_star_cluster_neelam/image1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig. 1 : A  young cluster NGC 1893 in star-forming region Sh2-236
(&lt;em&gt;Credits: A color-composite image created using DSS2-R (blue), Spitzer-IRAC 3.6 micron (green) and Spitzer-IRAC 4.5 micron (red) images.
&lt;/em&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star clusters enable astronomers to place the stars of a wide range of masses within the Hertzsprung-Russel (HR) diagram that shows the relationship between a star’s temperature and its luminosity and infer their evolutionary stages and physical parameters, such as age, mass etc. The mass of a star is one of the most important factors providing constraint to its future evolution, but it is not clearly known what determines the exact mass of a newly forming star. One aspect of this problem is the knowledge of the distribution of stellar masses, initial mass function (IMF), in a star cluster.  However, the precise statistics for low-mass stars (stars smaller than the Sun) are somewhat uncertain as they are faint. The theoretical basis for the IMF, variation with the metallicity, environment etc., is challenged by the observational evidence for the universality of the IMF. With the sensitive instruments mounted on moderate size telescopes, e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cfht.hawaii.edu&quot;&gt;Canada-France-Hawaii Telescope&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aries.res.in/facilities/astronomical-telescopes/360cm-telescope&quot;&gt;Devasthal Optical Telescope (DOT)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://subarutelescope.org/en/&quot;&gt;Subaru&lt;/a&gt; etc., that are capable of detecting fainter low-mass stars, now it is possible to shed light on the IMF of the cluster towards the very low-mass end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research work focuses on a young star cluster NGC 1893 from the New General Catalog (NGC was compiled by J. L. E. Dreyer in the year 1888 and contains about 7840 celestial objects mostly galaxies, nebulae and star clusters). In order to get more insights into the properties of the stars in a young cluster NGC 1893 (Fig. 1), Dr. Neelam Panwar and a team of astronomers of the Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES) in India performed photometric monitoring of this cluster. For this purpose, they employed the 4Kx4K Imager camera mounted on the 3.6-meter ARIES DOT.  Image Reduction and Analysis Facility (IRAF) software is used for image reduction and analysis. Various programs developed in Python and C++ programming languages are also used for data analysis and plotting. The optical data from DOT were deep enough to reveal very low-mass stars (about 0.2 times the mass of the Sun) in NGC 1893 (Fig. 2). The DOT data allowed the team to identify about 420 young stars in the central portion of the cluster, out of which 110 turned out to be new members. The study was complemented by archival data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://sci.esa.int/web/gaia&quot;&gt;ESA’s Gaia&lt;/a&gt; satellite, a sample of young stars obtained using infrared data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.ipac.caltech.edu/2mass/&quot;&gt;2MASS&lt;/a&gt;/ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spitzer.caltech.edu/&quot;&gt;Spitzer space telescope&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://chandra.harvard.edu/&quot;&gt;Chandra X-ray&lt;/a&gt; data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/evolution_young_star_cluster_neelam/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig.2 : HR diagram showing the evolutionary stages for different mass stars (left). Distribution of stellar masses in the young cluster (right). (&lt;em&gt;Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.11796&quot;&gt;arXiv:2111.11796 &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To determine the physical parameters of the cluster, it is essential to select the stars that are associated with the cluster. Since cluster members share nearly similar motion in the plane of the sky,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://vizier.u-strasbg.fr/viz-bin/VizieR-3?-source=I/350/gaiaedr3&quot;&gt;Gaia Early Data Release 3&lt;/a&gt; catalogue is used to select the kinematic members, i.e., stars having similar proper motion values and estimate the distance of the cluster using the mean parallax of the cluster members. The young cluster is found approximately 10,600 light years away from the Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For faint stars (about V&amp;gt;20 mag which corresponds to about solar mass, as seen in the CMD for NGC 1893) there is higher uncertainty in the proper motion, parallax values.The kinematic information is accurate upto sun-like stars. As the cluster is young (with an age of less than 10 million years), its low-mass members are still contracting towards the main sequence. Hence, the low-mass cluster members are young stars for which the HR diagram (optical color-magnitude diagram) yields ages less than 10 million years. They also studied the mass distribution of the young low-mass stars in the cluster and found that it is similar to other young clusters, i.e., their results favour the idea of a universal IMF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observations of star clusters show that relatively massive stars are often found to be located toward the cluster centre. It is not well understood if this mass segregation is due to the dynamical evolution of the star cluster or if this is related to the star formation process itself. Their analysis also suggested that stars with masses above half of the solar mass are located toward the cluster centre as compared to the stars with masses lower than this limit, indicating primordial mass segregation in the young cluster&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12036-021-09785-5&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Deep V and I CCD photometry of young star cluster NGC 1893 with the 3.6m DOT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt;  Neelam Panwar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Amit Kumar, S. B. Pandey&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Manora Peak, Nainital-263002&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/evolution_young_star_cluster_neelam</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/evolution_young_star_cluster_neelam</guid>
        
        <category>Young star clusters</category>
        
        <category>stellar evolution</category>
        
        <category>Initial Mass Function</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why are some jets curved: presence of dancing blackholes?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;A small percentage of the ejected hot plasma flows (the jets) from supermassive blackholes are observed to deviate from their intended path, resulting in unusual jetted morphologies. One of these peculiarities appears when the jet starts to dance /precess around an axis, forming curved jets with &lt;strong&gt;S-shaped&lt;/strong&gt; morphology. When we observe such sources through radio telescopes, we see a massive S-like structure floating in the vast cosmos. Due to their peculiar morphology, the formation mechanism of such sources is still debated. Simultaneously, an increasing number of such sources are being discovered with even more complex S-shaped structures, making the unravelling of the underlying physics more difficult than earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A blackhole is a voracious cosmic giant that feeds on surrounding matter to grow. Its gravitational pull  is so strong that anything that enters inside a certain radius (known as event horizon), finds no way  out, not even the fastest thing in this universe; the light photons. There is no limit to how large a  blackhole can grow in size. The largest of them are supermassive blackholes (nearly a billion times  more massive than the sun; SMBH), which are found at the centres of galaxies. Some of these SMBH  enter into an active phase (not yet fully understood how), during which they accrete matter  (surrounding hot ionised gas/plasma) at an accelerated rate, with some of this material being violently  ejected down the SMBH’s spin axis due to a complex process caused by a powerful magnetic  disturbance. The super-heated plasma material that is thrown out traverses a distance ranging from  sub-parsec to a few megaparsec in space with a velocity nearing the speed of light. Just to compare with our usable scales, one parsec is 3.26 light-years (a distance that light travels in a year). These  ejected streams of matter are called jets, which are destined to propagate along a straight path while  carrying the magnetic field from their origin. As a result, they mostly emit radiation at radio  frequencies due to the synchrotron process (a process where charged particles radiate when they  move in curved paths in magnetic fields), and hence we need radio telescopes to observe and study  them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/curved_jets_dancing_blackhole_gourab/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
(&lt;em&gt;Credit: https://fermi.gsfc.nasa.gov/science/eteu/agn/&lt;/em&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small percentage of these ejected hot plasma flows (the jets) are observed to deviate from their  intended path, resulting in unusual jetted morphologies. One of these peculiarities appears when the  jet starts to dance /precess around an axis, forming curved jets with &lt;strong&gt;S-shaped&lt;/strong&gt; morphology. When  we observe such sources through radio telescopes, we see a massive S-like structure floating in the  vast cosmos. Due to their peculiar morphology, the formation mechanism of such sources is still  debated. Simultaneously, an increasing number of such sources are being discovered with even more complex S-shaped structures, making the unravelling of the underlying physics more difficult than  earlier. Some examples of these radio sources are highlighted below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/curved_jets_dancing_blackhole_gourab/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Top image&lt;/strong&gt;: Image of SS 433 (obtained from VLA radio telescope), a micro-quasar in our galaxy  (similar system to what we are discussing here, but with a smaller length scale) showing the  presence of bidirectional precessing jets. [Credit: NRAO]. &lt;strong&gt;Bottom image&lt;/strong&gt;: Another example of  precessing jets of a powerful radio galaxy 4C +12.50, studied by Lister et al. 2003.
(&lt;em&gt;Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nrao.edu/pr/2004/ss433corkscrew/&quot;&gt;SS 433&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.astroexplorer.org/details/10_1086_345666_fg6&quot;&gt;4C +12.50&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/em&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To uncover the underlying mechanism that produces these sources, I, along with a team of Indian  scientists, have conducted a study where we tried to numerically (using computer simulation) reproduce an observed peculiar S-shaped source that has recently been observed using  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aoc.nrao.edu/evla/&quot;&gt;the Expanded Very Large Array Telescope&lt;/a&gt; in New Mexico. The source has a  technical name &lt;em&gt;2MASX J1203&lt;/em&gt;. At first appearance, the jets seem to propagate along a straight line from the compact core of the galaxy (centre of mystery!) and end in hotspots (places where jets  terminate or encounter a major collision with the ambient medium). But afterwards, the jets suddenly  bend in opposite directions, making a structure that looks like a wing. This is why it is called an &lt;em&gt;S shaped winged source&lt;/em&gt;. Our novel simulations have modelled this peculiar galaxy using a precessing  jet and have shown that it is not only the jet precession that causes such ambiguities in morphology  but also the galactic medium through which the jet is travelling shape the structure. The heavy galactic  medium (mostly gas) exerts additional force on opposing jet’s free propagation leading to slowing  down the jet significantly, as well as causing it to be unstable as it propagates to longer distances. The resultant structure, when observed from a fortuitous viewing angle (the orientation angle an object  makes with respect to the observer here on Earth), we see the formation of such peculiar &lt;em&gt;S-shaped  winged&lt;/em&gt; sources on the sky plane; what we see in the sky is just a two-dimensional representation of  three-dimensional objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/curved_jets_dancing_blackhole_gourab/image4.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.04705&quot;&gt;arXiv:2206.04705&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To elaborate our work a bit more, we have carried out computer simulations by adopting a novel  approach where we modelled not only the observed morphology but also the underlying micro physical processes of this radio structure. To answer the morphological peculiarity of the source, we first built a setup where a precessing jet is being injected from the centre of a realistic galactic medium whose time evolution we have further followed. As time progresses, the precessing jet grows in size, and at time 2.23 mega-year, a fully grown dancing jet is formed. When you see this structure from a  particular angle (the line-of-sight), the structure will appear as an S-shaped source with extended wing-like substructures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/curved_jets_dancing_blackhole_gourab/image5.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.04705&quot;&gt;arXiv:2206.04705&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must mention that finding this fortuitous line-of-sight angle, as well as the jet parameters that  perfectly mimic the observed source (2MASX J1203) was quite a challenging task. This is because the  existing models that tend to predict these parameters of dancing jets have seemed to ignore the jet  deceleration effects imparted by the ambient medium, which have been self-consistently adopted in  our simulations. As a result, our study pointed out that for a better determination of precessing jet’s parameters, numerical simulations are a better choice. Furthermore, when we started to model the  synchrotron emission part of this structure, we found out that the galaxy is radiating at a higher level  that contradicts the theories if we consider that the hot plasma of the jet is radiating away its energies  via radiation as well as via adiabatic expansion of the whole system with time. This further hint that  the radiating non-thermal particles are somehow getting re-energized, which is keeping the structure  alive for a longer time than what has been anticipated from theories. Using our simulations, we explicitly demonstrated that diffusive shock acceleration is the physical factor that assists the particle  in regaining energy supplied by the generated shocks in the medium. These shocks were formed by  the jet’s supersonic flows (flows that move faster than the sound speed in that medium), which caused  the source to be more active than it should have been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant question now arises: why did the jet begin to precess in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we have a water fountain that sprays water to a certain height. Now, if we want to make the  ejected stream of water precess around an axis, one has to externally precess the nozzle from where  water is ejected. Similarly, in our astrophysical scenario, the blackhole that is responsible for jet  ejection has to be precessed by an external force. It has been theorized that a secondary supermassive  blackhole possibly orbits close to the primary one, causing the spin axis of the primary SMBH to  precess. The secondary SMBH came from another galaxy that has recently collided with the existing  one, resulting in two SMBHs in a single galaxy. It has been observed that galaxies do collide with each  other, and in the local Universe, the rate of it is significant too. Hence the systematic dance of the  binary blackholes most possibly have made the jet to precess. In this regard, our numerical simulations have successfully constrained the precession period of the jet, using which one can calculate the  separation of the binary BHs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, only a handful of dual AGNs have been discovered yet, maybe because we are looking at  the wrong sources. Nonetheless, these sources with curved/bent jets can now be the ideal candidates  to look for dual SMBH pairs at their centres, detection of which can further help us better understand  the evolution of supermassive blackholes throughout the Universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/514/4/5625/6608271&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dynamical modelling and emission signatures of a candidate dual AGN with precessing radio jets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt;  Gourab Giri&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ravi Pratap Dubey, K Rubinur, Bhargav Vaidya, Preeti Kharb&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Technology Indore, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/curved_jets_dancing_blackhole_gourab</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/curved_jets_dancing_blackhole_gourab</guid>
        
        <category>Magnetohydrodynamics</category>
        
        <category>Blackholes</category>
        
        <category>Jet precession</category>
        
        <category>Shock acceleration</category>
        
        <category>Radiation mechanisms</category>
        
        <category>Active galaxies</category>
        
        <category>Jet-Galaxy interaction</category>
        
        <category>Dual AGN</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Core-collapse supernova from a possible progenitor star of 100 solar mass</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Supernovae are extreme astrophysical transient phenomena marking the death of stars. In this article, I take you to the journey of the life of a star as massive as 100 times our sun. Through the state-of-the-art simulation tool &lt;strong&gt;MESA&lt;/strong&gt;, we have studied the overall life of a 100 solar mass star and the implications of the resulting supernova. At the time of its birth, the 100 solar mass star is around 10 times bigger than the current size of our sun, while in the last stages of its life, it has evolved to around 1700 times the current size of our sun. The energy released from the resulting supernova from such a massive star would be so powerful that it would take around 100 million Suns shining together for a period of at least a few hundred days.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking up into the sky on a clear and dark night, we can see thousands of stars twinkling. While sleeping on the rooftop of my home in our village during summer days, I used to wonder why the night sky looked similar every night. The stars present in the sky last night used to appear in the sky every other night. Similarly, seeing the constellation Ursa Major (popularly known as &lt;em&gt;Saptarishi Taramandal in Hindi&lt;/em&gt;) shining brightly with its seven visible stars every summer night, I used to scratch my tiny mind about the unchanging nature of the heavens. But, do the heavens remain unchanged? No, not at all! Similar to the lifespan of a human being, every star that we see in the sky has a finite lifetime. Accumulation of cosmic clouds gives birth to stars in the form of spherical blobs by burning hydrogen as fuel in their core. These stars grow older while spreading a tremendous amount of energy in the form of light/radiation and finally die with no active fuel burning left in their core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The death of each star (for less massive stars having masses &amp;lt; 8 M⊙ subjected to mass accretion from a companion) is marked by one final, massive detonation or explosion, and the phenomenon is known as a supernova (SN), an event so bright that even if it occurred in another, very far galaxy, it could be seen from the telescopes available on earth and in space. The only difference between the lifetime of humans and stars is that humans can have a lifespan of around a hundred years or so only, but the stars live for a few million to a few billion years of age! This is the reason why the heavens in the night appear unchanged every night when seen through the naked eyes. However, as I mentioned above, the heavens change, with supernovae (SNe) being one of the means. So, has there been any bright supernova event in human civilizations that could have been seen through the naked eyes? Yes, nine such events have been identified and recorded by human civilizations in the past 2000 years! The first SN event was recorded in 185 A.D. by the ancient Chinese, as referenced in the work of two Roman chroniclers. Around 200 years later, two bright SNe in 386 A.D. and 393 A.D. were also recorded. The fourth one is the most bright SN in human history, which occurred in the year 1006 A.D., an event so bright that it could cast shadows on the ground. The fifth and sixth SNe seen through the naked eyes occurred in 1054 A.D. and 1181 A.D., respectively. The remnant of the SN that occurred in 1054 A.D. is known as the very famous &lt;em&gt;crab nebula&lt;/em&gt;. The seventh and eighth SNe seen through the naked eyes occurred in 1572 A.D. (known as Tycho’s supernova) and 1604 A.D. (known as Kepler’s supernova). The ninth SN seen through the naked eyes occurred just a few decades earlier, in 1987, named SN 1987A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our sun is a star in our galaxy &lt;em&gt;Milky Way&lt;/em&gt; which hosts about a billion other stars, many of them having masses greater or lesser than our sun. Further, in the known universe, there are billions of other galaxies, each of them hosting billions of stars. However, the SNe can be so bright that they can outshine their entire host galaxy and can be seen through the telescopes on earth even if they are occurring in other galaxies (or, in other words, being extra-galactic). Once such SNe is detected through space-based or ground-based telescopes, they are followed up, and their brightness is recorded until they become fainter beyond the detection limits of telescopes. For SN, the variation in brightness (or intrinsic luminosity) over a period of time is called its &lt;em&gt;light curve&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;With the state of the art software and simulation techniques, we are now capable of studying the lifespan of a star. We can numerically evolve a certain mass star from birth to death and study its implications. A review of one such work is presented in this article. Here, we have studied the life span of a star as massive as 100 M⊙. Figure 1 shows the change in the size of 100 M⊙ star as it evolves through various phases of its life. This star starts as a relatively smaller blob of gas, evolves to grow bigger, and during its last evolutionary stages, it has grown in size, having a radius of a few 1000 times bigger than our sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/2020fqv_core_collapse_superova_amar_images/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1 : The evolution of the size (measured by its radius) of a 100 solar mass star as it gets birth (left panel), becomes an adult (mid panel), and finally reaches the stage where it is about to die (rightmost panel). The subplot in the left-bottom corner marks the star&apos;s position on HR diagram (which is the variation of luminosity with effective surface temperature). The figures are also color-coded with blue meaning hot and red meaning less hot. These figures have made use of the results from Aryan et al. 2022. (Credits: Author)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the last evolutionary stages (approaching its death), the star is mainly composed of inert Iron in its core, and the burning of fuel in the core has almost stopped. Due to this, the core of the star is vacated of any radiation. The role of the presence of radiation in the core of a star is vital as it is the source of radiation pressure responsible for balancing the self-gravity of the core. But, when the core is vacated of almost all the radiations, there is no support to the self-gravity of the core, and it &lt;em&gt;starts to collapse&lt;/em&gt; under its own gravity resulting in a core-collapse supernova.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
   &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/2020fqv_core_collapse_superova_amar_images/image2.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2 : (Left )The variation of the core temperature (T&lt;sub&gt;core&lt;/sub&gt;)  and core density (&amp;rho;&lt;sub&gt;core&lt;/sub&gt;) as the 100 M⊙ star is born and evolves older to reach the last evolutionary stage reaching on the verge of core collapse. The blue triangle marks the core temperature and density at the birth of the star, while the red solid circle marks the same when the star is on the verge of death. This panel makes use of the results from Aryan et. al 2022. (Right) The light curves of supernovae resulting from the death of a 100 M⊙ star by keeping total explosion energy constant and varying the amount of total nickel mass. For comparison purposes, the light curves of three similar type supernovae are also shown but these three supernovae result from much lower mass (10 - 20 M⊙) stars. This figure has been adapted from Aryan et al. 2022.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The left panel of Figure 2 shows the variation of core temperature (T&lt;sub&gt;core&lt;/sub&gt;) with core density (ρ&lt;sub&gt;core&lt;/sub&gt;) as the 100 M⊙ star evolves from its birth (marked by a blue triangle) to the stage where it is about to die (marked by red solid-circle). We could see that near the last evolutionary stages, the core temperature and core density have reached in excess of 1010 K and 1010 g cm-3, respectively. Keeping such high density in a normal human life perspective, a matchbox full of such core material would weigh around 200 million Kg!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right panel of Figure 2 shows the light curves when a 100 M &amp;amp;odot; star explodes as a core-collapse supernova. The resulting SNe are Type IIP-like that are identified by a phase of nearly constant luminosity (also called &lt;em&gt;plateau&lt;/em&gt; phase) in their light curves. The length of the plateau is dependent on the size of the Hydrogen envelope retained by the star. So, we can see that SN 1999em, SN 2005cs, and SN2009N have shorter plateau duration, as they arrive from much lower stars having masses in the range of 10 to 20 M⊙. Further, in the right panel of Figure 2, on increasing the Nickel mass while keeping the explosion energy constant, the duration of the plateau in the light curve is increased. This behavior due to the increase in Nickel mass is attributed to the increase in energy deposition in the expanding ejecta by the γ rays that are produced by the radioactive decay of Nickel (&lt;sup&gt;56&lt;/sup&gt;Ni) and Cobalt (&lt;sup&gt;56&lt;/sup&gt;Co). 
One can also notice that the explosions from such a massive star would be so humongous that they would radiate at a rate of 10&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt; ergs/s or more for at least a period of 350 days. Again putting it in an observational perspective, it would be equal to around 100 million Suns shining together for a period of at least 350 days! Thus, the core-collapse supernovae are extreme catastrophic phenomena and are among one of the major events marking the alterable heavens. Keeping these aspects of supernovae in mind, we conclude that the heavens do change. It only requires an eye of a keen observer to see the change!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symbols used&lt;/strong&gt; : 
M⊙= Mass of the Sun&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt; : &lt;em&gt;This article has been submitted for the DST-AWSAR award.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional read&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A) Aryan et al. 2022, JApA, 43, 2, and,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;B) &lt;em&gt;Supernovae&lt;/em&gt; by Paul &amp;amp; Lesley Murdin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12036-021-09784-6&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Core-collapse supernova from a possible progenitor star of 100 M⊙&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Amar Aryan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shashi Bhushan Pandey, Abhay Pratap Yadav, Amit Kumar, Rahul Gupta, and Sugriva Nath Tiwari&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Manora Peak, Nainital-263002, India and Department of Physics, Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Gorakhpur University, Gorakhpur-273009, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/2020fqv_core_collapse_superova_amar</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2020fqv_core_collapse_superova_amar</guid>
        
        <category>Stars</category>
        
        <category>Supernova</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Revealing the nature of the brightest &amp; explosive astronomical sources in the sky using 3.6m Devasthal Optical Telescope (DOT)</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;India has a long history of more than two decades of observations of optical counterparts of gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) using Indian meter-class telescopes like the 1.04m Sampurnanand Telescope (ST), 1.3m Devasthal Fast Optical Telescope (DFOT), 2m Himalayan Chandra Telescope (HCT), and 2.34m Vainu Bappu Telescope (VBT) utilizing the longitudinal advantage of the place. In recent times, astronomers started exploring these exciting and explosive astronomical sources using recently commissioned (since 2016) India’s largest optical telescope, i.e., 3.6m Devasthal Optical Telescope (DOT) at Devasthal observatory of Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Nainital. In a short period of the proposed target of opportunity (ToO) observations (since cycle 2020-C2), DOT discovered many interesting results such as the detection of long GRB (GRB 211211A) from a neutron star-white dwarf merger, the detection of host galaxies of peculiar GRBs, the detection of most delayed optical flare (GRB 210204A) observed from any GRB so far, etc. This article briefly summarizes the recent discovery of dark (GRB 210205A) and orphan (AT2021any/ZTF21aaeyldq) afterglows of GRBs using 3.6m DOT + 4K × 4K CCD Imager.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to humans, stars also have a life cycle. They are born, live, and at some point, they die. High mass (more massive than eight solar mass) and low mass (typical to solar mass) stars follow a different life cycle. The death of massive stars produces the brightest and most explosive astronomical sources known as gamma-ray bursts (GRBs). GRBs are powerful bursts of high-energy gamma-ray radiation and are among the most exotic phenomena studied in modern astronomy. GRB emits more energy in a second than our Sun will emit in its lifetime. GRB events have two distinct emission phases: one is the short-lived prompt emission (the initial burst phase, peak at sub-MeV energy range), followed by a long-lived multiwavelength afterglow phase. The prompt emission (initial gamma-ray emission) of GRBs is automatically discovered by space-based gamma-ray missions such as NASA’s Fermi Gamma-ray Space Telescope, Neil Gehrels Swift Observatory, India’s AstroSat, and many more. Based on the observed time scale of prompt emission, astronomers classify GRBs as long or short, whether the event lasts more or less than two seconds. Their duration is associated with their origin: long GRBs occur with the death of massive stars, while short GRBs have been proven to be the electromagnetic counterparts of the gravitational wave (originated due to the merger of two compact objects) signals discovered recently by LIGO/Virgo.
GRBs are believed to originate from a “jet” moving at a relativistic speed, launched by a fast rotating stellar-mass black hole or magnetized neutron star formed at the core collapse of a massive star (long GRBs, duration &amp;gt; 2 sec) or in the merger of compact objects (short GRBs, duration &amp;lt; 2 sec). The ejected out-flowing can have various shells that can collide with each other creating internal shock, which is responsible for the prompt gamma-ray emission. Later on, this material expands and interacts with the pre-existing material surrounding the GRB events (external shock), producing the broadband synchrotron radiation, which attributes to the afterglow emission (see Fig. 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/grb_dot_rahul_gupta/image1.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: The theoretical understanding of prompt emission and afterglow of GRBs (Credits: Dr. S. Iyyani.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after the GRB-prompt discovery, ground-based multi-wavelength observational facilities (including ARIES telescopes in the optical/NIR bands) started searching for the associated afterglows across the electromagnetic spectrum. Specifically, optical observations play a crucial role in constraining the redshift, energetics, environments, and geometry of these powerful astronomical sources. The longitudinal advantage of the Devasthal observatory (which lies in between the Canary Islands and Eastern Australia) and deep imaging/spectroscopy capabilities of back-end instruments (at visible and near-infrared bands) of the 3.6m DOT telescope (see Fig. 2a) together provide a unique opportunity to perform deep and longer follow-up observations of the optical counterparts/ associated host galaxies of GRBs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the optical brightness, some of the optical afterglows of GRBs are defined as &lt;em&gt;Dark GRBs.&lt;/em&gt; In the case of dark GRBs, either optical afterglow is very faint or not detected even after a deep and long search using optical telescopes. In addition, a few rare optical afterglows are detected independently without any prior prompt emission detection from space-based gamma-ray satellites, known as &lt;em&gt;Orphan GRBs.&lt;/em&gt; This article highlights the recent discovery of dark (GRB 210205A) and orphan (AT2021any/ZTF21aaeyldq) afterglows of GRBs using 3.6m DOT+ 4K × 4K CCD Imager (see Fig. 2b).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/grb_dot_rahul_gupta/image2a.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2a: A picture of the 3.6m DOT telescope (India’s largest optical facility) installed at Devasthal observatory of ARIES, Nainital. (Credits: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/3.6m_Devasthal_Optical_Telescope#/media/File:3.6m_Devasthal_Optical_Telescope.jpg&quot;&gt;Ajay Talwar, Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/grb_dot_rahul_gupta/image2b.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2b: The detection of the third known orphan afterglow with a measured redshift so far using 3.6m DOT + 4K × 4K CCD Imager. (Credits: Author)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of GRB 210205A, an X-ray afterglow was discovered using Swift X-ray Telescope (XRT). We performed the optical follow-up observations to search for the optical afterglow using the 3.6m DOT + 4K × 4K CCD Imager; however, we did not find any optical afterglow despite deep follow-up observations, supporting the dark nature of the burst. We investigated the possible reason for the optical darkness. We found that either intrinsic faintness of the source or high redshift origin was a possible reason for the optical darkness of the afterglow of GRB 210205A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For AT2021any, no gamma-ray prompt emission counterpart was reported by any space-based satellites, and the Zwicky Transient Facility (ZTF, a survey telescope)  independently discovered this source. We also detected this object using 3.6m DOT + 4K × 4K CCD Imager (see Fig. 2b) and found that it is the third known orphan afterglow with a measured redshift. The detection of orphan afterglows can be explained by one of the scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the source is observed on-axis (viewed along the line of sight to the observer on the Earth), similar to typical GRBs, however, the prompt emission of GRBs (the initial gamma-ray counterpart) was unambiguously missed by space-based gamma-ray telescopes, either due to their limiting sensitivity or source was not in their field of view.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suppose the source is observed off-axis (viewed outside the line of sight to the observer on the Earth). In that case, the emitted flux from the prompt emission decreases very sharply outside the opening of the jet because of the relativistic beaming of photons (when photons are moving with ultra-relativistic speed emit radiation in a beam in the direction of motion). Such faint prompt emission will be very hard to detect by GRB satellites. Later on, as the jet decelerates (due to external shock), the relativistic beaming becomes less intense, and the emission from the jet becomes detectable to observers at larger viewing angles (off-axis). We only detect the afterglow emission without any prior detection of the prompt gamma-ray emission (see Fig. 3).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/grb_dot_rahul_gupta/image3.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: A schematic diagram showing the possibility of detection of the orphan afterglow from the off-axis scenario. (Credits: Author)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of  AT2021any, we performed a detailed broadband afterglow modelling (see Fig. 4a) and confirmed that AT2021any is observed on-axis (see Fig. 4b), and a gamma-ray counterpart was missed by GRBs satellites. We expect to detect more similar sources in the current era of survey telescopes with large fields of view like ZTF and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/grb_dot_rahul_gupta/image4a.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4a: Broadband afterglow light curve and modelling of AT2021any. (Credits: Author)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/grb_dot_rahul_gupta/image4b.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4b: A schematic diagram for the possible explanation of the orphan nature of AT2021any/ZTF21aaeyldq. (Credits: Author)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our results emphasize that the 3.6m DOT has a unique capability for deep follow-up observations of similar and other new transients for deeper observations as a part of time-domain astronomy in the future. GRBs are multiwavelength phenomena. Therefore, along with optical/near-infrared observations using 3.6m DOT, the follow-up observations at other wavelengths using Indian facilities, such as at radio wavelength using Giant Meter Radio Telescope (GMRT) and at UV/X-ray by Indian Space Observatory (AstroSat), may provide a comprehensive picture of these sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12036-021-09794-4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Revealing nature of GRB 210205A, ZTF21aaeyldq (AT2021any) and follow-up observations with the 4K×4K CCD imager + 3.6m DOT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Rahul Gupta&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Amit Kumar, Shashi Bhushan Pandey, A. J. Castro-Tirado, Ankur Ghosh, Dimple, Y.-D. Hu, E. Fernández-García, M. D. Caballero-García, M. Á. Castro-Tirado, R. P. Hedrosa, I. Hermelo, I. Vico, Kuntal Misra, Brajesh Kumar, Amar Aryan, Sugriva Nath Tiwari&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Manora Peak, Nainital-263002, India and Department of Physics, Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Gorakhpur University, Gorakhpur-273009, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/grb_dot_rahul_gupta</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/grb_dot_rahul_gupta</guid>
        
        <category>gamma-ray burst</category>
        
        <category>GRB</category>
        
        <category>GRB 210205A</category>
        
        <category>AT2021any</category>
        
        <category>ZTF21aaeyldq</category>
        
        <category>Devasthal Optical Telescope</category>
        
        <category>DOT</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evolution of plasma parameters during B class flares</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In this article, we presented the temporal evolution of elemental abundances during solar flares of GOES B1−B4 class, the weakest events for which such studies have been possible so far, using observations with XSM on board Chandrayaan-2. This study was possible due to the extremely quiet solar conditions currently prevailing along with the availability of appropriate instrumentation. By modeling the soft X-ray spectra obtained with the XSM during different phases of these flares, measurements of temperature, emission measure, and abundances of Mg, Al, Si, and S were obtained. We have shown that the abundances of these elements are nearly photospheric during the peak phase, compared to their 3–4 times higher preflare values. Beyond the flare peak, the abundances are seen to get enriched again and they recover back to the coronal values at the end of the flare. This suggests that during the flares, the coronal loops are quickly filled with plasma originating from the lower parts of the solar atmosphere without having sufficient time for the usually observed fractionation in nonflaring loops to take place. Our observation of the quick recovery to the coronal values shows that any process giving rise to such fraction must be occurring on a timescale of a few tens of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun’s atmosphere is made up of several layers, primarily the photosphere, the chromosphere, and the corona. The lowest layer is the Photosphere. The temperature of the photosphere is around 5500 degrees, whereas the temperature increases towards the outer layer of the atmosphere and exceed a million degrees at the outermost layer, the corona. The physical mechanism of heating the solar corona to such a high temperature has been a mystery for the last several decades. The current understanding suggests that the magnetic field associated with the Sun is responsible for such high temperatures at corona. The Sun’s magnetic fields are highly dynamic in space and time. Many regions on the Sun are found to have enhanced and concentrated magnetic fields, which are generally known as Active Regions (AR) at the corona. Occasionally sudden bursts of energy are found to release from the AR, known as solar flares. Though solar flares are very commonly seen within the AR, they are also found to occur outside the AR with a small amount of energy release. The modern &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spaceweather.com/glossary/flareclasses.html&quot;&gt;classification&lt;/a&gt; system for solar flares uses the letters A, B, C, M, or X, according to the peak flux in watts per square meter (W/m2) of soft X-rays with wavelengths 1 to 8 Angstrom, as measured at the Earth. The figure below shows the different types of solar flares observed by the geosynchronous equatorial satellites (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swpc.noaa.gov/products/goes-x-ray-flux&quot;&gt;GOES&lt;/a&gt;). X-class flares are the biggest flares seen in the solar atmosphere with a peak flux of &amp;gt; 10-4 W/m2, whereas the M, C, B, and, A-class flares are smaller and smaller flares having peak fluxes 10-5-10-4  W/m2, 10-6-10-5  W/m2, 10-7-10-6  W/m2, and &amp;lt; 10-7 W/m2 respectively (Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/biswajit_bclass_flares_images/biswajit_image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: Soft X-ray flux from GOES satellites.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swpc.noaa.gov/products/goes-x-ray-flux&quot;&gt;NOAA GOES X-ray flux&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the high temperature, the elements (H, He, Fe, O, Ni, Mg, Si, etc) present in the solar atmosphere are found to be ionized to their different ionization levels at different atmospheric layers depending on the temperature. As the origin of the plasma remains the same throughout the solar atmosphere, it is expected that the relative composition or so-called abundances of these elements remains the same throughout the solar atmosphere. However, the observational studies showed that the abundances of certain elements whose ‘First Ionization Potential’ (FIP; which is the minimum energy required to remove the most loosely bound electron from a neutral atom) is lower than 10eV are 2-4 times more abundant in the AR than their photospheric values. This phenomenon is known as the FIP effect. Figure 2 represents a pictorial view of the FIP effect. The x-axis represents the first ionization potential of the elements, whereas the y-axis represents the elements’ abundance ratio (called FIP bias) at the corona and photosphere. All the elements (e.g., Na, Fe, Ni, etc.) with a first ionization potential less than 10 eV have FIP-bias of 2-4, representing they are 2-4 times more in the amount present in the corona than in the photosphere. The FIP bias for the elements having first-ionization-potential more than 10 eV (e.g., Ar, Ne, etc.)  are close to one representing their composition in both photosphere and corona remain the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/biswajit_bclass_flares_images/biswajit_image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Plot of FIP bias versus FIP 
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1992PhyS...46..202F/abstract&quot;&gt;U. Feldman et al. 1992&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the true origin of the FIP effect is not well known, the present understanding of the FIP effect is based on the upward reflection of the magnetic waves, known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfvén_wave&quot;&gt;Alfvén wave&lt;/a&gt;, at the top of the chromospheric layer.
The cartoon below (Figure 3) represents the process briefly. Here we considered a magnetic-field loop rooted in the lower atmosphere and expanded to the corona. The red arrow represents the increase of temperature with a height from the lower atmosphere. Due to the perturbation of the magnetic fields, Alfvén waves will be present inside the loop and can travel throughout it (as shown by the black arrows inside the loop). As the waves travel from upward to downward, they can reflect from the top of the chromosphere (as shown by the black arrows).  Due to the reflection of the waves, an upward force known as “Ponderomotive force” is experienced by the ions (as indicated by the magenta arrow) present in that layer (see Laming (2015)  for details). The ions influenced by the Ponderomotive force travel to the corona and increase their concentration to the corona. The temperature and pressure at the top of the chromosphere are such that only the elements having FIP less than 10 eV can ionize, whereas the high FIP elements remain neutrals, resulting in only the ions of low FIP elements present at the top of the chromosphere to be influenced by the Ponderomotive force, thereby increasing their concentration in the corona.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/biswajit_bclass_flares_images/biswajit_image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Schematical diagram of the Ponderomotive force model.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1110.4357.pdf&quot;&gt;Laming et al. 2012&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the present understanding of the FIP effect is based on the reflection of the  Alfven waves generated due to the perturbation of the magnetic field lines. These Alfven waves are related to the mechanism that heats the solar corona. Recently, it has been believed that the FIP effect is the bi-product of the coronal heating mechanism. Thus measuring the abundances and hence the FIP bias can be a tracer to understanding the origin of the FIP effect as well as the coronal heating mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FIP effect has been studied extensively in quiescent AR closed-loops and during the peak of big solar flares. During the peak of the big flares, a low FIP bias has been found compared with the closed-loop ARs.  However, the detailed picture of the FIP effect during the flare is not clear as the time evolution study of elemental abundances during the solar flare was limited due to technical limitations of the present generation instrument (e.g., sensitivity: lowest flux that an instrument can detect, instrument’s energy resolution: the capability of an instrument to distinguish the emission lines present at nearby energies, cadence: time gap between two successive observations, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, the elements’ absolute (i.e.,  relative to the H) abundances are measured using the spectroscopic technique. A recent instrument, Solar X-ray Monitor (XSM) onboard the Chandrayaan-2 spacecraft, provides the spectrum of the Sun every second in the broad energy range of 1-15 keV. Its good spectral resolution and sensitivity have been useful for time-resolved spectroscopy. In time-resolved spectroscopy, the instrument provides the spectrum of the detected photons at each time step, and then analyzing each spectrum corresponding to a time step, we extract the characteristics of the incident photons on the detector. One can study the abundance evolution during solar flares using such a technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the period from 2019 September to 2020 May, covering the minimum of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solar_cycle&quot;&gt;Solar Cycle&lt;/a&gt; 24, XSM observed nine B-class flares ranging from B1.3 to B4.5. The observed XSM light curve (blue color) for one of the flares is shown in Figure 4a. Light curves of the same flare as observed by the other instruments (non-spectroscopic) are also shown by gray and brown colors. For the time-resolved spectroscopy, we used the XSM observed spectra at different time intervals throughout the flares, as shown by the green and orange shaded background colors. Representative XSM spectra for three different durations as marked by the “1”, “2”, and “3” are shown in Figure 4b. All the line complexes observed in the XSM spectra are annotated in the plot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/biswajit_bclass_flares_images/biswajit_image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: Spectroscopic analysis from Chandrayaan-2 XSM.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.07825&quot;&gt;B.Mondal et al. 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analyzing the spectrum of each of the shaded duration as marked by green and orange color in Figure 4a, we estimate the temperature, emission measure (EM; which is a quantity to quantify how much emission is coming from the source at a particular temperature), and absolute elemental abundances of four elements–Mg, Al, Si, and S throughout the flares. These are the first measurements of abundances during such small flares, and this study offers a unique insight into the evolution of abundances as the flares evolve. The results are shown in Figure 5. The flare light curve is plotted in a grey curve. Panels ‘a’ and ‘b’ (black and red color represent the results obtained from two different methods of spectral analysis; for detail, see the reference paper) show the evolution of the temperature and EM during the flare. In the impulsive phase of the flares, due to the sudden release of the energy, both temperature and EM increase as flares evolve. After the peak of the flare, the flaring plasma starts to cool down and reach the background plasma temperature at the end of the flare, as shown by the blue horizontal line.  The abundances of the Magnesium (black and red points in panels c) decrease toward their photospheric values (shown by the green horizontal band) during the impulsive phase of the flares. During the decay phase, the abundances are observed to quickly return to their pre-flare coronal values (shown by colored horizontal dashed lines as reported by several authors). A similar evolution of the abundances of other elements (Al, Si, and S) are also observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/biswajit_bclass_flares_images/biswajit_image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 5: Representative results of temperature, emission measure and Mg abundance for one B-class flare.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.07825&quot;&gt;B.Mondal et al. 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decay of the abundances (or FIP bias) during the impulsive phase of the flares can be explained by invoking the process of chromospheric evaporation, the process in which the photospheric materials come up to the corona. However, the quick recovery (in a few minutes time scale)  of the abundances from near photospheric to coronal values in the decay phase of the flare can not be explained by the present theory of the FIP effect alone, where to develop the FIP bias a time scale of 1-2 days is required. There are two possible scenarios that can explain our observation, as described in Figure 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/biswajit_bclass_flares_images/biswajit_image6.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 6: Models to explain the observed FIP bias and its evolution.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.07825&quot;&gt;B.Mondal et al. 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first scenario, Figure-6; (1a) Impulsive phase–After the flare onset (at time t0), heat energy travels down to the chromosphere and evaporates the plasma there. The process of evaporating the plasma from the chromosphere is called chromospheric evaporation. The temperature peak is identified at the start (time t1) of the chromospheric evaporation. During the initial phase, plasma evaporates with high velocity and quickly passes through the fractionation layer (top of the chromosphere, where the reflection of the downward propagating Alfvén waves occurs and the ions are separated due to the Ponderomotive force) without getting fractionated, resulting in depletion of the coronal FIP bias. The EM peak is achieved (time t2 ) once the loop gets filled with the chromospheric plasma. At around the same time, the abundances of the low-FIP elements also attain their minima. (1b) Decay phase–The speed of the evaporative up-flow slows down significantly, allowing plasma enough time in the fractionation layer to get fractionated. The fractionated plasma eventually fills the coronal part of the loop, thereby demonstrating the recovery of the coronal FIP bias. (1c) Representative temperature, EM, and elemental abundance evolution curves. Time t4 marks the time of complete recovery of the coronal FIP bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second scenario, Figure-6; (2a), At the time of the flare onset (time t0 ), high amplitude Alfvén waves are initiated. The released heat energy gets transported to the chromosphere by suprathermal electrons (high energetic electrons), at speeds faster than those of the Alfvén waves. Evaporation starts at time t1 and reduces the coronal FIP bias. The temperature peak is observed around this time. (2b) The EM peak and abundance minima are achieved when the loop is filled with the evaporated plasma (t2). Once the flare-driven Alfvén waves arrive at the chromosphere (time t3 ), they rapidly fractionate the plasma. These Alfvén waves also carry significant heat from the flaring site to assist the evaporation. The fractionated plasma is then transported to the coronal part of the loop through evaporative upflows, which help in rapidly recovering the coronal FIP bias. (2c) Representative curves of temperature, EM, and elemental abundances for the second scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier studies during the peak of the big flares (X or M) found photospheric abundances, but how the abundances became photospheric was not very clear. A time-resolved spectroscopic observation with a good resolution was essential to study the problem in detail. Here using the recent X-ray spectrometer, XSM onboard Chandrayaan 2 orbiter, we did time-resolved spectroscopy during the B-class flares and showed the complete evolution of the abundances during the flares.  The results suggest that the coronal loops are quickly filled with plasma originating from the lower parts of the solar atmosphere during the flares. During the decay phase of the flares, the abundances reach their 3-4 times higher pre-flare values within a few tens of minutes. These results will help us to understand the origin of FIP bias during flares and provide constraints to develop the model of the FIP theory. This study suggests that measuring the abundances during the flares is an important tool to get insight into the flaring process. The B-class flares are much smaller than the large X or M-class flares. Thus it is expected that even smaller class flares could show a similar variation of the abundances during the flares. Studying smaller flares is of great interest in the entire solar physics community as it is believed that the smaller flares occur very frequently and heat the solar corona to million degrees. In follow-up work, we will study several much smaller A-class flares and compare the results with the present study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac14c1 target=_blank&quot;&gt; Evolution of Elemental Abundances during B-Class Solar Flares: Soft X-Ray Spectral Measurements with Chandrayaan-2 XSM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Biswajit Mondal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Aveek Sarkar, Santosh V. Vadawale, N. P. S. Mithun, P. Janardhan, Giulio Del Zanna, Helen E. Mason, Urmila Mitra-Kraev, S. Narendranath&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Physical Research Laboratory, Navrangpura, Ahmedabad, Gujarat-380 009, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;p&gt;202&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/biswajit_bclass_flares_fip</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/biswajit_bclass_flares_fip</guid>
        
        <category>FIP effect</category>
        
        <category>FIP bias</category>
        
        <category>solar flares</category>
        
        <category>abundance</category>
        
        <category>XSM</category>
        
        <category>X-ray spectroscopy</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>General Relativity And Its Effect On A Deformed And Misaligned Pulsar</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Observed pulsars are misaligned in nature. The misalignment scenario occurs when the rotation axis and the magnetic axis of the star forms a finite non-zero angle between them. This scenario gives rise to very interesting phenomenons. This article explores such a misaligned star which is oblate in nature due to the deformations of rotation would vary considering general relativistic corrections. Our calculations show some interesting features regarding the magnetic field, power loss and also the charge separation on the surface of such a star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neutron Stars (NSs) are very dense objects found in the universe, having masses ranging from about 1.4  MΘ ( MΘ  is the Solar mass) to about 2.2 MΘ . NS are the highly dense collapsed core of a a star of mass 8 MΘ  to 20 MΘ formed after a supernova explosion. The central density at the core of the NS is about few times that of the nuclear saturation density. The predictions of Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) state that at such high densities, nuclear matter won’t be the stable state and the quarks present inside the nucleons will get deconfined resulting in a stable quark matter. Until now, there are no earth-based experiments that can probe such densities nor any reliable theoretical calculation. Therefore the only laboratory to test the theory of deconfinement at high density is at the core of the NS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very fast spinning NSs are also known as pulsars. Observed pulsars have a dipolar magnetic field with its magnetic moment directed along an axis known as the magnetic axis. The pulsars rotate about an axis called the rotation axis. These two axes are not directed in the same direction (they have some finite angle between them), and such pulsars are known as misaligned pulsars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/general_relativity_pulsar_sagnik_images/vel2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1 here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
A schematic diagram of a misaligned pulsar. The cyan-coloured spherical object is the pulsar which rotates about the rotation axis (blue axis), and the magnetic moment is pointed along the magnetic axis (red axis). The charged particles move with a velocity (v) as shown in the figure. The black lines show the closed magnetic field lines of the star. Image courtesy: author. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our recent publication, we have tried to provide a realistic model for such a pulsar. For simplicity of calculations, people tend to assume the star is aligned (the magnetic axis and the rotation axis coincide). Still, in reality, the pulsars found in the universe are misaligned. We have also considered the deformation due to the star’s rotation about its axis to provide a more accurate model. Thus our star tends to form an oblate shape, which adds an extra challenge to our calculations since we cannot assume the star to be spherically symmetric, which would have simplified our calculations. The general theory of relativity, given by Einstein in 1915, shows that heavy objects tend to curve the space-time. Since NSs are more massive than our sun, we need to consider these general relativistic effects to have the most accurate model possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work done by me, along with my supervisor Dr.Ritam Mallick, and my collaborator Dr.Debojoti Kuzur, shows some interesting results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our calculations show that along the star’s equator, the strength of the magnetic field reduces with an increase in the misalignment of the star. As there are no direct means to measure the misalignment angle, our calculations conclude that a pulsar which has lesser magnetic field near the equatorial plane compared to another pulsar having a higher magnetic field near the equator can be said to be more misaligned than the later. The pulsar will also lose its energy due to its rotation. We also studied how the general relativistic calculations differ from the known Newtonian approach of finding the power loss of the star. We see that with an increase in the misalignment angle of the star, the power loss increases, to a certain angle, after which it takes a sharp dip and rises again. As the star rotates about its axis with extremely high angular velocity, the charges near the star’s surface would separate as a result. This would result in the accumulation of the negatively charged particles called electrons near the poles of the star-forming dome kind of shape, and the positrons will accumulate near the equator of the star, forming a torus. The charge density near the star’s surface for such a scenario is called the  &lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1969ApJ...157..869G/abstract&quot;&gt; Goldreich-Julian &lt;/a&gt; charge density of the star. We also calculated the Goldreich-Julian charged density for our model and compared it with the known model for the Newtonian case. Our results report changes from the known nature of the charge density distribution from the previous values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/general_relativity_pulsar_sagnik_images/GW_Newt.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1 here&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/general_relativity_pulsar_sagnik_images/freq_557_new4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image 1 here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;

 &lt;b&gt; Top: &lt;/b&gt; Figure shows the comparison of the Goldreich-Julian density for the Newtonian and the general relativistic case, the x-axis denotes the polar angle &amp;theta; and the y-axis denotes the charge density in cm&lt;sup&gt;-2&lt;/sup&gt;. As we increase the angle &amp;theta;, i.e. we move from the star&apos;s pole towards the star&apos;s equator, we see a change in the sign of the charge densities. At the pole of the star, we see more electrons (negative charges), and as we move towards the equator, we see more positrons (positive charges).	&lt;b&gt; Bottom:&lt;/b&gt; The plot shows the comparison of the power loss for the deformed pulsar for different values of misalignment angle &amp;chi;. The yellow line shows the results obtained from the general relativistic plot. The green coloured line shows the power loss for known Newtonian methods.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find a complete description of our calculations and explanations in the original paper linked below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jheap.2022.03.002&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; General relativistic calculation of magnetic field and power loss for a misaligned pulsar.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Sagnik Chatterjee&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ritam Mallick and DebojotiKuzur&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Science Education and Research Bhopal, Bhopal, Bhopal, Madhya Pradesh, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/general_relativity_effect_deformed_pulsar_sagnik</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/general_relativity_effect_deformed_pulsar_sagnik</guid>
        
        <category>Neutron Stars</category>
        
        <category>Pulsars</category>
        
        
        <category>High Energy Astrophysical Phenomena</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The International Moon Day</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;On account of International Moon Day, we present a brief overview of the formation scenarios of the Moon. We also discuss the findings of Chandrayaan.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thats-one-small-step-for-man-one-giant-leap-for-mankind&quot;&gt;“That’s one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind.”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the famous quote by Neil Armstrong during the live broadcast when he stepped on the Moon for the first time on 20 July 1969. The Apollo-11 mission was regarded as the biggest technological achievement by NASA. Armstrong and Aldrin had spent around 21 hours at a location known as Tranquility Base on the lunar surface collecting lunar samples. After spending more than eight days in space, the group returned to the planet and touched down in the Pacific Ocean on July 24. To celebrate this great feat, the United Nations marked the 20th July of every year to be celebrated as “International Lunar Day” in its resolution 76/76 on ‘International cooperation in the peaceful uses of outer space’ in 2021. To mark this day, in this article, we provide the current understanding of the formation of the most familiar astronomical object we see in the sky, the Moon and the Indian lunar missions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moon has been an important part of the history of mankind, be it popular literature, religion or navigation. Scientific observations of the Moon date back to the 1600s, when Galileo Galilei turned his telescope towards the Moon to reveal its surface. Contrary to the popular belief that the Moon has a smooth surface, a topology abundant with craters and mountains was received with great surprise. Since then, we have had many scientific ventures to understand the Moon in great detail. Luna-2, by the Soviet Union, was the first spacecraft to reach the Moon and Apollo-11 by the United States made the Moon the first astronomical object other than Earth, where mankind had set foot on. Many studies have revealed important aspects of the Moon. Among all that, the most interesting question is about the origin of the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Darwin, in 1879, put forward a hypothesis about the formation of the Moon. He proposed that the Moon was formed from a piece of mass that spun off from a rapidly rotating Earth in its molten phase during planet formation. This hypothesis is called the fission hypothesis (Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ashish_international_moon_day/ashish_fig1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: Distribution of offset between magnetic field direction and clump orientation. 
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://supernova.eso.org/exhibition/images/0208c_moon_formation_fission/&quot;&gt;Moon formation fission&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, the capture hypothesis (Figure 2)  suggested the possibility of capturing of the Moon during a close flyby in Earth’s gravity field. In this scenario, the Moon was believed to be formed elsewhere in the solar system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ashish_international_moon_day/ashish_fig2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Fission hypothesis. 
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.ppt-online.org/909631&quot;&gt;Capture Theory&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A co-accretion model (Figure 3) was suggested alternative to both the stated hypotheses. This model predicted that the Moon and Earth formed at the same location around the sun by accreting the same material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ashish_international_moon_day/ashish_fig3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Capture hypothesis 
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencephoto.com/keyword/co-accretion-theory&quot;&gt;Co-accretion Theory&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, these hypotheses started to break when we started understanding the Moon’s composition and bulk nature after the Apollo missions. The composition of the samples returned by the Apollo astronauts showed that Earth and Moon shared the same isotopic composition. And it was also seen that the Moon’s bulk iron content was less than Earth’s. The three stated hypotheses explaining the Moon’s formation could not explain these results. This led to a new hypothesis called the Giant Impact Hypothesis (Figure 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ashish_international_moon_day/ashish_fig4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: Giant Impact: An artistic impression 
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://astronomy.com/news/2019/05/giant-impact-hypothesis-an-evolving-legacy-of-apollo&quot;&gt;Giant Impact Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1975, William K. Hartmann and Donald R. Davis proposed the Giant Impact Hypothesis. It explained that 4.5 billion years ago, after the Earth was formed and solidified to have a solid crust, it underwent a collision course with a Mars-sized planetesimal object which co-evolved in the neighbourhood of Earth. This impact caused rocks and debris to be collected in orbit around the Earth, and eventually, it accreted to form the Moon. This hypothesis could explain the same isotopic composition of Earth and Moon since both were created from the same material. By the time Earth had formed its solid crust (when the giant impact had happened), the heavier iron element in its composition had sunk to form an iron core of Earth. Hence, the material that was ejected from Earth’s crust and mantle as a result of impact was iron deficient. This explains the iron-poor nature of the Moon. As this impact theory can explain many known facts about the Moon, the Giant Impact hypothesis has been the long-standing theory that explains the origin of the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the global abundance of various elements and minerals on the Lunar surface will help us to validate and model the Giant Impact hypothesis. India’s moon orbiting satellite, Chandrayaan missions has significantly contributed to this direction. Chandrayaan-1 was India’s first mission to the Moon. Moon mineralogy mapper (MMM, also known as M-cube), a payload onboard Chandrayaan-1, detected the trace of water at the poles of the Moon. Another payload, C1XS (Chandrayaan-1 X-ray Spectrometer), could detect major rock-forming elements on the surface and reported the first measurement of enhanced sodium on the lunar surface. Due to the short lifespan of nine months of Chandrayaan-1 around the Moon, a global elemental map remained unachieved until India launched Chandrayaan-2 in 2019. Chandrayaan -2 was an ambitious mission that carried a lander, rover and an orbiter. The Vikram lander was designed to soft-land on the lunar surface, and the rover named Pragyan was made to traverse the lunar surface performing experiments on the surface. But unfortunately, both Vikram and Pragyan hard landed on the Moon, making them unusable. The Orbiter, which carried eight scientific payloads, orbits the Moon giving valuable scientific data since 2019. A global elemental map of various elements is awaited as a major result of Chandrayaan-2. This vital data can shed clues to validate the existing hypothesis for the formation of the Moon. These studies will help us make the biggest leap to understanding the formation scenario of the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgement&quot;&gt;Acknowledgement:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article has been written with the help of Robin Thomas and Shridharan Baskaran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;p&gt;202&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/ashish_international_moon_day</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/ashish_international_moon_day</guid>
        
        <category>Moon</category>
        
        <category>International Moon Day</category>
        
        <category>Chandrayaan</category>
        
        
        <category>Earth and Planetary Astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Clouds’ Motion entangled by Magnetic Fields in Cepheus Flare</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Stars take birth in molecular clouds. The presence of magnetic fields everywhere in the universe naturally creates a curiosity to investigate their role at all the stages of star fomation. The motion of clouds through the interstellar medium in the presence of magnetic fields may get effected and can shed light on the structure/orientation of stellar nurseries.  This short article will explain these possible effects in an interesting region of our Universe, Cepheus Flare.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding how stars are formed is one of the crucial questions in astronomy. Molecular clouds are the blank spaces or voids in between stars in our galaxy, the Milky Way and they consist of predominantly hydrogen or helium molecules. They are stellar nurseries in our local galaxy and the universe. The prestellar/protostellar cores are the high density nested quantities in large molecular clouds with a typical temperatures of 10 K and density of ~ 103 cm&lt;sup&gt;-3&lt;/sup&gt;. They are considered as the fundamental units for the formation of stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/cloud_motion_cepheus_flare_ekta/ekta_fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: Schematic of cloud of radius Rc moving in a uniformly magnetized background medium with a velocity, Vc making an angle θ with the field lines
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1086/307162/pdf&quot;&gt;Miniati et al. 1999&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magnetic fields, which are ubiquitous to the universe, is a very interesting property. Due to their interaction with the ionized material, they can play an important role in the dynamics of the clouds. The angular offsets between the direction of the cloud motion and the magnetic fields, θ is shown in Fig. 1. These offsets can help in preventing the disruption of the cloud (radius Rc moving with velocity Vc) against the Kelvin-Helmholtz instability in the interstellar medium as suggested by simulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/cloud_motion_cepheus_flare_ekta/ekta_fig1.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 1: Schematic of cloud of radius Rc moving in a uniformly magnetized background medium with a velocity, Vc making an angle θ with the field lines
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1086/307162/pdf&quot;&gt;Miniati et al. 1999&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stars which are young are still associated/embedded in the high-density clouds because the surrounding molecular material has not completely collapsed towards the centre. Their motion in the projected plane of the galaxy is defined as proper motion. Stars move in the interstellar medium (ISM) and their proper motion is a critical factor in determining their overall motion in the galaxy.  Proper motion can serve as a proxy of the motion of the clouds in the ISM. A team of researchers led by Dr. Ekta Sharma and Dr. Maheswar Gopinathan from the Indian Institute of Astrophysics, an autonomous institute of the Department of Science &amp;amp; Technology, Govt. of India and Dr. Sami Dib from Niels Bohr Institute, University of Copenhagen, Denmark carried out an observational test on a sample of clouds (L1228, L1251, L1172/1174 and L1147/1158) located at a nearby distance of ~330 pc in Cepheus Flare region identified in Fig. 2. The Gaia (Global Astrometric Interferometer for Astrophysics) and Planck, both are space based observatories to study the motion of stars and the emission in far-infrared wavelengths, respectively. The authors used proper motion data from Gaia Data Release 3 to study the motion of the clouds in sky plane (shown by arrows in Fig. 2) and Planck polarization data to construct magnetic field maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/cloud_motion_cepheus_flare_ekta/ekta_fig2.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 2: Background image in color scale is cloud emission in far-infrared wavelengths obtained by Planck satellite. Blue arrows show the direction of proper motion.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.07510.pdf&quot;&gt;Sharma et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They estimated various offsets between the direction of magnetic field and the motion of the clouds in the sky. The results show that the magnetic fields are ordered in all the clouds except one cloud, L1172/1174 which shows an offset (angle, θ in Fig. 1) higher than 30°. The authors suggest that the higher offset could be responsible for converting the cloud material in the form of hub-filament structure (see Fig. 3). These structures consist of a hub having less aspect ratio with high column density and a number of filaments with high aspect ratio with less column density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/cloud_motion_cepheus_flare_ekta/ekta_fig3.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 3: Schematics of Hub-filament systems.
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.00295.pdf&quot;&gt;Kumar et al., 2020&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starless cores are the earlier stages in the process of star formation which have not formed stars and the pretsellar cores are the ones which are on the verge of making stars. We made a quantitative analysis of the core orientations (direction of major axes) (in Fig. 4) with respect to the magnetic field in case of starless as well as the prestellar cores. The distribution for all the clouds is found to be random. The study concluded that the core dynamics could be affected more by the local variations in the magnetic field in the cloud’s environment. The results of this study have been published in the journal “Astronomy &amp;amp; Astrophysics”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/cloud_motion_cepheus_flare_ekta/ekta_fig4.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Figure 4: Distribution of offset between magnetic field direction and clump orientation. 
Credit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.07510.pdf&quot;&gt;Sharma et al., 2021&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aanda.org/articles/aa/abs/2022/02/aa40495-21/aa40495-21.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Cloud motion and magnetic fields: Four clouds in the Cepheus Flare region&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Ekta Sharma&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; G. Maheswar and S. Dib&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA), Sarjapur Road, Koramangala, Bangalore 560034, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page&apos;s canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page&apos;s unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON&apos;T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement(&apos;script&apos;);
    s.src = &apos;https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js&apos;;
    s.setAttribute(&apos;data-timestamp&apos;, +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/cloud_motion_cepheus_flare_ekta</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/cloud_motion_cepheus_flare_ekta</guid>
        
        <category>polarization; clouds; ISM; proper motion; GAIA</category>
        
        
        <category>Astrophysics of Galaxies</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
