<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> Welcome to CosmicVarta.</title>
    <description> Platform for promoting Indian astronomy research to the public.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 22:55:52 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 22:55:52 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Understanding the solar chromosphere through spectral lines</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This article takes the reader through a journey of inferring the cosmos - specifically our dear neighbour Sun - through various properties of light. The journey meanders through our work on understanding solar chromospheric properties through spectral lines, and seems to cluminate in the sea of questions raised by our work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light is one of the most fundamental, complex and inherently mind blowing things to exist in this world. Every culture across the globe attributes (or attributed) great significance to light, while adding multiple layers of symbolism and meaning. Light has its influence right from the chloroplasts in plants converting water &amp;amp; nutrients to sugar and Oxygen, to the largest of solar panels to generate electricity for entire cities. Light is, in some sense, our window to this world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is true for astronomers. Imagine an astronomer working  - I am pretty sure your immediate thought is a person looking through a telescope in the night sky. Well, you are pretty correct - in that most information about the universe comes to us through light! But light is not just what we “see”: the radio frequency on which mobile phones operate is light, and so are the X-rays which are used to check for bone fractures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What kind of light exists depends on how it is generated in the first place. The simplest way to make light is to get objects hot. A hot iron rod glows red, while an arc welding plasma glows blue. Heat, and temperature are primary drivers of what kind of light comes out. This “colour” of light is given by the wavelength (or the frequency) of light. The larger this frequency of light, smaller the wavelength is, and more the energy in light. X rays have a very short wavelength (and so high energy), while Radio waves have a very long wavelength (and low energy). Similarly, red light has a larger wavelength than blue (or violet) light. So, in general, hotter objects have more energy, and hence emit more in short wavelengths, while cooler objects have lesser energy, and emit more in longer wavelengths. This is the reason why X-rays are generally much more harmful than Radio waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun we see every day is obviously a hot object. So logically, we also expect it to give light corresponding to how hot it is. And this is quite true – the solar “surface” or the solar disc we see in the sky is at 5500 Kelvin. Hence, it emits most of its energy near greenish-yellow light. But all parts of the Sun do not preferentially emit this greenish-yellow light – rather, depending on the temperature, different parts of the Sun emit in different colours. In Fig. 1 below, I have displayed the same region of the Sun as seen in different wavelengths. The hottest plasma is seen in the 94 Å image, while the coolest is seen in the 2796 Å image - with temperature (approximately) reducing with increasing wavelength. Each structure contains material at different temperatures - this is because different structures form at different heights! A general
rule of thumb in the solar atmosphere is “hotter stuff forms at greater height than cooler stuff”, so the S shaped loop in the 94 Å image forms much higher than the structure in the 2796 Å image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just one aspect of the light that comes to us. The other aspect is that the material which emits this light, also leaves an imprint on “how bright” the light is at different wavelengths. This is slightly different from the Thermal radiation, which depends only on the temperature. The typical brightness at every wavelength for light coming due to an object being hot, looks somewhat like the top row in Fig. 2. Here, notice that the brightness shows some variation with wavelength (which, I remind you, is given by the colour of light) - but the essential point is that every wavelength has some amount of brightness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, check out the second row - corresponding to a Sodium atom. You will see that the brightness is present at &lt;strong&gt;discrete&lt;/strong&gt; locations in wavelength, and most of the wavelengths have no brightness. This is in stark contrast to the thermal radiation, and is followed similarly by all other elements listed in the rows below Sodium. But note that the pattern, or location &amp;amp; brightness of these &lt;strong&gt;spectral lines&lt;/strong&gt; of different elements is unique for each element. In a sense, spectral lines can be thought of as a fingerprint of atoms and molecules. Just like each human has a unique set of fingerprints, similarly each atom or molecule has a specific set of spectral lines as its signature. These lines you see are bright in specific wavelengths, and are called &lt;strong&gt;emission lines&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomers study the spectral lines of different objects like stars, galaxies, etc, and try to figure out which all atoms, ions and molecules are present in the object of study. Remember, what I have shown in Fig. 2 is the light coming from one vertical slit - that is why, the spectral lines are all seen as vertical lines. But this need not be the case - I can also look at approximately one point on the Sun (or even average over the vertical line), for example, and get its spectrum out. This exercise will give us a result similar to Fig. 3, where we just have the brightness of light for every wavelength. This is the kind of spectrum astronomers generally analyze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A side note here: The spectrum shown Fig. 3 is the brightness (or rather the intensity) for every wavelength. We can then construct a similar spectrum for a large region of the Sun, and obtain such spectra for each point. Now, if we consider the intensity at, let’s say 2796 Å for each point, we will get an image similar to the last panel in Fig. 1. How cool is that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will now have many questions: why is the spectrum of individual elements only at specific wavelengths, and not everywhere? What conditions give rise to the “brightness” of these lines? First off, you find the spectrum of elements at discrete wavelength locations because these arise from atomic transitions between two approximately fixed energy levels. The “quantum” of Quantum mechanics gives rise to this discrete nature. Next, the spectrum itself depends on, among other parameters, 4 critical properties: the temperature of the region where the spectrum is generated, density of the material giving rise to the spectrum, velocity of this material, and turbulence. These properties, under certain circumstances, can be easily inferred from just the spectrum of an atom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, note that the material which emits this light is a fluid (more precisely, plasma) in our case. Hence, the temperature and density of the plasma determine if a given spectral line will even form. So just knowing the fact that a given line is seen tells us the possible range of values temperature and quantity can take. Next, the brightness of the line is in most cases dominated by the density of plasma – more density, more brightness, but you do have the  effect of atomic physics and temperature. Third, the wavelength where we expect the line brightness to peak can be shifted to different wavelengths too! This is called Doppler shift. If the plasma is moving towards us, the shift is toward shorter wavelengths (called Blueshift), and if the plasma is moving away from us, the shift is toward longer wavelengths (called Redshifts).  Finally, if you see in Fig. 3, the line does not immediately peak at one wavelength. Rather, it starts to increase from one wavelength, reaches a maximum, and then reduces. This is called the line width, and is determined by the temperature, and turbulence in the plasma. Turbulence basically is a measure of how much fluctuation of different spatial sizes is present in the fluid - it is yet another measure of what the plasma we consider is like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So tl;dr in summary, using spectral lines, we can get an estimate of local temperature, velocity, density and turbulence of these plasma parcels through spectral lines. So what is the big idea?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big idea is that some specific regions on the Sun are thought to give rise to a stream of particles called the solar wind. We know that these regions are important, but we don’t know at what height the solar wind starts to form. Now, the solar wind is basically a stream of particles coming out of the Sun. So if you are looking “down” on the Sun, you will see that the particles are coming towards you. This means the spectral line which the particles emit will be blueshifted. So the basic idea is that we study these Doppler shifts for plasma which correspond to different wavelengths (and so different heights and temperatures, like Fig. 1), and see where the blueshifts start!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, these regions, which are thought to give rise to the solar wind, are called “Coronal holes” (CHs) - because they are seen as dark patches in the solar corona. In Fig. 4b below, all dark regions belong to CHs, while the brighter regions belong to “Quiet Sun” (QS). These regions appear very different in the solar corona. However, if we check what these regions look like at lower heights called the chromosphere, the differences are reduced (see Fig. 4a)! Why so? Has this “vanishing” of difference got anything to do with the solar wind? Can we do specific studies of these regions, and figure out what causes these differences? Are they dependent on the underlying magnetic field in any way? This was our primary objective of study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this juncture, I should tell you that scientists have done extensive studies of the CHs and QS regions in the corona, and all of the information I have presented in the last two or so paragraphs was generated in the last three decades. So we do stand on the shoulders of other giants – while we do bring our own thought process to the table!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to our work: we studied one spectral line (yep, just one line, and you will see how much information we can infer from it!), and its properties across both the CHs and QS regions. This line forms due to a transition of the C+ ion (called CII by astrophysicists) at a wavelength of 1334 Å. How do we know the correct wavelength? We can perform controlled experiments in labs on Earth and figure it out. Now, you have already seen how there is not a great difference between CH and QS in the intensity image of Fig. 4a. Similar results hold if we look at what the plasma velocity and line width are in Fig. 5. This tells us that if I were to not tell you where the CH and QS regions are, you cannot figure them out from either the intensity, velocity, or the width of the C II line. Thus, on a gross scale, the CH and QS are very similar!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting things happen if we account for the underlying magnetic field. How do we do this? We ask: what is the intensity in CH and QS at similar magnetic field strengths? Similarly, what are the velocities and line widths? The underlying magnetic field strength might be similar, but the structure of the magnetic field can be different! The structure of magnetic field (a.k.a magnetic topology) is important, because we know that the CHs are regions where the magnetic field comes out predominantly in open lines, while in QS the same magnetic field comes as short closed loops. These differences are seen clearly in the corona – but are they also seen in the chromosphere?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out it is the case! We can indeed differentiate between CH and QS if we consider regions with similar magnetic field strength. In Fig. 6, the black dots correspond to the average of quantity in Y-axis (Intensity, velocity, width) for regions with similar magnetic field strength (in X-axis). On an average, you see that the QS intensity is larger than the CH intensity in Fig. 6a – reminiscent of the differences in the corona, and seen statistically here. So one question is answered: CHs and QS are already differentiated in the chromosphere, but you can see this only statistically!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, look at panel b of the same figure. The velocity is mostly positive - indicating plasma moving away from us, and down towards the photosphere. Thus, the chromosphere is, on average, flowing downwards into the Sun. However, it is interesting to see that at 40 Gauss, a switchover occurs: for less field strength, the QS has plasma flowing down faster, while it is CH for larger field strength. This is counter intuitive – if the solar wind comes out and towards us in the CH, why is plasma moving away from us in CH?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, see panel c of the same figure. The line width is seen to increase with field strength. This tells us that the profiles are getting broader, possibly implying larger turbulence with increasing field strength. Here too, CHs are broader than QS for large field strengths!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things don’t stop here. The velocity panel in Fig. 6b raises many questions. And so, we repeat the analysis with a tweak - this time, we consider the blueshifts and redshifts separately. Why so? This is important to understand if the field strength has preferentially some effect on the blueshifts and redshifts, which get averaged out in Fig. 6b. And so, we check what the speeds look like in Fig.7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In panel a of Fig. 7, the CHs have larger blueshifts over QS, telling us plasma is indeed preferentially moving towards us in the CHs. Thus, in principle, these blueshifts could be a signature of the solar wind. Now we are in business!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In panel b, we check what the downflows look like. It seems for regions with large field strength, plasma is flowing into the Sun faster in CHs over QS. This was the signature which confused us in Fig. 6b. Why does the CH, which is understood to be a source of particles coming out towards the Earth, have particles going into the Sun, and away from the Earth preferentially? Are we doing something wrong? Or are the spectral profiles, and thus the process which generates these lines different in CHs and QS?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out it is not the case. I will not show the plot here (already there is an overdose of information – too much of a good thing is also not good! :P), but we find that the spectral profiles are very similar in both CH and QS. Thus, it tells us that the processes which give rise to these profiles are similar in both the regions – the differences are coming out only because of the differences in the magnetic field topology of CHs and QS!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, through this work we find that the CHs and QS might appear similar overall, but the differentiation in chromosphere is seen clearly if we consider regions with similar magnetic field strength. This differentiation is seen clearly as less intensity and excess line width in CHs over QS. The differentiation is clearly seen to arise primarily due to the magnetic field topology, and not due to fundamental differences in the way these lines form. However, our work poses a bunch of fundamental questions: Why is plasma flowing faster away from us in CHs over QS, when these CHs are supposed to be the sources of solar wind? Does this “redshift” bear any relation to the solar wind? How do these results tie up with analysis done for lines which form at higher temperatures (and hence, in the transition region &amp;amp; corona), and lower temperatures (lower &amp;amp; mid chromosphere)? And do the blueshifts we find in Fig. 7b have any relation with the solar wind?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To know more, and understand what happens next, keep watching this space!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.04287&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Properties of the C II 1334 Å line in Coronal Hole and Quiet Sun as observed by IRIS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Vishal Upendran&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Durgesh Tripathi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Inter University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics, Pune, 411007, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/solar-chromosphere-spectral-lines</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/solar-chromosphere-spectral-lines</guid>
        
        <category>Solar chromosphere</category>
        
        <category>solar wind</category>
        
        <category>spectral lines</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>POLARIZATION OF THE LIGHT REFLECTED FROM EXOPLANETS: A NEW WINDOW INTO THE STUDY OF EXOPLANETS </title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Polarization is an emerging technique in the filed of exoplanets. Understanding the basic physics behind the polarization of the light observed from the planets can help us study them in detail. One such aspect is to study the polarization of the reflection from the exoplanets which can tell us about their atmospheres, especially, the clouds present in them and also, the surface features. Several big-budget missions are being planned for polarimetric observation of the exoplanets. Theoretical simulation and modeling of planetary polarization plays an important role in this regard as they help us decide the targets as well as prepare the roadmaps for those missions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the discovery of thousands of exoplanets, the scientists are on a desperate quest to arrive at new direct and indirect techniques to get a complete picture about the formation, dynamics and the atmospheres of the exoplanets. In that regard, polarimetric techniques have opened a new window into the study of the exoplanets by overcoming many of the limitations of the traditional techniques.
Light is a wave of electric and magnetic fields. These waves oscillate at random direction perpendicular to the propagation of light. When light gets scattered by atoms, molecules or cloud particulates in the atmosphere or reflected by a surface, the waves oscillate in a particular direction. Then the light is called to be linearly polarized. An instrument called a polarimeter can measure the amount of polarization as it allows light waves oscillating only in a particular direction to pass. For example, if we watch the sky by using polarized sunglasses, we can see a change in the brightness of the sky in different directions. This is because of the fact that sunlight gets polarized due to scattering by the molecules and the dust particles in the atmosphere. Similarly when planets reflect the light of the parent star, that light gets polarized. As a consequence, the reflected light of all the planets in the Solar system is polarized. So, we can leverage this property of light to study the reflecting exoplanets as well.
Detecting light reflected from the exoplanets is difficult as the reflected light is feeble compared to the starlight itself and on top of that, only a small fraction of that reflected light is polarized. Moreover, in the case of planets that cannot be resolved from their host stars, the light from the host star contaminates the planetary light and the observable polarization in such a case can be as low as a few parts per million (10-6 order). As a result, detecting this polarization is extremely challenging. However, there are a few high-end instruments such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://newt.phys.unsw.edu.au/~jbailey/hippi.html&quot;&gt;HIPPI&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://newt.phys.unsw.edu.au/~jbailey/planets/polarimeter.html&quot;&gt;PlanetPol&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1086/595966&quot;&gt;POLISH&lt;/a&gt;, among others which are capable of detecting a polarization signal at parts per million (ppm) level. We have worked on a detailed theoretical calculation of the polarization observable from the Jupiter-like exoplanets. This will guide the existing instruments in framing observational strategies and will also help in the design of the future sophisticated instruments for detecting polarization from exoplanets. We published this work in the Astrophysical Journal (link given below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projection of a 3D planet on the sky facing us is a 2D disk (for example, the lunar disk) which is almost circular in shape. We developed a Python-based radiative transfer code (see Ref. 4) for the numerical simulation of the polarized intensity at each point on such a disk of a planet. We, then, calculated the total intensity by averaging this intensity over the disk, since we cannot resolve the planetary disk. The polarization of light from opposite hemispheres tend to be in opposite directions (see Figure 2). As a result, after disk averaging, the opposite polarizations tend to cancel out each other. This is why the disk averaged polarization from a star or a fully illuminated planet is close to zero. However, since the illuminated portion of the planetary disk varies with its phase angle (αorb; like when we see different phases of the Moon), the degree of polarization also changes. Polarization of the light reflected from a planet is maximum at half phases (α orb= 90o or α orb= 270o) and minimum at full phases (α orb= 0o i.e. when fully illuminated or αorb= 90o i.e. when fully dark). Another factor determining the degree of observable polarization is the orbital
inclination (i) of the planet (angle at which we view the orbital plane of the planet ; see Figure 1) i.e. whether the planetary orbit is at an edge-on view (transiting planets; i=90o), or at a face-on view (i=0o) or is at an intermediate angle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the traditional and popular methods such as Transit Photometry and Radial Velocity methods which can detect planets only if they are viewed almost edge-on, polarimetric method can detect and probe exoplanets orbiting with a broad range of orbital inclination angles. Hence, we can use this technique to detect exoplanets in future. Moreover, polarimetric studies can complement the other studies providing us with deeper insights into the structure of the atmospheres, especially about the clouds and hazes in the atmospheres as well as the surface features (for rocky planets) of the exoplanets. Using this powerful technique, we will be able to even detect liquid water on the surface of the exo-Earths in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more details, &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:aritra@iiap.res.in&quot;&gt;Aritra Chakrabarty&lt;/a&gt; can be contacted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac0bb7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Generic Models for Disk-resolved and Disk-integrated Phase-dependent Linear Polarization of Light Reflected from Exoplanets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Aritra Chakrabarty&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Sujan Sengupta&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA), Bangalore 560034, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/polarization-light-exoplanets-aritra</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/polarization-light-exoplanets-aritra</guid>
        
        <category>Exoplanets</category>
        
        <category>Polarization</category>
        
        <category>Planetary atmospheres</category>
        
        <category>Phase curves</category>
        
        
        <category>Earth and planetary astrophysics</category>
        
        <category>Review</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Using machine learning to infer Solar coronal heating</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This article traces the origins of the coronal heating problem, and describes in vivid detail our efforts in resolving this through machine learning. This is a non-technical article based on our paper, but references have been appended for the interested reader!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun is a spectacular celestial object that has captivated humanity for long and holds many unresolved secrets. It is a huge ball of gas, mainly made of hydrogen, but containing many other elements like Sodium, Calcium, Magnesium, Iron, etc. Generally, the Sun is seen as a disc in the sky. This disc of the Sun is known as “photosphere”, or the surface of the Sun. However, during a total solar eclipse when the Sun is hidden by the moon, streams of gas may be seen extending outwards from the photosphere as shown below. This faint region of the solar atmosphere is called the “Solar corona”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the 1900s, astronomers have been studying the Sun and various stars through the ‘spectrum’ of these stars. The spectrum of any star is basically the amount of light emitted at different wavelengths. Light as we know can be (for our purposes!) thought of as a wave, with the wavelength telling us, in some sense, how long each wave is. Stars produce light of various wavelengths, which is mainly controlled by its temperature at the photosphere. However, different elements in the atmosphere of stars can also give rise to “bumps” or “dips” in this spectrum, depending on how many electrons each element has. The number of electrons however depends on how “hot” the particular atom or ion is. Generally, the hotter an ion is, the fewer electrons it has. Hence, such bumps can be used to measure the temperature at various locations (and not just at the photosphere!) in the atmosphere of stars. This was the seminal contribution of Meghnad Saha and Cecilia Payne-Gaposchkin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Fig1_Vishal_Upendran.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig.1 - Image of the extended solar corona taken during an eclipse. Credit: Nicolas Lefaudeux.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on, astronomers analyzed the photosphere of the Sun, and found it to be at approximately 5500 K. In the 1940s, astronomers then took to analyzing the spectrum of the solar corona. Now, common sense tells us that as one moves away from a hot object, the temperature must reduce. Hence, we expect the solar corona to be at a lower temperature than the photosphere. However, astronomers found that as one moves from the photosphere into the solar atmosphere, the temperature initially drops and then starts rising to more than a million degrees Kelvin in the corona (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/105.6.32310.1093/mnras/105.6.323&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1086/12570410.1086/125704&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;)! The corona was found to be so hot, that elements like Iron, which generally have 26 electrons in their atoms, had lost more than 13 electrons! How does this occur?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been a long-standing puzzle with a deceptively simple answer. The simple answer is: common sense is correct. Only if one moves away from a hot object will one expect the temperature to fall. It would not be the case if, for some reason, heat is generated in the solar corona. This heat source keeps the corona hot and at a million degrees Kelvin. Then the question arises: What is this source of heat?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple guess can be made by looking at the Sun at the photosphere and in the corona. The picture below is taken from a suite of instruments called Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA) (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1007/s11207-011-9804-810.1007/s11207-011-9804-8&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; Helioseismic and Magnetic Imager (HMI), &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1007/s11207-011-9834-210.1007/s11207-011-9834-2&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;) on board the Solar Dynamics Observatory (SDO). SDO is a NASA satellite which observes the Sun predominantly in the photosphere and the corona. Think of it as an extremely complex camera (which it literally is!), taking pictures across different temperatures for scientists to study. The left image shows the map of the Magnetic field along the line of sight across the photosphere, with black and white representing negative and positive magnetic field polarities respectively. The grey areas have very weak magnetic fields, while the field is stronger if the color is blacker or whiter. On the right, we have the corresponding image of the corona, taken from AIA. Compare these two images carefully: it seems that the black/white areas from the magnetic field are located in the same regions as the bright areas in the corona. Hence it seems that the corona is brighter for regions with a stronger magnetic field. Might this be related to the corona’s temperature?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Fig2_Vishal_Upendran.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig.2- On the left, we have the magnetic field on the Sun’s photosphere, taken through HMI. On
the right, we have an image of the solar corona, taken through AIA. Credit: NASA/SDO HMI  and amp;

AIA.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was realized early on that the magnetic field of the Sun contains a lot of energy. This energy can, in principle, be used up to heat the corona. We now ask deeper questions: How does this occur? And how do we know this energy is enough to heat the corona?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more popular mechanisms of converting magnetic energy to heat is through “impulsive events”. Impulsive events are basically bursts of energy, where magnetic energy is dissipated as heat. The impulsive events, which convert magnetic to heat energy, are known to occur at a variety of length and time scales. These could be large or small and may last for hours or minutes, depending on how much energy was released. The large versions of these events, which release tremendous amounts of energy, are well known as solar flares. Many studies have been done on these large flares or on smaller events called microflares. The microflares, as the name suggests, have a million times less energy than the large flares. However, they are much more frequent in the corona. The hypothesis by Eugene Parker (in 1988) (&lt;a href=&quot;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/pdf/1988ApJ...330..474PAmerican&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;), and further expansion by Hugh Hudson (1991) (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1991SoPh..133..357H/abstract&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;) is that such impulsive events are much more frequent if they have low energy, and a combination of such events may maintain the coronal temperature. This is called the nanoflare hypothesis. It essentially translates to the hypothesis that one first needs to count the number of events that occur at each energy scale. Then, suppose one finds the total heat dissipated due to all such events at each energy to be larger for smaller events. In that case, impulsive heating is enough to maintain the solar corona’s temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studies generally attempt to count how many events occur at given energy and get a sense of how much energy is released in such events. Then, they compare if these energies are enough to maintain the corona at a million-degree Kelvin or not. Such statistics, however, are ridden with a grave fallacy: If individual events can be seen, we can count them. What if we cannot even see these individual events? What if all we see is a combination of a multitude of such events? This question has plagued solar physicists for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A possible answer to this question lies in “what in the corona do we see”. Studies are generally targeted towards the large, bright, and beautiful structures called Active Regions. In Fig.3, a picture of the solar corona is seen. Immediately, we can see that there is a bright region near the center, and this is called an Active Region. These active regions contain a large amount of magnetic energy which can be converted to heat. However, there are other regions in the corona where there are no beautiful large structures. These structures are known as “Quiet regions”.  Approximately every 11 years, the Sun is seen to wake up, become violent, and then go to sleep. This is known as the solar cycle. The active regions are predominantly seen when the Sun is active (the violence comes from active regions, mostly!). The solar corona, on the other hand, is hot even when the Sun is quiet and sleeping! This means we must study this “quiet time” to figure out coronal heating!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Fig3_Vishal_Upendran.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig.3- The solar corona as seen from the 211 A passband of AIA shows two distinct structures here. One kind of structure is the bright Active Regions, and the other is the background calm

Quiet Sun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our work, we addressed (or rather, incorporated) both of these characteristics to provide constraints on the viability of these impulsive events. First off, we took only the Quiet Sun data. All other large, dynamic events were left out. Second, we used a statistical impulsive heating model (&lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361:2006515210.1051/0004-6361:20065152&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;) to infer heating signatures. But how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter Deep learning (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deeplearningbook.org/&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;). Deep learning is a set of techniques (generally referring to neural networks) used to perform inferences on big data. These neural networks can “learn” the data given to them and perform any assigned task. When you check for translation of words on Google, it basically deploys deep learning in the background. The neural network used for such language-to-language translations has been trained on many statements and correspondences between two languages. Hence, when you ask it to translate words (or even sentences), it can translate pretty much very well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our work, we took the statistical impulsive heating model and made a large number of simulations. The impulsive heating model generates a time series of intensity (called light curves), given some free parameters. These simulations “statistically” would represent the light curves of the Quiet corona. However, there are no objective techniques to compare these simulations with observations in a statistically robust manner. Hence, we trained our deep learning model on mapping the light curves back to the free parameters. This is called learning an inversion code. The inversion code takes in the light curves, analyzes them in a highly complicated non-linear way, and gives out the best parameter set representing the light curve. The inversion code is checked on a “testing set” of simulations. Think of this whole procedure as attending a class (=training) and writing an exam (=testing). Since you typically do not know what questions will be asked in an exam, the testing set contains simulations that were not used for training. Hence, the performance of the inversion code is checked and validated in this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once this inversion code is checked, we apply it on approx. 3,00,000 light curves from the Sun to infer the free parameters. In this way, we circumvent the problem of not “seeing” individual events in the Quiet Sun  – we can infer their statistical signatures! This scheme is explained below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Fig4_Vishal_Upendran.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig.4 -A summary of our procedure. The simulated light curves are mapped to their parameters by training a deep learning model, which in our case is a Convolutional Neural Network. Then, these parameters can be inferred by feeding in the observed light curves in the model.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do we get from applying this elaborate scheme? We find the impulsive events occur at a frequency of around 2 events per minute. Each event lasts approximately 10-20 mins. Overall, we find smaller events to dominate over larger events, which seems to confirm the hypothesis of impulsive heating of the corona.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, we studied various properties of these heating events. First, we found that events can be either large and occur rarely, or be very small and occur frequently. This means that there exists a “well of energy”, that can be emptied by occasional large buckets or very frequent small buckets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we found that larger events die down much faster than smaller events. This counterintuitive result seems to arrive as a result of what is called thermal conduction. Thermal conduction is the reason why, if you leave the ladle for too long in the kadai, it gets very hot. Heat travels through metal efficiently, and makes it hotter. Hotter the kadai, the faster the ladle gets hotter. Similar phenomenon occurs in the corona, but here the ladle is the magnetic field lines, and the kadai is the impulsive event. The thermal conduction along magnetic field lines is very efficient, so the more the energy, the faster it is transmitted. We find signatures of this thermal conduction through our analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we find excellent correspondence between the properties of these small-scale events and large-scale events like solar flares. It almost seems like the small events we find are like younger siblings of the large-scale flares. And through a marriage of deep learning with solar physics knowledge, we can impose constraints on the heating of the solar corona!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/abf65a&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; On the Impulsive Heating of Quiet Solar Corona&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Vishal Upendran&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Durgesh Tripathi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Inter University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics, Pune, 411007, India&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/vishal-machile-learning-solar-corona</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/vishal-machile-learning-solar-corona</guid>
        
        <category>Solar physics</category>
        
        <category>machine learning</category>
        
        <category>coronal heating</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar and Stellar astrophysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Deciphering The Mysteries of The Quiet Sun Explosions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The outer atmosphere (the corona) of the Sun poses a long standing mystery regarding its tem-perature.  The solar corona is composed of plasma (ionised gas) that emits strongly in X-rays andultraviolet radiation.  Its temperature exceeds a million degree kelvin, while the visible surface (thephotosphere)  is  at  6000K.  One  of  the  theories  to  understand  the  so-called  ’coronal  heating  prob-lem’ proposes the occurrence of a large number of small scale explosions (known as microflares andnanoflares) on the Sun.  It is known that these flares are a manifestation of the magnetic field of theSun that is generated in its interior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/lakshitha_article1.png&quot; alt=&quot;A new image here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
Fig.1 - Caption to this image can be  used like this
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Sun’s magnetic field is not constant, it varies with anaverage period of 11 years, which is known as the solar cycle.  Approximately every 11 years, the Sun’smagnetic field reverses.  In other words, the north pole becomes the south pole, and vice versa.  The flip of the poles is an end product of the slow evolution of Sun’s magnetic field over time.  As the cycle progresses,  all of the Sun’s activities related to its magnetic field (such as sunspots,  flares,  coronalmass ejections) builds to a maximum (when the magnetic field reverses).  Then the Sun settles backdown to a minimum, before the whole cycle starts again.  The Sun was in a very low state of activityduring the minima of solar cycle 24 covering the year 2019.  It was in fact the quietest the Sun has been in the last 100 years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this quiet period of the Sun, at the mid of the year 2019, Chandrayaan 2 was launchedwith the several instruments/payloads to observed our moon and the Sun.  Among them CLASS is aninstrument to understand the abundance of elements present on the moon. But this requires knowledgeof the X-rays emitted from the Sun.  Thus, the orbiter also carried an instrument called Solar X-rayMonitor (XSM). XSM observed the Sun during its deepest minima of solar cycle 24, covering the year2019-2020 with a good temporal and energy resolution.  Using observations during this time, SantoshVadawale and his team has uncovered some fascinating information about the quiescent Sun.  Theyhave shown that during this period small scale transients, so-called microflares (smaller counterpartof the conventional solar flares) are occurring everywhere on the solar disk.Solar flares are eruptions of electromagnetic radiation of all wavelengths from the Sun.  They lastfrom a few minutes to a few hours.  Flares are classified depending on the energy they release during its  peak  in  the  soft  X  rays.   Though  the  number  of  large  flares  increase  with  the  progress  of  thesolar cycle, this study suggested that small flares, called microflares, keep exploding on the Sun at alltimes.  Though the definition of microflares has varied though the years due to the sensitivity of theinstrument, in this study flares having a peak flux below 10−8W m−2are considered as microflares.During this period of extremely quiet solar corona when no active regions were present on the disk,Santosh  Vadawale  and  team  identified  a  total  of  98  microflares  from  76  days.   The  microflares  aremarked in the lightcurve (Figure 1).  Most of the microflares were seen to behave similar to largerflares having a fast rise and a slow decay.  Some microflares did not follow this behaviour possibly1
due to blending of multiple microflares or they intrinsically have a different origin.  The temperatureand emission measure of these microflares are determined.  Temperature tells how hot the plasma getsduring the explosion while the emission measure gives an idea about the density of plasma emittedat that particular temperature.  The temperature is found to be between 3-6 MK and the emission measure is in the order of 1046cm−3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The  XSM  microflare  locations  are  identified  in  the  extreme  ultraviolet  images  obtained  fromNASA’s ‘Solar Dynamics Observatory’ and from the X-ray images obtained by the Japanese HINODEX-ray Telescope. Most microflares were seen to be associated with X-ray Bright Points. ‘Solar Dynam-ics Observatory’ HMI magnetograms were used to analyse the corresponding photospheric magneticfield.  They observed the microflares to be associated with magnetic bipolar regions having weakerfield strengths, which indicates magnetic reconnection happening at smaller scales (Figure 2).This is also the first statistical survey of X-ray microflares outside active regions.  By plotting thefrequency distribution of microflares, the team has given evidence for the hypothesis that small scaleheating events occur everywhere on the Sun and they contribute to coronal heating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Original paper:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/abf0b0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Observations Of The Quiet Sun During The Deepest Solar Minimum Of The PastCentury With Chandrayaan-2 XSM – Sub-A Class Microflares Outside Active Regions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Author:&lt;/strong&gt; Santosh Vadawale&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-authors:&lt;/strong&gt; N. P. S. Mithun, Biswajit Mondal, Aveek Sarkar, P. Janardhan, Bhuwan Joshi, AnilBhardwaj,  M.  Shanmugam,  Arpit  R.  Patel,  Hitesh  Kumar  L.  Adalja,  Shiv  Kumar  Goyal,  TinkalLadiya, Neeraj Kumar Tiwari, Nishant Singh, Sushil Kumar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First author’s Institution:&lt;/strong&gt; Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/lakshitha_solar_article_corona</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/lakshitha_solar_article_corona</guid>
        
        <category>sun</category>
        
        <category>corona</category>
        
        <category>x-ray</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar_Physics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to CosmicVarta</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Come join us on a journey which will take you to the world of stars, galaxies and beyond and feel enthralled by unlocking the mysteries of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 minutes to read&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-cosmicvarta&quot;&gt;What is CosmicVarta?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astronomy is truly a global subject. The boundaries between the nations, people, ethnicities do not exist for  astonomers. We all think of the entire humankind as one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, India is a country where astronomy is equated wih astrology by even the well educated individuals. This itself is a paradox, as the Indian civilsation has a rich history of astronomical observations and calculations (expand). It becomes necessary and a responsibility for profesional astronomers to present a platform where the authentic research being carried out is presented and discussed in language which a ‘non-expert’ individual can understand. Moreover, while high quality research is communicated through the  reputed journals, the students who are not dealng with he subject on a day to day basis might find it diiffuciut to grasp. We present &lt;strong&gt;CosmicVarta&lt;/strong&gt; as an online platform where we simplify the current astronomical research being carried out so that people from every background can grasp the essence of the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a group of Ph.D students, who all are working towards our doctoral thesis and through this platform, we want to share the astronomical  research being carried out by the Indian astronomers scattered all over the country. Another area where we’d like the users to utilize this platfomr is: career guidance in astronomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research in astronomy is pursued at only a handful of research insitututes, hence prospective studens may often find it challenging to find relevant information. Through this portal you may find information regarding the various career optiona available, various positions available at astronomy institues in india and the other necessary information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This portal will also serve as a information hub regarding various softwares and databases that are available to be used by the public for free. We can even help students who are  looking for short term projects using such huge volume of data by connecting with the scientists working actively in that area of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come join us on a journey which will take you the wonderful world of stars, galaxies and beyond; and feel enthralled by unlocking of the keys to the mysteries of the universe which the scientists are doing on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/welcome_to_cosmicvarta/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/welcome_to_cosmicvarta/</guid>
        
        <category>sun</category>
        
        <category>corona</category>
        
        <category>x-ray</category>
        
        
        <category>Solar_Physics</category>
        
        <category>popular</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to the website.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As an introduction to the website, let’s write a love letter to our intended audience, so that people get a feel about what this place is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-github-io.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/new_post/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/new_post/</guid>
        
        <category>tag1</category>
        
        <category>tag2</category>
        
        <category>tag3</category>
        
        
        <category>Cat1</category>
        
        <category>Cat2</category>
        
        <category>Cat3</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A sample post on this webpage</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As an introduction to the website, let’s write a love letter to our intended audience, so that people get a feel about what this place is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://beautifuljekyll.com/plans/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1472712739516-7ad2b786e1f7?ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;ixlib=rb-1.2.1&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=1050&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#(tentative)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://deanattali.com&quot;&gt;Vivek Kumar Jha&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quasar accretion disks&lt;/strong&gt; are very difficult to undestand owing to their larger distances and singificantly smappler angular resoultions on earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** Bold like this**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Italic like this&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;we-can-generate-our-own-toc-like-this&quot;&gt;We can generate our own TOC like this:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;Table of contents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#sponsors&quot;&gt;Sponsors 🏆&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#build-your-website-in-3-steps&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build your website in 3 steps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#plans&quot;&gt;Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#add-your-own-content&quot;&gt;Add your own content&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#customizing-parameters-for-each-page&quot;&gt;Customizing parameters for each page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#supported-parameters&quot;&gt;Supported parameters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#featured-users-success-stories&quot;&gt;Featured users (success stories!)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#faq-and-support&quot;&gt;FAQ and support&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#credits&quot;&gt;Credits and contributions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;embed-of-a-youtube-video&quot;&gt;Embed of a youtube video.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0Soqggmccxk&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;features&quot;&gt;Features&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://beautifuljekyll.com/updates/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What’s New?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to see the latest features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SIMPLE&lt;/strong&gt;: The primary goal of Beautiful Jekyll is to allow literally &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; to create a website in a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern&lt;/strong&gt;: Uses the latest best practices and technologies to achieve nearly perfect scores on Google Chrome’s Audit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile-first&lt;/strong&gt;: Designed to look great on both large-screen and small-screen (mobile) devices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Highly customizable&lt;/strong&gt;: Many personalization settings such as changing the background colour/image, adding a logo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible usage&lt;/strong&gt;: Use Beautiful Jekyll directly on GitHub or via a Ruby gem - choose the best &lt;a href=&quot;#build-your-website-in-3-steps&quot;&gt;development method&lt;/a&gt; for you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Battle-tested&lt;/strong&gt;: By using Beautiful Jekyll, you’ll be joining 50,000+ users enjoying this theme since 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SEO and social media support&lt;/strong&gt;: Customize how your site looks on Google and when shared on social media.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments support&lt;/strong&gt;: Add comments to any page using either &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.facebook.com/docs/plugins/comments&quot;&gt;Facebook comments&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://utteranc.es/&quot;&gt;Utterances&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://staticman.net&quot;&gt;Staticman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tags&lt;/strong&gt;: Any blog post can be tagged with keywords, and an index page showing all the tags is automatically generated.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analytics&lt;/strong&gt;: Easily integrate Google Analytics, or other analytics platforms, to track visits to your website.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photos support&lt;/strong&gt;: Any page can have a full-width cover photo and thumbnail.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSS&lt;/strong&gt;: An RSS feed is automatically created, so you can even host a podcast easily with Beautiful Jekyll.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-github-io.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copy&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/ketan_demo_article</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/ketan_demo_article</guid>
        
        <category>tag1</category>
        
        <category>tag2</category>
        
        <category>tag3</category>
        
        
        <category>Cat1</category>
        
        <category>Cat2</category>
        
        <category>Cat3</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A new post</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a new post. Let’s see where it goes.
We can add as many posts like this and they get updated automatically!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;header-1&quot;&gt;Header 1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a new post. Let’s see where it goes.
We can add as many posts like this and they get updated automatically!This is a new post. Let’s see where it goes.
We can add as many posts like this and they get updated automatically!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;header-2&quot;&gt;header 2&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a new post. Let’s see where it goes.
We can add as many posts like this and they get updated automatically!
This is a new post. Let’s see where it goes.
We can add as many posts like this and they get updated automatically!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;subheader-21&quot;&gt;Subheader 2.1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a new post. Let’s see where it goes.
We can add as many posts like this and they get updated automatically!This is a new post. Let’s see where it goes.
We can add as many posts like this and they get updated automatically!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;header-3&quot;&gt;header 3&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-github-io.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copy&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/welcome-to-jekyll/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/welcome-to-jekyll/</guid>
        
        <category>tag1</category>
        
        <category>tag2</category>
        
        <category>tag3</category>
        
        
        <category>Cat1</category>
        
        <category>Cat2</category>
        
        <category>Cat3</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Flake it till you make it</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Under what circumstances should we step off a path? When is it essential that we finish what we start? If I bought a bag of peanuts and had an allergic reaction, no one would fault me if I threw it out. If I ended a relationship with a woman who hit me, no one would say that I had a commitment problem. But if I walk away from a seemingly secure route because my soul has other ideas, I am a flake?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that no one else can definitively know the path we are here to walk. It’s tempting to listen—many of us long for the omnipotent other—but unless they are genuine psychic intuitives, they can’t know. All others can know is their own truth, and if they’ve actually done the work to excavate it, they will have the good sense to know that they cannot genuinely know anyone else’s. Only soul knows the path it is here to walk. Since you are the only one living in your temple, only you can know its scriptures and interpretive structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the struggle are two very different ideas of success—survival-driven and soul-driven. For survivalists, success is security, pragmatism, power over others. Success is the absence of material suffering, the nourishing of the soul be damned. It is an odd and ironic thing that most of the material power in our world often resides in the hands of younger souls. Still working in the egoic and material realms, they love the sensations of power and focus most of their energy on accumulation. Older souls tend not to be as materially driven. They have already played the worldly game in previous lives and they search for more subtle shades of meaning in this one—authentication rather than accumulation. They are often ignored by the culture at large, although they really are the truest warriors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A soulful notion of success rests on the actualization of our innate image. Success is simply the completion of a soul step, however unsightly it may be. We have finished what we started when the lesson is learned. What a fear-based culture calls a wonderful opportunity may be fruitless and misguided for the soul. Staying in a passionless relationship may satisfy our need for comfort, but it may stifle the soul. Becoming a famous lawyer is only worthwhile if the soul demands it. It is an essential failure if you are called to be a monastic this time around. If you need to explore and abandon ten careers in order to stretch your soul toward its innate image, then so be it. Flake it till you make it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;disqus_thread&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
    /**
    *  RECOMMENDED CONFIGURATION VARIABLES: EDIT AND UNCOMMENT THE SECTION BELOW TO INSERT DYNAMIC VALUES FROM YOUR PLATFORM OR CMS.
    *  LEARN WHY DEFINING THESE VARIABLES IS IMPORTANT: https://disqus.com/admin/universalcode/#configuration-variables    */
    /*
    var disqus_config = function () {
    this.page.url = PAGE_URL;  // Replace PAGE_URL with your page's canonical URL variable
    this.page.identifier = PAGE_IDENTIFIER; // Replace PAGE_IDENTIFIER with your page's unique identifier variable
    };
    */
    (function() { // DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE
    var d = document, s = d.createElement('script');
    s.src = 'https://cosmicvarta-in.disqus.com/embed.js';
    s.setAttribute('data-timestamp', +new Date());
    (d.head || d.body).appendChild(s);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;noscript&gt;Please enable JavaScript to view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/?ref_noscript&quot;&gt;comments powered by Disqus.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copy&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/flake-it-till-you-make-it/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/flake-it-till-you-make-it/</guid>
        
        <category>tag1</category>
        
        <category>tag2</category>
        
        <category>tag3</category>
        
        
        <category>Cat1</category>
        
        <category>Cat2</category>
        
        <category>Cat3</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Powerful things we can use on the website</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There are lots of powerful things you can do with the Markdown editor. If you’ve gotten pretty comfortable with writing in Markdown, then you may enjoy some more advanced tips about the types of things you can do with Markdown!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the last post about the editor, you’ll want to be actually editing this post as you read it so that you can see all the Markdown code we’re using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-formatting&quot;&gt;Special formatting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as bold and italics, you can also use some other special formatting in Markdown when the need arises, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;strike through&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;==highlight==&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;*escaped characters*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-code-blocks&quot;&gt;Writing code blocks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two types of code elements which can be inserted in Markdown, the first is inline, and the other is block. Inline code is formatted by wrapping any word or words in back-ticks, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;like this&lt;/code&gt;. Larger snippets of code can be displayed across multiple lines using triple back ticks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;.my-link {
    text-decoration: underline;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;html&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;li&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;ml-1 mr-1&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;target=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;_blank&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;#&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;fab fa-twitter&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;css&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-css highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.highlight&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;#999988&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;font-style&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;italic&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.highlight&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.err&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;#a61717&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;#e3d2d2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;js&quot;&gt;JS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-js highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// alertbar later&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;scroll&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;scrollTop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;280&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;.alertbar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fadeIn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;.alertbar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;fadeOut&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;python&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello World&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;Ruby&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-ruby highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'redcarpet'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;markdown&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Redcarpet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello World!&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;markdown&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;to_html&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;c&quot;&gt;C&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-c highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;printf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Hello World&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;walking&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference-lists&quot;&gt;Reference lists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quick brown jumped over the lazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to insert links in markdown is using reference lists. You might want to use this style of linking to cite reference material in a Wikipedia-style. All of the links are listed at the end of the document, so you can maintain full separation between content and its source or reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;full-html&quot;&gt;Full HTML&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the best part of Markdown is that you’re never limited to just Markdown. You can write HTML directly in the Markdown editor and it will just work as HTML usually does. No limits! Here’s a standard YouTube embed code as an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cniqsc9QfDo?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>/powerful-things-markdown-editor/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/powerful-things-markdown-editor/</guid>
        
        <category>tag1</category>
        
        <category>tag2</category>
        
        <category>tag3</category>
        
        <category>new_tag</category>
        
        
        <category>Cat1</category>
        
        <category>Cat2</category>
        
        <category>Cat3</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
